let's get started
uh so a couple uh Logistics uh before we
start uh so uh I do hopefully have been
in on the slack workspace uh We've
nailed down the time slots a lot of
times a lot for the section is down to
three time slots but you have to vote uh
so uh we're trying to find the time that
that's uh most suitable but uh uh well
thank you that appeal will not be able
to make the time but the sections will
be recorded uh and uh also
um you know if you uh you know the
office hours uh are posted in the
updated syllabus but that's more
flexible and uh you know
a question is an economic to my office
hour you can always always feel free to
next time sure
um
um okay so uh this lecture uh and the
next uh couple uh lectures will be about
lagrantian formalism
uh for uh fun mechanics
uh well this is a preparation for uh the
study of genuine Quantum field theories
um but uh you know actually a lot of the
technologies that were really
the most clearly explained in a simple
model mechanics which will do that
um which we'll do first
um so
um
[Music]
uh let's recall uh in uh classical
mechanics
[Music]
uh and then there's the hamiltonian
foreign
formalism
um
we can talk about uh the state of
classical system and again that is
characterized by the coordinates uh and
in time derivative of time uh I'm going
to most
um
could be some general coordinates for
Alpha Atomic index that went from one to
an if you have a system and equate the
freedom hopefully this is uh uh uh not
unfamiliar from classical mechanics
I think
uh but the point is the important things
in the state description
any questions about this yes
uh we have uh the state is
the alphas are uh the uh canonical
momenta uh conjugates to these two
um now in the case of uh uh you know
three particles a moving space
what's your momentum but if you can't
generalize coordinates then P into
quality some generalized motion is
hundreds of years
uh now
um
um so
and then we need to describe hand
Evolution and that's that's the job of
mechanics uh so uh the question uh the
timely Evolution will be characterized
by its own equation of motion
the action
um
action
uh probably you know oh no that's what
that means and
um okay uh in the hematology problem on
the other hand uh we can write the
equation of motion of any uh that I
expected that the time is derivative
because of Any quantity let's say f is
some uh
and the question is
brackets
um how many of you know when the person
bracket is
so for example uh
uh qdot is a pH live
yeah
um
uh okay so
uh let's see
and um now of course these two problems
uh are supposed to be equivalent for the
standard form of the lagrangian or the
hamiltonian so these are lagrangea
definitely is
they're related by
um
minus l
and this will be evaluated uh at um
the solution to the equation
could be out by the Alpha dot which is
the same at the position that the
extreme Idols to the right hand side
with the direct to computer
difference
uh so hopefully you have all seen this
before uh are there any questions uh
before we move to Quantum Mechanics
that's interesting a reminder of that
classical mechanics and the relation in
hamiltonian and laguential problems
any questions
okay yeah
um why is hamiltonian like P Alpha like
lower interest required
uh in what sense are they dual uh uh
good question so um uh one way just to
say is is because
the position bracket
uh so the Muslim bracket
which is
two changes and G until q and this is
defined to be uh because he might be
mentioned
Alpha minus uh the one with f and g
switch
um
imagine this
um uh and uh
to the structure of this hamiltonian
system uh in fact you know the the
hamiltonian system is only a Divine
provided that you specify that the
poisson structure which is parameters
now the point is that uh I think
probably in your uh you know freshman
mechanics course when you first learn
this kind of thing you start then you
start with it very quickly you are
LeBron James as a way to rewind
lagrangea LaGrange equation
um but once you're casting you no longer
need to think about the Q dots right so
so run your bonus of you as it's
familiar and if you do this is
Data System you've only talk about
computers
any other questions
uh all right so uh now let's talk about
mechanics
uh so now it's about quantum mechanics I
think
um so uh important mechanics
um
uh well usually probably more familiar
with the hamiltonian
um so uh
uh we have that was speak of the state
um let's say
uh kit so this is a statement very fun
builderspace this discarding age this is
the the Hilbert space
um of uh physical States
in a product and support
um and uh uh uh
you don't know and if you want to
um
promote a classicism component system
and through the procedure of
colonization and you uh and this H into
some operator and Page hat uh by
replacing p and Q with a p huge hat
um and you replace the bottom bracket by
probably the appropriate commentators
according to the economic communication
commutation
um
uh now um
so
um
and uh of course uh I do well no uh the
state can be specified equivalent
equality specified in terms of the wave
functions
um and then we can speak up I'm
evolution
uh
which is uh
um
characterized by a unitary operator
that's called a uh P that represents
time evolution by the amount of time T
and this can be written as individual
convention e to the minus I over H bar
the hamiltonian times
operator
um and uh of course um then you know
that there are two different ways to
Android time Evolution I'll show you the
picture uh in which uh the state
themselves uh transform the kind of
evolution but actually
viewer okay
um alternatively in the Heisenberg
picture which is uh more convenient for
most of our considerations
um I can break picture you post the
state fixed
and instead you evolve all the operators
uh the correspondent observables uh
under time Evolution uh conjugation so
operative o and the time Evolution get
transformed to all uh multiplying by
deleting on the right and the UT inverse
on the left
um and at this quantity I'm going to
design it to be o of P so instead of
talking about the state uh evolving in
time we'll be talking about operating
moving time these are the kind of
operators who's not in the state will be
our physical observatives
um and uh of course the consequence of
this
[Music]
um
we were here is a consequence of of this
uh
um it is a consequence of this that um
the time derivative
of this operator defining it this way uh
it's a easy uh computation
and this is the inside analog of that
equation uh just with the possible
bracket replaced by the commentator and
within factors I and h y
um okay so uh so that's a quick recap of
quantum mechanics in hematology problem
uh the state and time even though any
questions
okay so
um uh hopefully that's all familiar to
you uh and now let's discuss the uh
lagrangia
uh formism and quantum mechanics
um so another one you come to the
Quality mechanics uh
what is like one Republican point of
attendance how do you do that uh well
um uh this is uh
uh you know this is really done through
the pathogen
um
I think probably uh most of you have
seen the path we were before uh but uh
may not feel I'm not sure if everyone
feels comfortable with it so I'm going
to discuss this in some detail because
the pandemic was going to be an
essential tool in the formulation of
quantum field Theory uh and we're gonna
spend the time trying to uh you know to
be uh to be solid with this in one
mechanics and as you see it's actually
pretty untrivial even in very simple
amount of quantum mechanics and there
are many solarities associated with it
um which will which is why we're going
to spend a little time on that uh so in
order to form the quantum mechanics uh
through the lagrangian
um and we're going to work with the
action
uh this action is still of the possible
form so
um whenever we use the so you see uh in
the classical mechanics of course H and
L are both this functions of these
variables
um but in quantity candidates would like
to promote H to an operator there's no
operator that corresponds to the ground
here okay so the quantum mechanics of
lagrangea instead of the ground Gym
LaGrange is still a classical concept is
there some ordinary function no q and Q
dot still no difference uh all right
um
so uh uh so how do we do quantum
mechanics uh in this language uh well
the uh the claim is that um if you want
to characterize so first of all let's
start with that
um some basis of States let's say uh if
I write uh Q uh KET this means uh that
this is the is the
Q uh
um hat eigenstate
you know
um all right so this when I came out of
the Alpha Zone the operating this is
on the right hand side is the eigenvalue
is infected but operator can you think
of some particle
um and say uh
the simplest example of course
the positive examples would be this L if
we
um
potential describing
yeah um describing particle uh uh
properties and potential and moving some
potential and
um
the quantizer system you expect to have
some hamiltonian in the usual form
um the San Antonio would be
is the
uh
and a plus v
few hats
um and uh here I'm going to be talking
about the eigen state uh we're back with
two hat Market that's the usual story
but now I want to
formulate uh the system purely in the
language of the lagrangian without
appealing to the hamiltonian so how do
we do that
um
to do that
well first let me write on the formula
for the path integral
um
perhaps most of you have seen this
formula but we're going to go to its
derivation and discuss all right and
discuss how to use it
so
um we're going to be interested in The
Matrix elements of the time Evolution
operator in a sense uh this you know
because this queue basis will form this
complete basis of our Uber space in the
typical I mean simple I mean volume
system like like this uh if you
characterize all the Matrix Elemental
time you build operator you know
everything about the time evolution in
principle uh so here uh this uh
subscript I stands for initial and the f
is final so I have some initial State
and some final State these are state of
my arbitrary Choice okay so I'm not
saying that the state here I will evolve
into qf I'm not saying that at all I'm
just picking some arbitrary basis States
uh Qi there's qis these have eigenvalue
Qi Alpha with back to this operators
Cube I Alpha hat and these have some
eigenvalue Alpha we're back to this
queue
of a hat operator uh and this UT is the
time Evolution operator uh I was talking
about over there
it's pretty good capital T for the total
amount of time of evolution and again uh
let me remind you that we're going to be
working in the high temperature so and
the primary uh only operator is
gonna evolve according to that equation
over there the state will be how it's
based uh but in any case this the state
is the way this is some fixed record
number space and this we're just talking
about the Matrix elements of the time
Evolution operator
okay and the statements of that integral
is a representation uh it's a formula
like this it says that this thing is
supposed to be some kind of integral of
e to the I over H Bar times the action
uh this action is going to be
evaluated so I never wrote the limits of
the integral here uh so here in this
context there's action it's going to be
defined by integrated from zero to T DT
of L
so this is filled as a functional of uh
so this is
um as a functional
of a view of githat for T ranging
between uh zero and the capital T let's
say
um
and um so this s is viewed as a function
of the skill uh and we're going to going
to be perform an integration over the
space of functions uh Q of T whatever
that is
um what is an appropriate measure which
we'll discuss
and the subject the boundary condition
that Q uh at the initial time which is
equal to zero is equal to Qi and Q at
the final time which is a equal to qf
and that's at least heuristically is how
what the pathway is supposed to be and
what it does for you
uh any questions about this
yes
uh well how would you promote lagrangeas
to an operator uh there's no there's no
rule for what you do with that
I can tell you a function of the
canonical variable cubes and teams and
the rule is to promote the queue that
people operators and replaceable bracket
with accommodate
the textbooks there are no rules avoided
with two jobs and they did we don't do
anything with it you simply say that
once you have promoted excuse MPS to
operators the time Evolution indicated
by this this equation which is an analog
of a straightforward analog positive
questions if you buy the appropriate
versions
but it's not obvious uh problem
to coupon mechanics this classically
what you do is extremise them with
action right so so we want to find the
quantum analog of that and and as you
might know have heard of the quantum
analog of that is instead of two
instead of extremizing the action you
want to uh
integrate into that
action or into the io British bar and
action with some appropriate measure
now this uh so how many do I have seen
this formula I've written here
okay how many people know how this is
derived
is likely not quite correct
um in fact if you think about it
um uh how can this really be how can
this be exactly be true uh since
um you know
you know ambiguities when we promote uh
the class we haven't turned into the
bottom we have to tell you right there's
operators to worry about in general so
this Edge could be something
um and uh you know it doesn't have to be
uh simple like that for example if you
take the lagrangian of a 3D Rigid body
and try to come here for that it's not
of that simple form and um uh and in
fact you will have to uh in that case
you know this quadratic Terminal B was
some cooperation that depend on Q
operation
uh so who tells you what the operator
wonder you should be using
now in this Library there is a speaker
so it sounds like there's some ambiguity
that's it's not there is about this
there is another problem
information
uh yes
yes for example
um yeah I mean you know yeah and you
know generally uh it's always possible
to actually some operative order H bar
and some small coefficient and limit
zero that we would just go away you know
all the uh quality ambiguity are going
to be of that form just by demanding you
know it if I take uh some you know
polynomial expression let's say in p's
and q's and people be having two hands
there are many different ways of water
just when you make the result is her
Mission doesn't fix the answer at all
foreign
[Music]
um
uh the cubes themselves
uh and then that's generally going to be
the case
um uh and uh so so you know
we're gonna transformed into the
hamiltonian you'll also find the
quadratic term in the piece uh we'll
have some coefficient that depend on the
cubes
all right
um yeah uh uh after all uh that would
not be the case because there is no if
you have a really rigid body right
there's no potential there's a bunch of
companies zero and the whole thing is
just a kinetic term so you cannot
possibly be something like just you know
some of Cuda squared you know because as
you might know the actual rotational
motion but pretty pretty rotating 3D
Rigid body it's not so Criminal
um okay any other questions
okay so as I said uh in Vermilion
classical system the quantum system and
Hamilton there can be some ambiguity
after all I'm always free to add some
for the page terms for the hamiltonian
nobody can stop me from doing that and
the informally the limit with respect to
zero I'll reduce the same classical
hamiltonian a quantity of course are
different systems uh where would this
kind of ambiguity come from in the uh
lagrangian formalism uh well to
understand that uh well uh you know you
just need to go back and look at the
derivation and see what is wrong with
derivation and of course
um there's some uh maybe the element in
the room is you know what what the heck
is this thing here all right so so we're
going to spend some time discussing that
we're going to revisit or introduce the
derivation of this one
we're going to discuss
um uh what is a measure is or how you
should understand it and that's uh in
some sense where all the suddenly is
hidden uh and uh um there's the zombie
that goes into how you define this
measure is related to the issue with the
so-called regularization uh
regionalization kind of terms and all
that all these things together it really
all has to do with how you define this
measure foreign
make sure
um okay so let's review so we're going
to look at the time Evolution from zero
to time C and I'm going to divide this
and so uh with many slats
um uh and uh that's all we're here seven
times zero we are starting with the
state uh who's uh that is I guess they
went back to the Cubes but you had
argument is Qi we end up with the state
when I United Nations are so the
position where the coordinates move from
Qi to qf
um and uh yeah we're going to at every
type of time Evolution we're going to
insert a complete basis associated with
some
um uh position United States with the
positive q1 and Q2 and Q3 uh and some
support in terms of the explicit formula
and what we'll do is that we're going to
take this Matrix elements of the time
Evolution operator
I'm going to rewrite this importantly in
one way
so the uh let me use capital D for the
number of degrees of freedom and the
number of cues so if you want
um
the the Hue uh n minus one so here I'm
assuming that their end of this time
intervals are equally spaced in time so
this is T divided by n
Okay so
um
Evolution I'll just write an explicit
form of the appendicular version
operator e to the minus sign over H bar
uh
by the amount T Over N that represents
this step of the time Evolution and then
I'm inserting this Q uh n minus one okay
uh and then we have
two minus one
and so on support and finally we have a
q1
uh
okay so this is of course the identity
uh so far this is I've not made any
approximation
um
uh and uh and so there's more
convenience of notation uh let me uh
Define this could be qn and this Qi I'm
gonna call it q0 so I can write a more
uniform expression or this is equal to
uh integral of a product of the few
little n little n random one so
n minus one two
in plus one minus transportation
are there any questions about this
foreign
okay so
um let's uh let's look at this
expression over here
uh so that expression over here
uh this is one term by itself can be
written in that I'm gonna insert a
complete basically like these and that's
right uh V uh D and uh there's some
standard normal addition factor to Pi H
Bar D
um
now this is due to uh monolithic
convention for the standards momentum
basis which you probably all have seen
many times
Q then plus one so I'm really insert in
here uh p n
r uh but the normalization is such that
integral of the cube
Q
the one the insertion is is a factor of
time which part is
a convention it's such that the Q of an
a is going to be into the I which are a
few thoughts
um
any questions about this
so I I so far I haven't still haven't
done anything this is just all kind of
identities I'm just rewriting the whole
thing to this integral and the term in
this product itself is a situation in
the end in this one
any questions
so this as we said is uh this is the
wave function of the
State uh the the
end so this is the wave function the
same way
sorry well this is q a dots PN
Alpha indices
okay that's still exact uh this is the
the point where we're going to uh make a
approximation
so
um uh well there are several various
ways to to think about this so for
example
um so I think of uh and
goes to Infinity
and large
Over N we're talking about the Matrix
elements of um
one minus
H bar which has a over n
completely
over and squared
it's
all right
um now
um
uh if you're as far
uh if you write H bar in terms of p's
and q's let's say moving on the B is the
left and Q to the right of course you've
got something simple like this you don't
have to worry about ordering but more
generally uh the p's and q's are not
convenience in h and you have to you can
always rearrange the order
um uh in some way uh and if you play it
in order please activity
on the left the keys are on the right so
you can take the B10 to the to the left
to the Q is the act to the right you'll
get the argument
so uh so then uh in that case you can
write this guy as
uh as uh B
uh Q uh well
so so the the overlapping in this is he
brought into the cube that is just e to
the minus I on British bar p n starting
with q n
um sometimes
um uh one minus I over H bar h e n q n
what's up
uh so far so good
any questions
I've taken that into account so so in
other words when I write this H without
the Hat what I mean is that I take this
hat okay
I moved yeah I moved a piece of that
because the right I can get some
combination commentators but the
computers again themselves against the
same very range but you always reduce
numbers every time you commute at the
end of the day you can always write a
chat the operator in the form of
products of B hat and two Hardware P hat
is always on the left if you have always
in that form you replace
and that's the thing I'm calling this
page
so this handle
so now this might give you the both
impression that there's some Secrets
ordering we're on the pieces to the left
right actually there's no such sacred
ordering uh you you'll see why why
that's the case but so far uh that's why
thank you
all right
um so uh to uh summarize uh this whole
thing here uh can be so this everything
in the integrand is back to the DN here
uh can be written as
um
[Music]
let's bring these three things together
I have PM starting with q n plus one
minus q n
maybe I have that uh and I'm going to
rewrite this in the form of explanation
uh as minus h of p n uh n and times T
Over N uh Plus on the highway returns
which I will not
be worried about in a moments why do I
want to write as an exponential is
because the exponential uh will behave
simply on your product so now if I take
this and just multiply them together
turn that probably into sum of the
exponents so that's it will be easier to
manipulate it yes yeah sorry again
uh yes so let me give you an example so
let's say uh you have a term uh Q has a
p hat and Q okay
so once I have done this
by a spot bar and now I'm good so if you
had x to the left it because
Q half x to the right except q u n uh
and then and end up with just some
numbers
so this is now the the term uh if I
replace
[Music]
I'm assuming that uh for the moment
although um I mean you know you could
generate the school on to the Taylor
series
standard
any other questions yes
so how are you like moving the machine
side effects oh all I'm saying is that
uh you know if I take this whole thing's
words uh is going to be you're gonna
swear this so that's not also going to
be up 100 here it's work and so all I'm
saying is that if I replace this one
minus this thing by e to the minus this
thing I'm only making mistake of order T
Over N squared but I mean I made that
mistake to begin with anyway so I'm not
going to worry about that but the reason
that I'm not going to worry about that
really is because later on I'm gonna do
the sum and take a little bit n to a
minute uh all right so for now of course
you cannot drop this term you drop this
term you you're changing the answer
um but uh the claim is going to be for
this climate where they will bring us up
but the client is going to be that in
the limit this capital N Go to infinity
and you can actually ignore this or
ignore this
um but we'll see whether that's really
good
yes
normal
ah uh uh good uh well the thing is the
prescription I gave you so far right you
can work with any age cat I'm just
telling you some way to to to produce
this page out of it I didn't say this H
is the naive pathway expression
uh but I said no I was saying that uh
you know and they're given the classical
system there's no reason why the
so-called quantization has to be unique
there's no a correct reason why there's
a unique the quantum systems that reduce
the cost is between the concepts
any other questions
yeah it's whatever you're just
explanation could be easier to deal with
like the multiplicative that's right I'm
about to do that
uh okay so that's the now
it also works if you have no potential
uh I mean
Q hats and uh
look for essentially any Hamilton
uh but uh for most our purposes uh we're
going to be restricting ourselves to
like around your system with the two
derivative kinetic terms in which case
hamiltonian will always be quadratic in
p uh but the dependent on Q is arbitrary
foreign
okay so let's collect this together so
so this is measurement of the tiny
motion operator is now equal to the
integral uh product little n from one to
capital N minus one the qn to the n and
product again from zero to ten minus one
e and actually there's one extra in the
B compared to the Q as you might see
here
minus two n minus h q n d n
discovered in that way and plus some
terms of other e Over N squared
now
what you see here
going on potentially with ordering so if
I started with some classical H remote
to H hat and but then both in this
procedure this age might different from
the classical expression by something
called H bar just like this here so uh
in principle uh you know if you just use
some naive classical expression there
could be some other H bar correction
that could that could be there but for
the reason I have a snap
there's something to keep in mind
okay
um so uh now
um
okay so if you are a great physicist
like fireman you would uh formally take
the angles to Infinity limit
if you do this in the calculus path of
the class but uh but that's right
um
um uh well we would like to write this
uh and uh in this limit uh you you might
imagine there's qns and pins uh turned
into uh functions of uh the ability
um and um so this
this measure here uh there's something
that instructs you how to integrate over
the space of Q centps as functions
availability
so I'm going to write this as V of Q or
sometimes be a community
but let me surprised that this is
function so
um it's some kind of equation measure
um and let's look at this uh this
exponent
this exponent uh well
um formerly the limit Capital angles
still goes to Divinity uh anything here
is going to be uploaded by N squared
multiplied by the sum well the sum has n
terms and so uh you think now you'd
expect that that people to drop out uh
in the limit uh and go into Infinity uh
and uh and then what are you left with
well
um
uh so uh where that's where it is I over
H bar
um the sum is going to be a
approximation of integral uh the
integral in DT uh from zero to faculty
um and this is going to turn into uh T
at T QT
Dot why is that uh well you know let's
say the step a little end horizontal
time T but then this is approximated by
P of T and this is just the integral of
Q Dot and P over that very small time
step so that's something
it is to become that at least provided
this p n and qns are suppose if that
really Equalization of some uh you know
sufficiently smooth looking function
then this will be true
is
something we'll have to worry about
potentially uh and the second term here
will just be well this is just the Over
N is like you see this reference into
minus h of
foreign
okay so um this is uh formerly the uh
doesn't really know anything the
hamiltonian form of the passenger
formed
of uh with happiness
um
okay so let me make a few comments about
this
um
so as you have seen already
uh so how do we actually make sense of
this instruction well one way to make
centimeters because we go back to that
but really in so far that's how easy
right that's the only thing we know
um so uh you should think of this
uh well this this is right here let's
say this
all right when it comes dropped
um as the true definition at this point
of this pattern right so this is in some
sense a regularization so this is uh
sometimes referred to other than that is
regularization
so
um
uh so
in order to
uh to Define
the the functional measure
requires typically requires
uh regularization
that is uh we don't
really know April and how to integrate
over the space of the functions and
that's not something you learn in the
Calculus class
um when we typically do is to try to
um we can understand this as a do that
some kind of limit that is with for
example we can prefer discretize time
into these steps and we integrated with
each and cues at each uh time step so
that that's uh just going back to the
original formula
uh there are other ways to regularize
which might be more convenient for
project computations and but then you
have to understand what the sense their
equivalents which is not uh which is by
no means obvious
so so what we have done so far is to uh
discretize
uh
um
uh now
um another comment is that uh so okay
but maybe you might say that you know
once you do that you kind of you can
offset
um now of course up to up to that point
it was a true derivation but the last
step there was a bit of 10 way we
started young here
um so you could easily imagine uh some
alternative way to to do this
regularization
um
uh for example
uh you know for example uh what do you
record okay so when we recognize not
only we have to if we didn't say if we
discipline not only we have to replace
and measure by something like that we
also have to turn this expression and
the exponent here into some of this
great sum
uh now we said that okay this guy is an
approximation of this
but who says this has to be PN not b n
plus one
well the way we derived it was indeed PM
uh but if I only stare at this analog
expression uh and I want to guess how to
regularize it how would I know it's the
N is going to be in plus one or the
average between plus one or some other
something else well you don't
okay so that's the problem
um so there seems to be a bit of
a bit of you
uh well well we'll see that this
ambiguity is um uh sometimes a feature
not a bug
[Music]
and I will be able to resolve we'll be
we'll be able to figure out a way to to
resolve uh this ambiguity but in some
sense the part the value resolvements
and beauty is part of the definition of
important Theory from the planning open
review
um so
um in fact uh
uh there's a little bit of discussion I
wrote in the lecture notes that I will
post after the class that I will not
write on the board here which is that it
will turn out that if you you could have
replaced uh you could have repeat the
same direction
um
by
uh
you could have repeated the same
derivation
um
uh with uh
uh
let me see
um exchange if you you could have
repeated the derivation exchanging the
rows of the PS and cubes
um and um in which case uh you see uh if
you exchange the role that p's and q's
uh here Q here and P over here you want
to order you know in this page uh you
want to you want to remove the QQ has to
the left and you have to write after
ordering it as this so in which case you
end up with a with different expressions
for this uh for this age of p and the qn
uh and if you actually do that uh you
end up with something like the TN plus
one here
[Music]
uh the point is that that can be viewed
as a different regularization of the
path integral but it's different
regularization would only be the correct
answer of the time Evolution uh provided
by this this age actually different from
your organization by something of water
H bar
so there's some uh
potentially the order is far
ambiguity uh in here that depends on how
you write about X
uh so let me just write this in words
um so so here press h this contains
uh other h-bar antibodies
um which are
they're tied to the that we would
usually call the scheme of
regularization
is in
so the currency in the present example
the spring and seeing just have to go
with how you break that break down this
into the discrete steps and supporting
the B somewhere insert the cubes
um
um and so if you choose April I choose a
different version of the skin you might
end up with uh in order to produce the
same physics you might have to use a
different age the difference uh by
something like other H bar
the difference is uh called color chart
area
literature
yeah um when you say regular
organization like even giving a measure
to that thing uh I mean both no there's
a there's some measure which eight right
is ill-defined uh I would need to uh
both need to turn this into
um a find limits of integral like like
that one so I could there are other ways
to to to to alternatively integral this
is one way of doing it
um where this is discretizes time uh and
uh but once you do that uh the excuse
and beats are going to be you know
instead of uh continuous it's not a
function to P then now there's a large
set of discrete variables so that might
say the variables uh you also have to
express this in terms of those variables
all right so so when you do that there's
some small ambiguity
now please and you get this amazing to
be a significant level for each bar but
uh they will match it
so of course this Integrity you don't
encounter your undergrading from the
times plus because in icon back it
always starts and you don't never say
one you can't you always start by
writing that one hand however it
actually is once you have the operator
there'll be there's no ambiguity that's
fine uh the only reason I hear when you
have music is because we insist on
formulating in terms of lagrangea why
bother now in a number of these quantum
mechanics is not too important to use
the lagrangian and we don't have to use
our ground if we don't like this and you
don't have to worry about it which is
pretty much which is probably why that
you know you have some of you have seen
the category but you don't really know
so much or care about the derivation
because you don't actually need it in
the simple quantum mechanical models
um the reason that we're going to be
using this kind of problem
is because the lagrangea has equivalent
to have an advantage uh it's easier you
know I'm going to open them to uh to
preserve and passively symmetries such
as the pancreation
so in the hamiltonian formism as I have
been moving into the last lecture is
rather uh the the Commerce symmetry is
obscure uh and uh uh you know what not
only that it's obscure it's not easy to
build the correct communion that has
um that has uh relativism causality
because it just got some generic
interaction terminal hamiltonian the
publishing signal will be instantaneous
as in the case in the generic uh quantum
mechanical models
[Music]
Theory uh and one of the key criteria is
that uh you know we have to respect the
rules of speculativity
um and uh it's possible to work in terms
of organism but it's it's not easy uh
and uh to some extent is easier than the
price you have to pay because you have
to worry about organization and common
terms
uh it's going to be a part of the uh
definition uh you know how you result
ambiguity as I said earlier should be
viewed as a part of the definition of
the quantum theory in this moment
uh now uh in
if you don't have any additional
physical principles like symmetries and
so forth then generally there is no
principle to tell you how to choose the
term of what HR and have it done
um in practice you always determine that
by some additional physical input uh it
turns out that Hungary symmetry
particularly this I mentioned last time
which is a very strong constraint it's
not obvious this moment but we'll see
later on that um uh it's very strongly
strength then very often for large class
the quantum field theories help you to
pronounce goodies down to finally many
possible parameters
yes
yes if you uh that that's right that's
the thing I was you can put the videos
there and insert the cues here right so
I think you can kind of try to do that
and that's presenting the thing I was
measuring if you do that you'll actually
use a different wondering
and why
wow so I I think your question is why is
lebronianism uh why does it why is it
easier to preserve this imagery no it's
not why
it seems
uh well I'm not uh it is a user-friendly
thing I mean it is possible to to
computer without every time I look
around here
it is possible uh it uh slightly less
convenient for the purpose of
perturbation period and things like that
but it's absolutely possible to discuss
that without whatever yes sure so in
that case
yeah
but what I'm trying to say is that um
I haven't discussed in detail what what
is the the company I mean
the point is that uh it's uh
it's hard to write out the correct I
will tell you
uh it's hard to know what this important
they are into the many you know in
tournament right most of them don't work
and most of them will lead to an
inconsistent varies with the uh
super numerals and you have to know
exactly whether you can buy including
terms sometimes
yes are there issues with their
derivation if we choose for C to go to
Infinity
um
that uh depends
um you could say that you sometimes uh
typically this left hand side is the
field defining that limit in some in the
hospital
thing and this is
fine so we don't like to take that limit
however uh
um we will take elements of
um well later will be interesting
elements where you can take the
imaginary part of field of definitely
sense that that will have some use but
for so far the time people say it's in
real time and that we do not want to
take the time but we will imagine times
yes
I'm gonna come to that next I'm about to
schedule it out please I haven't
discussed that yet
okay so so now let me uh carry on one
more step because so far I haven't
connected this to lagrangement yes and
this is still the hamiltonian uh but uh
but that's just one more step
um okay so uh if H uh DQ
is quadratic
uh
uh for example in our
in this case
like this
but then
obviously and
well this intro looks like a Galaxy in
fact if you stare at it uh it's a it's a
conversation with the slightly awkward
um
uh
coefficient which is uh which is
imaginary
um but we're going to uh not worry about
that too much at the moment we'll come
back to that
um so
um uh if you choose
you know the correct uh Contour
integration
um at least you'll be able to uh to
perform the integral as a Galaxy
integral
um and uh the results of that uh
gaussian integral
um
yeah the result of the Galaxy integral
is uh is going to be well if you think
about some
and that's why let's give you some
network uh and if you have some
additional uh
TV times something else sometimes
um then you can always complete the
square
um and uh uh then you just get uh the
the same uh number where you don't have
to multiply by the e to the exponents
that extreme lines would be back to T so
um
let me just uh write this in your
formula
um so if Pages were not impede we can
integrate
um
uh and then we're going to be left with
digital with the queue uh well
um you have to be a little bit careful
here because
um you know generally uh there's a
there's a factor so let's say your first
time we're not there you just have this
P Squared this question
um there's uh
uh more generally uh if uh this
coefficient here if this work comes
resolution that only depends on Queue
um integrating out the peak by the
gaussian equal will give you a factor
that depends on Q
uh so that factor will be correcting
this measure so I'm going to now use the
notation uh with that with a bracket
just to remind ourselves that
um
that there's some uh correction to the
measure factor and when you iterate that
P if you think about it it's uh you know
this thing is a uh it's not something
that you have to you have to be a little
careful about so for example
um you know the graduate system or or
the piece the cues which are sort of the
canal granites
um there is no uh there's some Freedom
intrusive to kind of components there's
like the sound of Freedom you're truly
in the general it's coordinates I can
rescale Q by factor of two at risk of P
by a factor one-half
in which case uh this measure will stay
the same if I you know your CLP and Q
are but if by individual P this thing is
no longer invariant underestating of Q
by Factor two uh so you have to worry
about it the normalization how this
measure is required but if you get
confused you can always go back to this
expression and remember the narration
and you can recall how this measured
okay anyway so the point is that after
you integral RP uh you have some uh this
measure against a correction and then
you have into that this expression here
uh now
um after continues Square uh LP by the
gaussian so you'll be adapted with uh
this exponent here extremise went back
to uh
DT
equal to the obstacle minus h
that's the thing over there
um but now I'm going to extremise this
with record B so that is said the
derivative of this is equal to zero that
is Q dot is equal to two
now you can take
this quality
this is uh uh sort of the recycling the
inverse Lagana transform that relates to
hamiltonian back to the ground earlier
about this
let's make a problem this
team is the sequel to the LeBron James
right so uh so with that we end up with
a LaGrange form of the pattern that is
we have uh
element of time you build an operator
which is an integral over a q of P equal
to the ACT e to the I over H Bar times
the action this thing this whole thing
is that it says e to the time over H bar
that's correct that's correct
um uh if it's not uh then uh then you
have to you have to worry
um but um
you know all the kind of standard
mechanical systems are of that one uh so
at that level is okay uh but more
generally uh it's it's something
and second question so when when do you
write this modified measured are you
still speaking
um like modified I like some some um
so here you know there's some factors
depends on and for example
whose organization
[Music]
that's right that's right so foreign
and last thing I was wondering on this
is that when we integrated over the
screen how did that resulting up in Kobe
T dot equals DHCP if we didn't
exclusively write that down
uh
wait are you asking uh how do I know
this the worst information
no right
this is just two right I mean uh you
know the result of integrating RP uh up
to this councilman factor
is that it's going to be
minus B squared
this okay so the way you can compute
this is by completing the score you
write this in here as a minus Square
well my question was is that we always
had to do that because
foreign
we always have that or is it or are we
oh no no no no no you see over here uh p
and Q are independent variables right
there's no relationships right so that's
right so the queues and these are
independent variables are integral over
in this in this form so so over here
there's no really
eliminated
and what you can say here is that
you know the result of integrating this
thing in PMP
factor is given by the detail this
exponent
the same thing but just extremise went
back to here
so I'm thinking that this explaining
here and extremising effectively
it's really easy it's just some
quadratic uh functionality and
extremising that would like to be right
the result what is the result of that
well uh well first of all this is what I
mean by distance
I'm taking this object and I I demand
that it's first folded American without
a zero that is Q naught minus
important
uh
because once we integrate
um that's right so so uh yeah
like this I completely square and uh
have this and uh have some individual uh
and now I can always
change variable the feed by shifting a p
by this whatever it's sitting over here
and that becomes standard gaussian
people does that give you whatever
factors
and then I'm back over with this but
here which is the result you get by
let's remind this expression
okay
yes
um if you want to view the pathway or
some kind of fundamental principle uh uh
you know you might think that that
display attention is just some uh
particular way to make sense to you know
new language to recognize the packages
um uh and uh and indeed uh you know if
if we start with just knowing the
lagrangian and we don't know what
hamiltonian is and uh precisely as an
operator uh then uh you know if you
write the path of the world you have to
figure out a way to make precise sense
of it I want to make sense of it is to
do this this realization we'll see that
it's not the only way to make sense of
it there are other ways that are more
useful for product computations
um but whatever way you choose to
realize it uh there might be some
ambiguity for the h bar
that plus
no that that step is is fine but that
doesn't have anything to do with this
ambiguity uh except uh that sometimes if
this coefficient here depends on Q then
you have to worry a little bit about how
you normalize this measure
um we will see uh how this is treated in
practice
um in fact that uh in a way is uh can be
understood also in terms of discounted
costs so that that's uh that's something
we'll understand uh in some examples yes
what exactly are we taking deep feed
like what are we okay that that's a very
good question that's a very good
question there's a side of a hand and I
see that I didn't get away with it uh
um
um so
um if you wish uh yeah so that's any of
the any kind of questions are like that
you always have to go to uh you know
through the regular history where this
integral is actually defined so for
example if you do this then uh then then
you can literally stare at this
expression now you're integrating that
measure energy yeah there's a yes
so that that you don't have it but like
the particular n goes to Infinity right
now we're I guess integrating over hit
the number of differentials which seems
so defined uh uh well you're instructed
to do this tutorial first and then take
into Infinity but that's how the
regulation is supposed to work right uh
and the otherwise you you'll be not
doing anything so so you want to first
uh um this retire in some way so to make
uh this would have a Time variable maybe
uh later we'll see if we can have the
first way transform and and then play
some cut off on the player notes
um that's something else you can do
um and uh after you do that
regularization uh you now have a well
defined in the world then you can
perform anything then hopefully you can
pay the limit back to the end to
Infinity uh and hopefully the results
would make sense and if describes actual
visual system of Interest
uh
uh okay uh I guess I'm out of time
I only managed to go get through half of
it
uh and the the issue is that we probably
have to we don't have to delay the
Commerce because we're gonna uh but what
was it uh
it's good to be it's good to be uh you
know slow and uh and more have more
discussions
okay
thank you
um
[Music]
what's up
um
is
[Music]
so I I take this I thought something
about this here
is
foreign
[Music]
okay uh there are more uh useful
homework yeah we're gonna spend a lot of
time for the rest of this uh
um
[Music]
thank you
injury
um
foreign
[Music]
plus whatever value is at the minimum
so then we so the first part when we
integrate over P minus something squared
the exponential of that respect to P are
constant because it's a calcium
vegetable we just bury that into DQ oh
there's another part that's left over
there
yeah
minimum of the
um
something
yeah
NOTE END VIDEO 96lN2omwit4
NOTE BEGIN VIDEO 2: uzixOflp0tY (2022-09-08)
NOTE JSON3 SHA-256 c0f71bfb5af7324d8daadbddfb855ad7911068f78df9845b2b34a7bc2ff8b623
NOTE VTT SHA-256 9a6a84d1072468e4f3f4d295d961023f452f47d9b581fbe7c09fef4acc8a928c
Kind: captions
Language: en
uh first of all the second time has been
decided to be Fridays uh 10 30 a.m in
the same room here
um and uh we understand that uh from the
poll that's not exactly everyone can can
make it but we'll report it and uh uh
and also Alex will go to the office hour
afterwards at two to three p.m on
Fridays uh in uh Jefferson 453 the seven
room upstairs
further questions after the section if
you go uh Billy's office hour
um and um uh the first uh problem set
has been posted is in the homework
Channel um slack
um uh you know you don't need to look at
now in fact some of the stuff will make
more sense after today's lecture
um I should say that uh the problems uh
look pretty long but it was mostly the
statement that try to guide you through
the problems so it's actually a lot
longer the better because
taking out the convention and explain
what you need to do
um and um you know if you if you happen
to be if event is scary and they don't
know what to do it shouldn't worry
um you know we're here to to help you to
guide you through this you know once you
understand the physics the actual
problems are actually pretty trivial um
like 90 of doing physics is to
understand how is that the calculation
you know and most of the time once you
understand exactly what they do the
actual calculation is pretty easy at
least the not the way that these
problems don't do that uh so so don't be
scared but I do uh encourage you to look
at it right away after the class
um don't wait till last minute
also it's due on Tuesday
um the reason uh usually you won't make
it bi-weekly but uh this problem said is
actually despite the land of the
statements actually on the shorter side
so so we want to make it do you want you
on Tuesday
um and uh uh but you know as I said
don't come with your last week yes
the text source for the Primitive yeah
uh uh sure uh do you prefer looking in
the attack than PDF
so we can like fight the solutions uh oh
uh uh sure but but yeah
but the other thing everyone use paper
snack for us it's not exactly the same
time
maybe not inconvenient but anyway I I
can see
okay
so uh
um so so let's start with uh uh with the
physics
um so last time I uh introduced the time
in the world people can find the
mechanics
um and um now I'm going to discuss uh
how you would use this probabilism to
study some observables uh that uh
captures uh you know physical quantities
of Interest such as the energy spectrum
of a quantum mechanical system
um so um
we were considering it's on a simple
funding mechanical models with uh
finding many degrees freedom to begin
with with some hamiltonian operator uh
but sometimes you're telling me as a
function that uh uh
[Music]
um so
um
say we're interested in
um the uh energy levels of the
hamiltonian
um I'm gonna probe that by studying the
following quantity
performance
um so uh basically
um uh observable uh of Interest which
will be uh particularly convenient upon
the filter even though this is not
something that's often always discussing
quantum mechanics uh
um is uh
correlation uh functions
uh in the ground state because
um so it might be a kind of a peculiar
thing because that's it everybody you'll
see it's already why it's a natural
thing to do study the ground state are
denoted by zero gets pronounced
um
um later uh it should be clear depending
on whether I write Q if I write Q as an
operator acting on the states sometimes
I will drop the hat or forget to write
the Hat it should be clear depending on
the context whether it's an operator or
a uh is a bear so so now it's operator
you have uh uh now uh as uh We've
written in the last lecture
um this Q has update uh the timely
Evolution dictated by this
um
uh relation uh into that I over R which
has B into that minus the signal Base
Bar which had a t that's how the
operator evolved in either a picture uh
so the query function I'm going to be
interested in is the following you've
had a uh you had zero uh in the vacuum
and take its overlap with the value so
this thing uh because it's the two-point
equation function in in the ground state
um others so G of B
right so that's the definition
uh any questions so far
and so so there's a definition so I
think you had the time zero average if
you had the time T again the things
overlap with the vacuum notation always
actually is in a hydrogen break picture
so you know the the say does not involve
um
okay
now uh why would we care about Central
quantity
uh well uh obviously uh if you have a
question
um so if you have a uh what's a normal
basis
of energy
uh
and say
um
this person said and in some en ends of
the answer to that
and so forth
um then uh we can write this G of D so
we can insert a complete basis
so basis
uh
United States
um is there a complete basis in uh here
uh and uh equivalently right there's two
point for your function as the sun over
energy
and yes zero
foreign
[Music]
so
if it's okay is then not equal to sum
over n
and zero or two times zero and and uh
zero zero sometimes the
foreign
[Music]
any questions
um okay so this is going to be a basic
Observer of interest because
um you see it captured the energy level
so it has a difference between the
energy of the ground state and any
exciting State uh in principle if you
know GOP is the function P you can do
the inverse polio transform and figure
out so captured all the information the
product is that this overlap is not zero
which genetically would be
um now of course if you take the
harmonic oscillator there's an accident
if you take a common alternator actually
this state only is non-trivial for n
equals one but but the more generic
system this Q had on the vacuum I can
come across that it will generally have
none zero overlap with any excited
States in that situation there's um two
point function will capture all the
energy Spectrum Within
okay so so that's one reason why I would
be interested in this but another reason
I do speak swirly is that this is
something that's uh relatively easy to
calculate using the pattern more
formative
um so uh my assumption
uh e n minus e0
is uh is not negative because we're
assuming the easier always
um so
uh
uh one of the things we're going to do
with this with something we're going to
be doing all the time in common field
Theory uh is to real tree of e not just
as function of a real number T but I'm
going to consider it as an energy
function in C and another continue G of
T so complex values of d
okay so uh by the way uh how many people
feel comfortable with the notion of
another continuation of analytic
function okay I think not everybody
because um uh now uh don't worry you
know we will uh introduce these things
gently uh but um uh I should say that uh
the first thing or most important
mathematical tool for Quantum field
theory is complex analysis in one
variable so this is something that uh if
you're not familiar with at this point
you will be familiar with by the Android
so so we'll
we'll
be you know introducing things uh as we
go along
um uh but uh but now this is the first
time we're gonna encounter that so
um
but let me make a statement
um so
uh imagine you uh I'll take this pumpkin
gft and extend the notion so April is
defined for real number T real-time
Devolution uh but we're gonna imagine uh
we're gonna attempt to try to extend GOP
uh as a function uh complex by the
function of complex primary 13. now can
we actually do that
uh now if you look at the sum in terms
by term obviously you can do that
because you have this exponential you
can replace the T from a real number to
a complex number there's nothing wrong
about that
um but there's a question that when the
sun will converge
uh the sound generated infinite sum
there's a question of whether converges
um typically a quantity system you can
take the harmonic oscillator but how
many ounces actually is maybe it's too
trivial for this purpose because 10 is
actually equal to one of the sum from
case but for generic uh you know uh
system with some arbitrary then one
degree level arbitrary potential let's
say
um the sound could be evidence sound but
in that situation uh you have to be a
little hair because uh if you replace
this T by compact parameter depending on
the sign of this imaginary part uh you
know if you want to have an I uh the I
times T will have a real power it can
take the positive sign or negative sign
so generally if you take if the sign if
minus i t has positive real part then
they multiply this energy this will grow
exponentially for higher difference and
then typically the sum might uh diverge
and this result is it'll be fine it will
not exist
um on the other hand if you um
uh so if you analytically
continue
um
uh to uh complexity
uh well
uh imaginary party Limited
then you have a minus I absolutely
positive and then R minus I again so you
have the real part of this exponent will
be some negative number times UI minus
e0 that'll be as long as you're
suppressed by high energy
so in that case the sum will tend to
converge and indeed there's a
mathematical theorem so which I'll now
elaborate here
um that will guarantee
um that this sum provide that makes
sense the real key is going to make
sense also at reminder P the Omega
uh in which case
um so uh
for this the sum of N converges
um and uh P of T is a qualifying
um and uh has some nice properties which
I will not fully elaborate on but uh to
say that it is
this this continuation uh through
complex by their p is well defined uh a
pro I provide you that imagine part of
these
okay so we're going to be interested in
studying this two-point magnitude of Aid
not only for real T but for
um uh complexity with negative imaginary
parts
a few squares so effectively to be what
zero is
fine no not necessarily uh oh
and gm0 is fine but that's not the what
I'm worried about I'm worried about uh
um uh I'm worried about uh uh you know
acquiring a positive imagine Fund in
that case sure
uh no uh so far I haven't made any
additional statement right all I'm
saying is that let's go into contact
but here it's a real axis this is the
imaginary axis
um uh so uh all we say is that so
abrahim's achieved they find anywhere
around that because it relaxes uh and I
can't I think go down and um and I
expect that
cool
um okay
if you know what happens to the
imaginary team
oh yes absolutely
um uh so uh well that that's the thing
that uh about any continuation uh
perhaps yeah uh let me say a few more
words about about uh growth emergency
and I'll come back to
come back to the extent to which uh you
can determinate this
um so uh in particularly important case
uh is uh
um
so
for example uh let's take C to be minus
I now where now is a positive real
number
called the real number
um and uh commonly you know this is
sometimes called the weak rotation
um I don't like this term rotation
because uh it's not really we're not
relatively anything it's really any
configuration and you know this will
become clear uh into examples
um but um
in this case
if we start with this this guy uh but we
think T to B minus right now
um uh well
down there of course so so here we have
a sum over n
zero two zero and and
two zero zero this is just one number
and now and e to the minus one over H
bar the N minus e0
as I said earlier you know these things
are explodingly suppressed at higher
energies and there's some typically
convergence
um and uh it is also going to be true
that uh if you uh know the value of the
GRT on the negative axis
um you can uh if you also know that it's
analytic in parallel you can uh
unambiguously can view this back to real
um
uh
uh to agree about your teeth uh maybe
just as a as as a a kind of a brief
mathematical aside how does this work in
general you have some function update uh
that uh a functional real value how does
that conversion work uh I'll just make a
quick comment about that so um so again
imagine trying to define the function on
the complex deep plane with the real
axis here and imagine access over there
so a plus RI this function would be
defined anywhere along the real axis
uh now uh uh suppose the function is
analytic at one point which means that
the Taylor series of the function
converted to the function itself in a
neighborhood of that point uh so over
here you can write the paper series
sum over a and t minus d0 relative and
where this point is the mineral
get suppressed by some um some number to
Npower uh this uh uh these uh every term
in the sum well because of the sum will
converge we'll have some radius
comparatives let's say let's say this
this is the radius convergence
um and uh converters
um it always will also converge if you
replace uh T minus t 0 it will replace d
uh by not just any real number on this
interval but by the compass number in
this little disk so so the the
stereotypes will Converge on this disk
so we Define anywhere inside of this as
an under function
um and uh so that defines unambiguously
the element integration the function
from this part of the real interval to
the disk from complex play but you don't
stop there uh you can now start uh a new
from any point into this and ask uh what
if you do data expansion over here and
they might have some other radius
converters maybe convergence and the
start of a point over here maybe
conversion that is and so on and so
forth and uh in this way uh the the
value of the function on this interval
of the real line will determine is the
value on the sequence of this into the
complex aspect this is how integration
works right sometimes uh this might be
obstructive if you discover that your
strong Singularity of the function on
the complex plane you can have the
failure series but not the radius
convergence cannot extend beyond the
points
um so that there could become
obstruction but in absence of custom
fractions you can new by this sequence
of the disks and do the Taylor expansion
over this sequence events so
um I mean you know if you're not I mean
I witness um
okay uh but this is another procedure
that allows you to define the
information and despite the structure
Analytics
uh any questions
yeah
I this is the definition of
beneficiation
I'm saying that I sort of function with
reality I can associate and move the
function of one context here
uh and let me repeat what I said here uh
the way this functional complex variable
is constructed by taking the pillar
Series right so starting with 10
receivers around a point on the real
axis I can any random data series which
we tend to find their way to convert so
if you have to find the radius
convergence it will also converge you
can replace B by a complex number inside
this list
um and therefore
inside the disk uh this produces a
complex analytic function that is
defined on this
as well defined under this one is going
to start at the another point on this
and do the same procedure uh provided
that uh that you still have some radius
number
uh you know I I invite you to
and I'll try the example of uh like
one over one minus D over something that
is yeah
if you take the the function the one
over a common is e right they start at
the origin you'll find that there's
already convergence which is equality
over here but so if you if you just do
the Taylor series uh you're stuck on
this disk but if you really expand over
here you can go around this and and you
know so by by this procedure you can
cover the python explain exceptions so
this is how it works
okay uh any other questions
yeah
actually yeah when you're you're in the
initial Circle in front of an area
Circle are you using the same particular
Series
yeah because I'm really expanding the
function uh at that point and so I need
to use the average derivative of in
order to function at that point
anyway
so it's all additional questions will be
we'll go into the section
uh I I will not use that if I but
anything I will actually use I will um
you know I will explain more but for now
uh I think we we know we need to proceed
uh
okay
um
um all right so
uh uh your sister review that why this
will be a convenient thing to do
um
so um we assume that there's a gap
uh due to the first excited state and
the ground state I suppose the energy
between U1 is zero uh is impossible so
there's no regeners here they run a
scale uh in that situation
uh we can we can replace
uh
this zero cat in this polarity function
uh by wow uh you know and basically it's
an arbitrary generic state it doesn't at
the beginning
uh and uh let me consider the
um well we'll consider the operator
imagine time uh let me take uh is the
minus one of H bar uh H minus B naught
of t
uh and I take a limit
ation
so this is a procedure that uh looks
like kind of find the evolution of the
state in imaginary time uh and as an
inner limit as an imaginary time to
to Infinity uh this operator is going to
kill everything by the ground state
everything that's not right will be
supporting suppressed
so absolute organization if you pick
some generic status overlap with the
ground state so this limit is going to
pick up pick up address the ground state
component
s
um
so
um so the acquiring function largely in
the ground states of Interest I can do a
bit of rewriting so this uh 2.200
function you've had d q 0 is 0. uh how
can I do this way so this is the same as
the limits of capital and Divinity of
the following I think some objects to
say PSI
um
over here
I do this which is e to the minus 1 over
is bar 100 million times P because
sometimes I forget to write a hat
uh this matter so you should always have
a hat on it into the
on the right bar
okay this is the original concrete of
that
uh and uh QT
q0
um and uh a normalize this by
by the thing without the query circuits
onto the minus two over this bar
the time
uh as you can see this is uh this is
equal to that because what I found right
hand side is uh simply to pick out the
contribution uh from the ground state
components of uh of the state side and
this uh minus e0 here doesn't matter
because it's going to cancel between the
numerator
in fact I think last lecture someone
asked me whether I want to take the
Theta Infinity in the pattern you go
this is what we're supposed to do okay
well we'll see that first
um any question about this identity here
yes so where did the E not go I decided
it ends up because
upstairs and down here though
um okay so uh uh let's uh interpret
this top formula a bit uh because as I
said so far this is construction but we
can think of imagine that this is kind
of a time you'll lose your money imagine
your time if we draw a picture of
um colored talk
obviously
good
so uh I would say there's real time
and here's the minor nine
um
so um
we start with some State uh we're going
to evolve uh in Imagine time
uh by some amount
uh actually
the way I would like to uh
all right so this corresponds to uh the
evolution uh by minus i t which is
over here and I evolve down
um by the uh it's announced or minus i t
that corresponds to this emotion
operator and then I get to
uh after that Evolution I get to this
operator
it's already slot here
um and then I can rewrite this two hat
as uh the time evolution by T but thank
you hat then they evolve by minus
U on the right and Universe on the left
so um
so we can view that as uh
time Evolution uh in real estate uh by
some by the amount uh P here
um and uh and then I inserted
the operator two hands again
you have over here
um and then that operator there tells
you to uh evolve it after insert that
operator account state did that evolve
back in real time back to zero and then
this thing tells you to further evolve
uh provide some amounts by some large
amounts minus I2
okay so so this uh top expression can be
viewed as you have some operator
sandwich video size expect the value of
some operator what is this operator is
the time we losing the imaginary time
starting from here down this way for
some long imaginary time then go forward
in real time or insert a few hands go
for any real time is there another two
hats involve back in real time and then
uh down on the imagine the prime access
again
you can think of it that way
the green arrows are
these two highly Evolution numbers
so this is
just some picture to to a guy you're
thinking you don't find it that if
you're convenient to think of The
Spectator you can't ignore this picture
um now uh
alternatively
uh we could uh instead just consider uh
GLT for Imaginary time which actually
might be more convenient if you think in
terms of this picture so if
alternatively if you
know alternative
uh we can consider G just at P equals
minus one
positive real account
um so this this one as we said it's and
it's been the same expression you just
replace this that you have uh well the Q
hat p but if you had okay
foreign
possibility they've been released inside
e to the minus 1 over H bar Capital H
at P minus Tau T is very large because
it's going to be positive uh Q
0.
uh
[Music]
when I say divided sorry now we're going
to say
uh
okay so in this case uh you can we can
just speak of the evolution is imaginary
see uh where
um
uh three
starts with uh
wow let me just uh think of this uh tile
axis which is
the difference in the increasing
direction we will start as minus t
uh then we'll get to a Time Zero uh
where we'll research Q hat and then we
evolved by some
amount of time now
this Evolution operator and we insert
another two hats and then we evolve by T
minus
that's it
here
okay
um anyway so so this is just another way
to rewrite this two point function uh
with uh imaginary negative imagery
indeed uh and as I said uh this is
whatever where you write it the all
characters send me one information this
also captures the energy spectrum of uh
yeah
in a way that's describing over there so
for example if you know this function uh
and for a function Tau you can just do
the inverse buff transform and recover
the energy exactly
um so uh it's a widely bother
I think this
um
we're going to uh now investigate how to
access this observable using the
password
uh it will be convenient to work with uh
complementary time evolution in this
context of these recovery functions just
because as you'll see uh the path
integral is a better Behavior yes
so what critical information
the only intuition uh it's uh some uh
Matrix elements of operators there's no
uh at this point uh I don't need to give
any interpretation this is just
something I can study a capture the
energy spectrum and some other
information about metric settlement that
we still have
um the real reason that I'm gonna be
interested in this is because it's a
natural thing to cover using pattern
um uh so you know if you want to probe
any observable using pattern book this
is sort of the combinative thing to
start with but I haven't explained that
because apart from that there's no I
wouldn't assign any further physical
activity basis
any other questions
yeah
foreign
um okay so uh
so something happening well
how do we continue such a thing
well uh well here's a here's a nice
thing about it
um so in the past integral
but it only compute
this two-point assumption
um uh well uh you can follow
uh the same logic as the way we derive
The Matrix elemented operator last time
but it started doing a complete basis at
uh you know small steps of time
um and then you get rid of the conjugate
momentum well you know we did this dire
Mission about last time and it will
produce some kind of integration over uh
this path of Q uh going to some range of
time
um now what happens if you uh have this
additional insertion of Q hats uh well
uh you just uh you know
you know if you get to the point where
you have time zero you just insert the
screen half and then get time p is there
another two hats
um and if you calculate the Matrix
element of the student hat because this
p's and q's the end and Q and Laser
States uh you'll just pick up qn at that
step
so so the result of this uh and this
will be just calculated literally by
inserting a q t and q0 into the library
but no longer as operator but just as
variables and what I mean is this so you
would write integral DQ this measure
factor which we don't have to carefully
interpret this in value of computations
um we have t to the I over degrees power
and action a prior this would be from
convolutional time to some kind of time
or specify that in moment so lagrangian
I can give you that DT
um
and uh
uh well it's not same material Prime
um and uh this is going to insert QT
and uh zero
in here
um
now this is not quite the left hand side
yet because if you recall our generation
last time uh this pattern is about
within computes well first of all you
have to specify some boundary condition
uh now we do not want to specify
conditions of your final indeed we don't
have to specify because you know here
the side here is the arbitrary actually
I could have replayed this side by side
Prime this doesn't actually matter
um so so I can replay the five Prime by
Simon killing natural Side by some if
you find though it wouldn't have matters
uh that dependence will drop out
yes this if I if I evolve in this
specific way uh I'm only going to pick
up the contribution from the ground
state
um so uh and indeed that's the procedure
we're going to follow uh so if you take
this and divide by the passenger row
uh
the same path in the world but now
um
without this Q insertion
uh and then you take a limit
uh where you want to take essentially
the Imagine part of TF
okay so so this is going to be the
empathic representation of the uh to the
point correlation function of our
interest
um uh so far uh if I take tea to be
Realty uh and I follow this procedure
um then uh you know this
you have to interpret with action which
is
indeed you have to interpret that action
uh as a contour degree on a complexity
plane that follows exactly this path
I've drawn over there
uh things will be a little bit easier to
think about and more a little bit more
clear-cuts if I just declare that I want
to calculate the uh and the continued
version this quick rotated version of
the two-point query function uh Geo Tau
Ortiz
if I if I'm just interested in that uh
then
um I could uh uh just follow this path
uh just moving in imaginary time I don't
I don't have to do this weird thing over
there so that's a that's going to be a
bit more straightforward
uh any question about this formula here
yes just to make sure
so the q i and Q final can be any right
that's good that's correct so here I
don't even need to specify the boundary
condition because that depends on the
market will drop out in this limit
that that's why that's why I introduced
that that whole Gadget video
I mean I could have kept track of the
final condition but it's uh it'll make
things a little bit more Counting
okay uh any other questions
yeah so in this case we're taking
um like the states uh q0 timely runs it
equals the same QR
no no no no no no no uh no uh Qi uh
plays the role of this side primary and
the qf uh will play the row of the side
here and I don't have to specify them
because because the dependence on that
will drop out so so then how did we go
from what because
uh last time I never had this group had
research
so so last time uh so this is something
new compared to last time uh uh what you
had to do you can read me the the
derivation last time so uh you know for
example uh uh you see you can think of
this whole thing as I'm finding the
operator variable in this path in
complex time uh but at some point
actually because I mean
time you're gonna insert a few hacks
because
and then after some other time you got
to insert the list you have okay
uh that's the thing you want to
calculate right that's the thing on you
want to calculates when you call a
particular procedure what do you
actually do well you're gonna be
discretizing this steps
like we're doing it last time and those
two hats is going only going to enter in
that computation in this Matrix element
between you know the instruction of this
basis here and the basis is over there
uh but in that case uh you know if you
follow that derivation uh this Cube had
you know it's going to be done with some
q and P basis and it's interesting the Q
has on the cube base let's just pick up
this argument eigen value which is some
qn
this q and turns into Q
of t or Q of zero uh that is the now the
variable
of the integration so let me emphasize
no this is kind of a you know basically
but very important points which is that
on the left-hand side this is an
operator
so so then I have this operator
and this corresponds to the instruction
of this effect so I'm I'm you know here
I'm integrating over the space of
functions Q of P or any t uh so the Q 0
is one of these simply many variables if
you wish and the skill T is another
point of this
variables uh and I just insert that into
the integral this is part of the
integrand
and the claim is that this pattern it
was supposed to reproduce that that
answer provided that you regularize this
measure correctly as we expand it
said
imaginary
it all throughout
uh so that's not literally like I will
do that in a moment but I said so far
I'm still in this way of writing I'm
still taking the key to be real and then
in order to do that I have to interpret
this action as defined by following this
path over here
I guess that that's the reason I I do
this
through the start here right so I have
to follow this this entire time
okay uh but uh certainly I'm going to
say that if I instead of the work with
them during the imaginary tea I just had
to drive this red Point down here then I
just go down this way don't have to
worry about this which is why it's
convenient to work with g at the
negative imagery
uh yes but the whole point is that
acceleration is unambiguous if you have
if you know the function for imagery
yeah
it is analytic on this lower half
complexity plane then that has all the
information to determine the function
and reality
because
uh I'm not sure what do you mean by can
do analytic I mean the function is
you know when we prove there and see
calculus for a reason
oh uh uh uh well uh I didn't say uh
ideas that I haven't been doing this in
March with me uh but uh we can launch
into a lengthy discussion of how you
numerically and continue that's actually
a very interesting subject but it will
take us a bit uh far from from the theme
but
um
but numerically you can help me also do
that you see this this procedure of uh
repeated headers here this is not a
multiplication way calculation but it is
anyway if you go if I go to Archer if I
order in the Taylor series on this you
can this is not just some imagination of
mathematicians this you can do on the
computer
okay uh any uh other questions
okay
um
um so uh let's see
um okay so um uh so now uh as I as I
have reloaded to uh I don't want to keep
talking about this we are a contour here
so it's a little bit more convenient if
I just work with a negative imagery T so
we're going to from now uh often uh
consider this rotation
um so we're gonna take UNT and take uh P
to be minus signed out very often often
uh when there's no room for confusion
I'm still going to write this as Q of
Tau uh but it's understood that the
Qatar is actually a different function
right it's an integration of this two at
least now
it's really cute minus ital but you know
probably will be clear depending on the
context what I actually need
yeah I could have maybe put like like
this but let me know
um
okay so this is by a slide uh notation
um and uh if I if I so uh now if I apply
that to uh this actually on the
lagrangian I would kind of derivative of
q a q dot P by DT of Q so that will
become uh
foreign
so
uh so typically
for example this uh La Grande so I
suppose this lagrangea is in the form
let's say it's religion actually
potential magnetic term is a potential
term right uh and if I do this
replacement it goes to a minus I doubt
uh I would write this as I will replace
these two dots with I times C by the
time of Q so this becomes minus one half
foreign
and of course if I integrate also this
measure DT has to be become has to be
replaced by minus I uh
um and um
um so
um e to the I over H bar integral L of u
q Dot
and they did under this weak rotation
and
it will become well what does it become
well this T is going to become uh uh
minus I DP is going to become minus I
detailed but I'm going to write such as
this minus I and I where it's okay so
but I'm going to put the extra minus 9
in front and Define this thing in here
as the what we usually call the
euclidean version of lagrangian the wick
rotating version is a function of Q and
Tau of Q where my convention is always
going to be such that this l q q dot is
it defined to be minus well euclidean uh
Q has been held Q so for example uh if l
here the usual lagrangian is one half q
dot squared minus V of Q then this
euclidean version of lagrangian
is just uh
it's minus of that so now it becomes
plus one half d by d p q square plus a d
over
okay so the reason for this assignment
is just that I want to make this L
euclidean
um this guy here I want this to be
positive uh so the potential is the
boundary from below so this thing is a
function as a functional well as
function of Q
this Foundation below
okay so so in this uh which rotation
procedure uh replacing T by minus I Tau
and this exponential here this waiting
factor in the pack really well that
becomes uh e to the minus one over H bar
the integral of the what I call the
euclidean lagrangian l e uh
um and as I said typically this guy here
is going to be uh positive or boundary
From Below and so
um unlike uh This original when you're
back in patio which is uh you know for
the real path this will be some phase
which is oscillatory you you might
imagine that that's kind of uh let's say
numerically important to calculate
because you have this while the acid is
is
that then converts to my question
um but uh once you do this quick
rotation it looks much better because
now this guy here is going to be
exponentially suppressed for wildly
fluctuating pads so it's going to be
dominated by the kind of hat that really
have a small values of the euclidean
action which is the quantity that's
bounded From Below
okay so so that's another reason uh why
this uh which related version of the
planet is much nicer to work with
because uh it actually will have a much
better conversion property
uh any questions so far
like minus like if it's the magnets like
you just uh so the side here is
important uh I have to find the sign of
the canister right so this L is minus l
e and this one is icons are getting the
I so the sign is correct
euclidean action
it differs from the usual connection of
the action Better Sound
I don't listen
all right so um
so with that uh
we understand that if you want to
calculate this
uh
you you play a version related version
of this two-point function uh we can
just use the nuclear version which is uh
um you know well you just replace that
way back by this and uh and this
integration range is going to be found
like minus T2
minus t into the T if you wish then they
take limit this particularly to Infinity
about in the numerator
and the result is supposed to be well
defined that gives you the actual uh and
regulation two-point functions
okay
um
any questions yeah
so in general we're going to perform a
work rotation we get you know some path
integral which is a lot lifestablization
right but in order to get back to our
actual measurable cervical right we have
to find you know what that analytic
situation equals uh well uh you can uh
so you know you know I mean this
intuition you know you can extract this
identity levels without having to
explicit within information in fact it's
you know in the sense actually easier
but this is what people
you know I actually do in uh
we'll not get to that anytime soon but
uh you know
this is uh not just uh uh you know
um uh some uh abstract mathematics uh it
can be turned into academical
computations of actual energy levels for
example uh let me
yes
um but but uh in uh both you know this
kind of simple model but also later in
actual uh vulnerable Theory
um uh these kind of quality functions
are expected to be uh have a nice energy
property that's expected
um provided that I'm not important
filtering is actually defined it's
actually well defined so so in a
non-portrait defined Financial Theory
such as Quantum Yuma theory important
Dimension or 5433 Dimension
um these kind of functions are going to
be well defined uh uh for things like
QED it will not quite be well defined
but that's because QD itself is not
defined a number of different level it's
only defined level of predivision theory
so in that case there are various
pathologies associated with this kind of
coordinary function
any other questions
yes
um what if the two operators
ah uh ideas uh okay good uh so uh so far
uh you see um this is uh uh you don't
get to choose the water okay so so the
water is specified
um uh so far
alternated here
um I'm always going to be uh uh in a
specific ordering
um uh in fact for this euclidean uh
version uh of the uh
so you know if you if you switch uh q0
and Q on one side now
um You Might uh be in trouble because
that's like negative uh negative tell
and I I don't know that in this
entrepreneur
I don't know that
um so uh uh
uh what we'll discuss later uh how to uh
uh starts with this kind of a quick
rotation of the ukulele American query
function and recover the uh the the
real-time moments about the region but
it's so far you know this is not a Write
the basic Theory so the renting will be
somewhere but uh we will later
understand how to recover uh query
functions with arbitrary ordering but
for now the the order is as expected
any other questions
invest in a part of the variation step
by step and you don't get you don't get
your troops
in this case it's always spotters
um all right uh so uh next we're going
to discuss how to actually evaluate the
pathway well we're writing this after
expression but uh are we just pulling
ourselves or does this actually they're
actually useful for computation well of
course you can always go back to this a
realized version like last lecture but
we just do that and then uh We're Not
Really Gonna gain anything because you
just go back to the Panasonic
formulation we somehow like to do a
little better than that
um so but the key here is actually going
to be that
um you know once you we decided that
this integration is supposed to be
integration over path of pill in time or
in people in time or imagine time
um there are different ways to
parametrize the space or functions of P
like last time we tried to the project
very function it just by discretizing
time and and every time we have one
variable but they are better things you
can do for example you can Fourier
transform in time you might consider uh
expanding to take a thing you might you
might consider the Fourier expansion of
Q of T so instead of working Queue at a
longer time you go to frequency space or
a transform and then you instead of
integration queue but every time you
integrate over the Fourier modes of uh
every uh frequency okay so that turned
out to be much more convenient for
private computations and we'll discuss
one example of that and it also is for
another example before
and in fact this way of thinking about
the path signal as the integration of
the Fourier notes is much more
convenient for doing what we'll see that
doing preservation Theory
foreign
so to evaluate
uh
the not really girl
uh well the key
uh will be
to
find
a convenient
and also uh regularized
expression
of the measure let's DQ
okay so for example uh as I said I would
like to potentially work in uh some kind
of a frequency space so you can imagine
taking cure a towel
um you can expand this on some video
bases or functions of how so some more
and some q and F and Tau and this F in
the pal
is going to be some uh suitable
uh basis of the functions between now
uh you know they could be you know
employer mode so it could be something
else
um and uh the uh naive realities you
might imagine that you can replace this
integration in the function field of
Health by the integration in the
conditions which are really the only
weird about this
functions if these are exposure
functions say this uh then uh deployment
modes and uh overhand
ability
now of course this will still be
International integral but you might
imagine uh not getting this on a large
group
okay so that's something that one might
attempt to do
any questions
uh well that is this question mark here
uh you don't know that
[Music]
by this gaussian
all right so so that will become
contributed to this measure now in some
people situation this will actually be
true after some constant normalization
you think your nine space is the
function at best but that may not always
be the case
um
uh this will come back to Pilot a little
bit uh well we'll see that in one
mechanics uh but it turns out that uh
the recently which uh things are nicer
if you want to build
uh
uh and this reason it really had to do
with the Retro visiting locality so as I
emphasize in the first lecture opponent
filter is a specializer in quantum
mechanics it's a nice version of quantum
mechanics where some ambiguities don't
actually gets resolved by the
requirement of locality
but uh these words probably does not
mean much right now but uh so uh let me
postpone the proper answer to that
question
but uh but in fact the problem too in
the promise uh is uh precisely uh asking
you going to reacting to study this uh
in a very simple one problem
example of a quantity mechanics
yes
integrals converges to something and
that is uh you should say that
yeah so um
uh let's do this for the simplest uh
example of uh
one of the simplest examples of one
mechanical models
with the increasing level of
sophistication okay so we're gonna first
discuss the harmonic acid
um okay so
example one
is just the harmonic the quantum
harmonic with the quantum harmonic
oscillator uh so the hamiltonian is as
you know uh p squared plus Omega squared
two hat squared uh over two I'm studying
the word last one
um and then uh this of course at the
classical level uh will correspond to uh
a lagrangian that is just one half q dot
squared minus the potential we just
won't have omega squared
Q squared
um okay and uh uh we are going to uh
investigate
um
this uh kind of a two point for your
function of Interest
now a verse uh actually you know from
the undergrad hungry but what is the
ground state and the Waypoint
representation if you wish and Q is just
a position operator in that case uh and
you just calculate this explicit but
we're going to go through this painful
process using Pat people to calculate it
so
um and to do that
um uh we're going to consider the quick
rotating version
so uh we're starting with the our
original happy one I keep my mind and we
have described and we're going to be
calculating things like integral and DQ
of e to the minus one of H bar do you
put it in action with some insertion
into this excuse before if you're
interested in uh two point foreign
thank you
um so in fact I want to do this example
as explicitly impossible and so we're
actually going to
um choose uh boundary condition so so
we're going to take this uh action to be
uh the integral of this equilibrium
version of lagrangian uh from some say
minus P to T that's like I mentioned
I've been using implicitly earlier
um so uh as I said the boundary industry
is not going to actually matter in the
line T to Infinity uh but it will be a
step for now just to show you the
explicit computation I'm going to start
by taking a PW finite and actually do
this uh in the this functional
integration so to do that we do want to
in order to you know have a definite
computation we like to choose some
binary condition so we're going to
choose
uh the boundary condition
and
imaginary time
so or with Q L remember this now is
rotated it's a matter of time
um so true there can be such that Q of
minus t is equal to zero and the Q of T
is also zero
okay so in other words
now we're evolving and you plan time
from minus 16 to 8 and uh so
some object function does
that okay sorry zero and start by zero
um so uh given uh this constraint we can
expand a general function uh on the
four-year basis subject to this next
frame that's what they expand
uh
uh if you're now on the foyer basis in
this case because of the boundary
condition
um
over q and f n l and from one to
Infinity what are this Advanced well you
can choose this at ends
to be uh
proportional to the sign of n i uh Tau
plus p over 3T
and so forth so uh this is a complete
basis of uh functions uh the advantage
book that titles minus t
hope you can
distinguish my handwriting this is two
which is not to be confused with now uh
in this Tau so tell plus d we have
disadvantages that minus how would minus
d
know this is a complete basis
um but uh it will be uh
useful to normalize this I'm gonna stick
it in one of our square root T factor
and just to normalize this function at
an end
um so far is a bit ad hoc but uh I'm not
gonna be uh
for them so
let me tell you this a bit more
precisely
so uh
yeah that's how
um uh is uh
basis
functions
uh that today
uh the
prescribed the boundary condition
I'm Hungary
condition
uh and uh orthonormal
for for the normal
uh with respect to
a Super Bowl it defines inner products
functions
for example
that is to say that we're going to be an
inner part between the X
to be
integral from 90 state to T
and star of the family
and this should be move on demand that
this is
say that is autonomous way back to this
inner product defined by different way
um
any questions about this
so I'm just expanding uh this is the
point expansion so in terms of in terms
of this uh we can then write this
include an action so what's the equation
in this example the integral from minus
P to T
one half you can tell a few squared plus
one half
Omega squared Q squared comes out right
so remember so uh go if you go through
them we go through your procedure and
flip the overall sign this is our
euclidean lebronian
uh now you take that extension and plug
it into
here and it can re-extend this action uh
in terms of
uh the QX
so in terms of the Cubans
um what is the
action well um
it's uh
um
all the time so let me just quickly uh
state to this and uh and I'll finish uh
this next time so uh it is very
important company you just said let me
pick this and plug it into the integral
uh
um you'll find that uh
you know so so you take this and the
stick into this entire queue and
multiply by another project without
queue uh I just have q n times qm
during the FN uh but that integral you
can do and you'll find out that the
result is going to be non-zero only if n
is equal to M and the result of this and
this and sum over and uh
uh q and squared uh one half and I over
and c 200 plus one have omega squared so
um the first term come from the
beginning
uh the second term comes from this
well thank you this is
and that's the result of that then
action as a function of qns
right so um this happy to grow
uh whatever it is that you want
something to start which you can study
and we will study next time when I
insert like some cues and from that
we'll extract this quantity function uh
so that uh we're gonna compute by uh
turning it into the course integration
over this poem about qn so the product
and from one to Infinity uh and uh this
action is just minus one over H bar sum
Over N from y to Infinity uh one half of
uh M pi over two t squared plus Omega
uh
two N squared and with whatever QA
searches uh that you want to put in
uh now this integral you all know how to
do at least one by one it's just a
gaussian integral because I've chosen
this unprinted approaches quite really
you can see that the kinetic term is a
diagonal so there's no mixing of between
the Q and the qm or different n and n
gaussian integrals uh but we're going to
be interested in insertion of additional
cues
uh and unfortunately I don't have time
now I will finish that calculation
um
uh
next time yes so let's give this away
because we can follow each
um
that's correct that's correct so far uh
this is the Ukrainian government now you
see uh uh yeah that's correct
uh if you you might imagine that
um
you know if you
um you're going to do this in a lot in
time you might you might worry that uh
you know instead of expanding Factor you
have some positive base but actually
um we've set up the the you know the
real-time competition such a way that
it's actually still going to look more
nice like like this because you had a
problem that that weird time come to
work where most of it is still in
imaginary time Direction so ultimately
in in a sense that this kind of a path
in the world in one mechanics is always
should always be viewed as defines
really imaginary time that that's that's
the best way to think about it it is the
um
it's sort of the path people that this
uh mathematically
yes
uh good so uh first of all a first
comment is that
um you could of course imagine training
online attention here's normalization
measure but that's on constant if you
change by some constant I I wouldn't
worry about it because ultimately uh I
don't care about over organization on
this it's going to cancel between the
numerator and Dynamics if I'm interested
in the important functions
uh you might worry about uh
um the dependence
it depends on okay in some way and that
could be bad
uh
um that now did not happen in this
example uh you will uh that the purpose
of a problem Set uh the problem two in
in the in the problem set I have was
just posted is precisely to let you
study uh this to investigate this
nomination in a in a similar but
actually even simpler than this in some
sense example uh and uh well you see uh
if you use that this will be time
regularization as we have the right last
time you know what noise is supposed to
do because when we derived from Hamilton
so in that case there's no ambiguity
um in this case while we don't know what
the matter is but if you in first of all
you know uh going from this q and to
those Q so this qn or the poem The Last
Time those are at least we apply to the
different variables
factor is
okay so you could study that and you can
figure out what it is
um uh I'm not going to discuss that
right now in fact uh that uh Jacobian
Factor even was a remark at the end of
the P set it's an extra credit part of
them it's not you're not even required
to study that you're coping Factor well
it's really some aspects of
personalization you'll see that it's not
always trivial sometimes you have to
keep track
um but in this example it turns out that
it's not there's no there's no uh actual
uh non-trivial uh dependence uh
yes
uh well the limits are commands me to
put it you're integrating over all
possible functions here uh so I'm sorry
I mean these four amounts are under
strength uh in this case real errors
is
yeah
um uh that depends on uh what what you
what you want to get get out of it uh
you know you could say that uh there's
regularization I did last time is a way
to make it rigorous uh but it may not
preserve all the problems you want to
preserve listen to their life
Enlightenment that we've been talking
about is that like a well-defined like
nightmare space on the space of the past
uh on the actual space the functions
that depends I believe a simple cases at
least in the gaussian case if it
actually can be made like a rigorous on
the space of functions uh but uh
um this is not something I will get into
uh in this class
um uh in practice uh and that is almost
never used in physics but it's something
that is worth understanding impossible
and uh
I think uh
applications but for these are very
simple models it can be made precise
but but for our purpose we're always
going to think about this um as defined
through regularization we're not going
to try to you know consider some uh you
know measure on some organizations
facing functions
um
uh any other questions
NOTE END VIDEO uzixOflp0tY
NOTE BEGIN VIDEO 3: M0py5a4RWhE (2022-09-13)
NOTE JSON3 SHA-256 68cc35a320a6cf1e957ca594cb797da76d9e3bd2b4ce05384db1518ad5f7d24a
NOTE VTT SHA-256 80b51e48ed7ffc85f60349ac80664e2edbcb1e0bf349dd77a922350c4c6089f1
Kind: captions
Language: en
uh okay let's uh get started so uh let's
finish this uh calculation last time uh
we're talking about uh still the system
of important and so
um we are working with
um the usual uh
uh like so
um and then um we uh we're performing a
liquidation so you feed to uh
and uh
it defines with uh
M squared
about
Omega squared 2 is greater
um and the quality is that the the
observable that we're interested uh in
uh competing uh was uh this quantity uh
the ground state uh
Q hat p q hat zero
um and then uh we uh once again in this
um
T going to minus type how is a
hypotheist so T had that negative the
negative imaginary number
um wrote this as uh let me for now just
uh indicate just to avoid unnecessary
confusion I call this ge often I will
drop this with this uh this uh super
script uh so the GE is related to G uh
binary equation P equal into minus sign
power
but anyway I can write this in this in
this way still
um
I'm just going to write this as two
halves it's really repeat now
um
um and uh and we said that uh the reason
that we wanted to uh write it this way
is because uh once we uh have done the
with rotation uh it's uh there's a
convenient uh path in the world uh
expression for this in terms of
QuickBooks in that we don't actually
have to uh uh specify the boundary
condition he says we can take this limit
uh t uh going to
um technological Divinity uh where we
add
um
this uh
it's about minus on the page bar s uh
including
being the integral in this example I'm
taking the range actually minus t to
capital P from uh vital of uh with l
uh Oblivion uh as a function of
qren over there
um and uh with the insertion of Q uh Tau
Cube zero
um uh and uh
is it the same thing but without that a
circuit
do I have last time and uh then we're in
the middle of doing this calculation
um
time but that would uh to be the purpose
of this in this sense we uh decide that
we want to use a different way to
represent the the functional integral so
that is we expanded the QR Tau
the boundary condition doesn't matter
but if I were to do a calculation of
this quantity I'd find it before I take
the limit I still have to specify the
boundary condition and last time
um the way I said that we're going to
specify the boundary condition we could
say that
so as we go from -15 it is
um this view is that the queue of power
isn't a typically zero and endpoints
right so uh and with that we can expand
on the four-year basis and from one to
Infinity uh q n and n sub Tau and uh
is normalized in the way I explained it
last time so and hi uh K over to t uh
and then
the internet access in terms of this uh
just plug in and calculate and with the
straightforward calculation
um and the result is a sum from remote
stands from expand from one to Infinity
uh so one half is a potential return
uh Omega squared with the right it will
the cube now score just becomes sum over
again squared and the kinetic
environment gives uh n pi over 2T
this way
so so once we have that uh we are then
ready to to take this and plug into that
formula uh and and then these uh the
cube tile and q0 over here we can just
again expand in terms of the qns and
this event this comes along with the
right
um and so uh really uh these qns These
are the integration variables in this
functional integral so we just need to
perform uh the integration the scale
change across so we just need to study
the integral of for example
n
um uh there's good I read the romance of
visibility
there are no constraints on these
copages other than the real parameters
um uh and uh e to the minus one over
H bar uh let's say you look at the term
that is depend on two n so let's look at
that a particular term like so
um
uh well actually let me just spread it
this action is Manifest me uh
positive evidence
the function of the qns
um and uh if you have uh if you have now
so so this will be one of the factors
the numerator you have the similar thing
you can have some uh insertion so you
may have uh
one or or or or qn or maybe qn Square
when we expand this cute talk it's zero
um
okay so so of course if you have one
discussing integral you have qn uh then
this this integround is off so we've
just got zero and squared uh you get
something uh we're gonna calculate
um but uh uh a little bit right over
here so the uh
it's uh it's not hard to see that
um so
let's say this guy let me write this
here
zero
um
calculate uh let me use it in the
patient this uh q and qn expression
value this is just uh uh you know
product so I've now replaced that uh
measure by just the product of uh dqn
from one to Infinity uh there might be
some overall Dimension constants uh
which I will not care about for this
purpose because that's whatever it is
it's going to be cancel between the
numerator and economy
um so I have in the numerator and this
uh e to the minus one of H bar and let's
say
and with a q n q n is actually I'm
definitely expecting value so so
um I'm gonna divide by the integral
um
about
without any section
uh as you can see
um okay right so so that's all that's
needed uh to calculate this and then the
result of this is just going to be a
limited Infinity of that it's the value
of Q and qn times uh F and now
yeah
um what does like bracket q and qn
what's the definition
this is a trivial trivia
and really funny this whole thing is the
expectation value so you think of this
this integral as a sensor for uh you
know this is something e to the minus
actually the sum weighting factor and
we're just sampling over it's not
impossible uh values of qn and
calculates with this weight the
expression value of the product the
quantity q and QX oh this is just just
the definition
uh okay so but let's let's focus on this
one this is all we need to know in order
to get to the get to the answer where we
care about
any questions yes why do we like why can
we pick a particular event and um
uh because it's only about the salvation
over a pole and uh yes we do uh yes and
uh
sorry ah okay sorry that's what that was
the time okay
thank you
okay uh yes
I agree that what we have is awesome
he's going to imaginary time when we
expect it can be exponential in the in
English uh good question uh this is a
very important point I want to clarify
uh when I draw uh what cute cow is this
has nothing to do with the time
Evolution I think about the question the
most right so uh the Q tau is arbitrary
integration variable uh there's no
constraint until apart from the boundary
condition so nobody did I say that you
have to pay any kind of equations there
is no such a sound
this F of NFL these are arbitrary based
the functions the only they're only
subject to the constraint that they have
to vanish and the two endpoints the
minus C and T that is the only only uh
only constraint
that's the rule of the pattern right
nowhere did I say use the word equation
of motion the question motion
exactly what it means well you you will
see it but so far there's no there's no
need to mention such such words that's
cute it's just some uh integration
variable nothing more than that
so imagine this last time but maybe it
was a little bit quick I'm assuming I'm
setting q0 and sorry Q minus P minus t
to zero and also set a Q Plus E3 so this
is my q i I call it Qi this is qf right
that's the initial and final division
but that was the arbitrary I I could
have changed this is zero to uh whatever
whatever number right I want the whole
point is that it won't matter uh as long
as I choose it through the same but I'm
going straight in the numerator and
denominator that was the whole point of
the derivation last time right when we
show that as you take the limit other
people Infinity you always project onto
the ground state so as long as you're
interested in the ground state
especially Mattingly
or later it would be causing this no
vacuum that certain value the ground
state has been value
for the which one thing happening bro
they're not even sure it won't matter
well we'll say that expressly so so far
obviously everything depends on capital
T but we'll see that there's a
well-defined articles in better limits
we're in the T dependence will drop out
any other questions yes
uh yes it is uh that's about this okay
okay doesn't matter
okay uh
uh so
um
um okay so what is this well uh
obviously uh if uh if n is not equal to
n this is uh this is going to be equal
to zero
a factor that's like this with a single
insertion or qn and not zero because
it's integrated on
uh so uh the only situation you have to
worry about uh is uh when n is equal to
n in which case uh you can just easily
calculate this galaxy integral with the
Q and squared insertion and the final
answer I'll just write down the answer
so
that's a good something so uh so the
conclusion is that this uh equation
value
and command is equal to uh chronic or
Delta in n and n so when m equal to n it
is a h bar over uh
calculus
I don't know how to do that integral uh
any questions about this so far
um so so with this uh then uh we uh we
have the answer so let's plug in and uh
and look at that uh
coordinate function
so uh the quantities that they call
um
um well in fact uh it's uh just for the
sake of discussion let me consider
something uh slightly more General
um so uh let me consider
um
let's add uh Title One and uh file two
um perhaps a slightly okay notation I
didn't want to introduce new notation
but uh you know whenever I write
later because so far once I have done
the reputation I'm always writing
keywords just a functional top and
hopefully you remember where it comes
um
so
uh so this uh would be uh according to
what we wrote over there
um uh this was it's about to be the
limit of the figures Infinity of sum
over n and M Run 1 to Infinity uh this
uh
qn u n value and a one again
um and uh uh so let me just one more
steps because Infinity of the following
uh so uh now n had to be equal to M for
this would be not zero so I just have
sum over n one definite d uh I've got
this Factor H bar over
and pi over uh two t squared plus Omega
squared uh and then I I have f n Tau 1 f
n Tau two uh now let me plug into it
plugging the expression at ends on God's
uh one over t
uh sine of n i l one plus capital T over
2T times sine uh another n pi
foreign uh Q at QE at R1 is
uh yes uh yes now you you uh one should
be a slightly uh careful about this so
um uh you know usually what I really
demand is expression uh is that you um
take uh uh zero Q hat T1 you have P2 uh
this was the two point function because
G of T1 and D2 and another we continue
to function to T equals to minus Title
One and into one not two minus one I
want e to those two minus five two uh
now you could try to do this directly at
level of the operator uh but uh to do
that it had to be a little bit careful
because uh this my spoil some of the
standard assumptions you might make
about this operator so for example
um
mentioned
unique uh
and I'll do it around that's right but
we pass out here
um and um uh so so they can say that the
skill has now uh would be a CEO would be
still replaced by minus I found so this
becomes these are the uh one over
uh
actually let's make sure
yes one number H bar H hat hotel uh Q
hat zero e to the minus one over or you
can't now
um uh and uh if you take this and plug
into this query function uh that's
actually correct but you have to be a
little careful for example
um uh this operator I like that one uh
for real how it would not be permission
anymore right so usually we say that the
skill had T in quantum mechanics right
for ENT is a permission operator and
that is that is true that property is
invariant under time Evolution if it
will evolved by this there's no
permission because because the hermitian
can't hear that this is
the same expression
um uh but that's not true
okay so so
careful enough but then then yes you can
you can just take it you have a towel
and do certain things but but if you get
confused you should always think in
terms of original know two points for
your function in real time and follow
this analog continuation procedure this
will be quite important when we discuss
uh we discussed the anonymously
important field Theory later
um uh by the end the case uh as you
recorded last time uh the job of this
for the moment is to is that the capture
some information about the spectrum of
the theory that's why we're interested
in it so if you get confused you can
always go back to uh this representation
of this in terms of the energy
eigensterase that I wrote last time uh
and uh and and understand the meaning of
of this quantity we're trying to compute
any other questions
um okay so so now let's let's calculate
this let's quantity in the Picos
independent limit so so if uh everything
we're saying so far makes sense
of limits should be well defined this
expression looks a bit complicated
um so let's uh let's investigate what it
is in the uh
that
thank you
um so as you might expect uh
if you
in real time
it's no longer coaches for example
foreign
um because before you take the limits uh
we're not projecting onto the ground
state
and so so there's no reason to think
that it's time translation variants
but um
any other questions
um okay so so let's take the limit
because Infinity how do we take the
limit well as you uh might imagine uh
the sound has a chemical integral
somehow
um so in fact uh but let's see so uh
let's look at this point here is here
uh this and pi over 2T uh this little N
is a sum over all positive integers uh
and so when the capital t is very large
then this becomes very density space
um there's a kind of some kind of
continuous variable I'm going to Define
this to be okay and so the idea is that
the sum Over N is supposedly but with
what measure well let's let's see so
um so the point is that this if we
Define this would be k then pi over 2T
right
any uh questions about this
um so uh so then uh with this uh it's uh
they're pretty easy to turn this
left-hand side well between this button
here uh into uh uh continue from the
left left side of the board
okay so continue from the left side of
the board right uh so this is now
becomes an integral uh integral of what
so so
Decay from zero to Infinity
um I have to compensate uh with uh so
the sum will become 2T over pi times
this integral but then I have to
multiply this H bar divided by D so D
pencil you get two H bar I
um and then uh this one over this factor
is just one over uh K squared plus Omega
squared to have that
and then have the two signs so the sign
becomes
uh sign of uh M pile original view
that's K so sine of uh K uh cell one
plus T and the sine of uh okay
uh Tau two plus three
also had to take limit T equals to
Infinity because then the GE is still
yeah it does make you feel uncomfortable
but we'll see what happens
okay so so it just turns into this
integral yes before we're using the
limited synchross Infinity to turn you
know that quantity
should have already evaluated uh well uh
the claim uh not quite because uh uh you
know you can't literally substitute the
Stick Of The Infinity in the in the sign
uh because uh uh well
um
uh
well I I guess you know if you're
writing such a way to eliminate then you
could but so far I'm not I'm not doing
that
um uh I mean uh I suppose you you could
have done that but it won't matter for
our purpose
um so uh
um you know you can you can you can take
the speed to be some arbitrary a large
constants and take this into Infinity
for the rest of this point in Paris and
then take this at the end it's not
actually going to make a difference in
the answer but uh I suppose you could
also uh you know uh laboriously uh you
know I guess depend on where they're
standing even or are they rewrite this
signs of the cosines
but you know the answer will be the
second one
foreign
expression uh so we can perform this
integral by uh there's a standard trick
to do this but but we're going to
rewrite this in terms of
um explanations so so rewrite uh
that's I uh in terms of
uh the explanation of things like e to
the I okay
here we'll have a possibly this time
okay two
okay uh so here you will see uh terms
involving Tau y minus how two and also
Tan One Plus Tau two plus two t
all right so so all we need to do is to
calculate some kind of uh
Decay with this exponential function in
k
uh this kind of integral is something
that will encounter over and over again
in this course so I'm going to go
through it uh once for all and how to
calculate this because now of course you
you might just look up some I don't know
mathematical handbook or with
Mathematica which will tell you the
answer
um but uh but there's a useful trick to
use to calculate this kind of integrals
that will come up over and over again so
I want to explain uh explain a Little
Dream let's consider
um uh the integral uh oh by the way
before that let me looks nice
modification so the integrand is uh even
functioning okay obviously so I'm going
to double the integral multiplicity and
Factor one half so that's the same thing
uh
okay Tau just considered as an example
because they're all going to be of this
form
over K squared plus a negative squared
so once we know how to do this is
up there
um
okay so
so uh the the way that is totally useful
for us to for evaluating integers of
this type which I understand it will
come up over and over again
um these two uh
view this uh view this
um has a contour
uh integral
uh
uh a polymorphic function
so we're gonna once again
um consider now this is the 50 Grand
and function okay the first thing we
observe is the integrand is a analytic
function of K that can actually be and
they can continue until the entire
complex play except we're composed
so
um if you take the 50 Grand and uh
continue to the higher complex so this
is the complex
this is the real axis and this is the
imaginary okay
access and um
and our integration
is performed
by
uh
by integrating along the real
along the real actions
we're going to do this integral as a
counter integral
any questions so far so far in this let
me know anything uh so the idea is that
we want to simplify integral by
deforming accountable now a basic
property of uh
the version of a homework function is
that the integration of another function
so allow any close uh Contour is zero so
this is uh everyone familiar with this
fact so this is one of the most basic
facts of complex analysis uh in one
variable uh so so that means the result
of this integral that doesn't change if
I deform the Contour to something like
this okay the indoor is exactly the same
uh provided that the function so the
requirements that often has to be uh
complex analytics in between
uh now if you look at this function it
is going to be analytic indeed except uh
when the denominator vanishes right so
it's got um
the function here
as a whole post at k equals plus minus
Pi Omega and I say and the function in
complex K so the both are here and here
so this is I okay sorry I Omega
so we're allowed to people when we come
to arbitrary won't change the result of
the integral uh unless you get past this
hole
uh there's another way equipment to say
it okay so before that then we say that
um if you didn't have this all uh if you
are able to expose the conquer all the
way to Infinity
um then you see uh suppose so I didn't
say anything about the sign of Tau so
assume that assume that power is real
which is the case for our application
here right so uh on two cases either tau
is positive
negative these two cases of Interest
um now if tau is positive right uh if
you send uh K to the manual if you send
the imaginary part of K to Infinity
uh then e to the i k Tau will be
exponentially suppressed
right so so if power is positive if you
push the counter all the way up uh it
will be uh you know just got zero zero
uh instead of equivalently there's
another way to say this sometimes we'll
say that we can close the Contour on the
other half plane so when I draw this
yellow Arc the bigger the little Arc is
that
uh infinite uh distance
um so the contribution if it tells
greater than zero
uh is going to be negligible as you push
the arc to Infinity
right so um so in that case uh you might
as well calculate the total uh integral
along the Green Path together with the
yellow Arc and that is a closed Contour
uh and with the clothes Contour you can
it have been a call the result will just
be zero
but it's because of the code you can
stream the sound color uh
um it's ready to conquer off of the onto
this running the hole without changing
the integral and the result of that is
just the residue of the function uh at
the ball
right so the the conclusion is that uh
by this by this argument
um
we
look at that uh let me just right here
now the conclusion of this argument uh
is that
um
uh for
Tau positive
um the the integral
uh
this integral is equal to uh two Pi the
revenue there and says
k equals to the pole uh into the I take
it out
um and um
uh
uh and there's this residue is a
straight word to calculate for example
you can write this as the e to the ik
tell over
The Edge plus minus sign oh my God okay
plus I Omega to take the radio just
means that you you strip up this strip
of this strip of this factor and for the
rest you send okay to I Omega
so the result of this is then equal to
uh pi over Omega e to the minus
Omega power
any questions about that that's the
result of this integral
yes I can explain why the upper like
curve would give you zero like I guess
like powers and imaginary so when K
becomes very large
I'm assuming right so that was positive
um so if you're way up there uh it's
suppressed because it's it's much
suppressed uh okay so yeah so K is a
matter of reasons okay okay has a large
imaginary parts right right okay and if
you're out there in this direction yeah
uh it's gonna be suppressed because it's
economic So Soft so whatever which are
you working you go again you estimate
the country from different sections of
art but it's just gonna it's just gonna
be zero
um
so so that's the results again it's very
simple result
um and uh you can repeat the accent the
the analysis so so this this argument uh
uh this argument doesn't apply for Tau
negative okay because for tell negative
this it doesn't manage the desire kind
of blows up
um so that'll be the value of the
function blows up so
um if uh
uh if tile is a negative uh you have to
do something different you have to close
uh below
I'm going to go this way from now you
have to
go to Contour on a lower half plane
in which case uh you get the revenue
here but with a minus sign because of
the orientation the counter runs counter
clock so it runs the clockwise uh and uh
if you if you do that calculation uh
you'll find that before uh Tau negative
uh you know the the result of this uh
this integral is uh minus two Pi I of
the revenue uh uh
minus I Omega the same function here
foreign
okay so uh we're not quite done we're
almost done so the ones we have this
gonna plug into that and uh we're gonna
find
here's the following
as you take this limit
uh here are you going to get friends
like this
right so some of the terms evolve into
the ik tell what minus how two so I want
to help you with the difference uh the
other terms will give you is things like
e to the ik Taiwan plus 100 plus plus
two t so you're gonna have here L1 plus
Alpha plus two t by the way between the
infinity so that term will just drop out
and deliver people
using this formula you'll find the
result is H bar over to Omega e to the
minus Omega Tau y minus
that's our final results
and remember what this is where we're
covering
okay so now if you uh recall uh this uh
one of the world last time concerned
with decomposing this in terms of
insertion of a complete basis of
energizing States uh the coefficient
here tell us about the gap between the
excited the energy difference the
exciting States and the ground state so
here are the only contribution we see is
Omega this Omega you recognize as the
gap between the first exciting state of
the harmonious and the ground
now vaporizer has some arbitrary
operator not just q but some maybe some
polynomial here let's say Insertion I
could also find other exciting States
but in this case stand for some due to
some accidents of the harmonic offset
they're actually Q back on the ground
state as you probably know it's only
involved the first excited state this is
the accident for the harmonic but more
General lagrangea system that would not
be true
in this case because this guy here
only overlap with the first excited
States we only find This this term
evolving
Omega itself which is the gap between
the earth exactly State and the ground
state
any questions about this example
now by the way let me just say that of
course if you have this in this case
because the formula is so simple it's
trivial to elegant video back to the
real time if you wish but uh you know
I'll let you figure out the signs yes
[Music]
that is correct uh while this explain
was what we plan to begin this was there
was a well-defined expression and uh
right in terms of well I mean you know
you know how to compute this using uh
the wave function you can just write a
great round State weight function like
we're going to calculate this as some
integral and you'll find the same kinds
of your check for yourself
oh uh right I mean of course the kind of
being killed you might worry that we
dropped on infinite uh constant Factor
but it's always a cancer between the
numerator and economy right so here
we're covering some kind of expression
value so for this purpose I don't have
to be too careful about the content that
modifies this measure pack now in the
homework problem you have to calculate
now the expanded value by the partition
function the homework problem number two
and for that purpose you actually have
to keep track of all normalization so so
so that's a bit more subtle but uh
any other questions
all right
um so
um
uh so it was nice that it worked out but
uh but it was a pain
uh and uh now I'm going to introduce a
bit of uh
some simple uh technique allow us to
simplify such computation so we don't
have to go through this exercise uh
over and over
um
uh so uh you see uh in the end of the
day we're just doing some Galaxy
integral in this editing this simple
example we're doing a Galaxy integral
um and uh um it's useful to uh have a
efficient way to calculate this kind of
experience values in the Galaxy video so
I'm going to first describe a
mathematical formula for calculating
equation values back to gaussian
integral that's very easy to uh to to
understand uh and then we're gonna later
we'll see the application of this very
soon see the application
oh um
okay so now
uh so let us consider
um
so consider
a general form of the Galaxy integral in
multivariables
um let's consider the following so the
big thing well the cube Vector says an
n-dimensional Galaxy is equal
um and uh we put the minus something the
something is supposed to be the analog
of this actions euclidean action here
right so I'm going to take this thing to
be so Q is some Vector this Q Vector if
you think of it as an analog of the
collection of all these qms that you
wish
uh so e to the minus the action so it's
action that is going to be one half uh Q
uh trans to both uh multiplying a matrix
a multiplying Q
and so this a
is um
right now let's say a symmetric Matrix
so
um
some symmetric means
so this is the sum over n n a n n like u
n u n
let's assume that
um
uh and uh plus uh so let me say
generalized this by adding a linear term
J back with that with Q back where J
it's an arbitrary vector and I call this
uh the generating function uh Z as a
function in Theta because this is
definition
um okay so this uh we can do uh so I
just write a formula once for all and
and figure out how they can do this but
the result if you didn't have this J
Term uh you just get 2 pi to the N
number two
um one number square root of the
determinants of the Matrix a
the the simple way to do that is to do a
change of variable you change your base
do a linear change the base into queue
to diagonal activations okay that's the
simplest way to derive this answer
anyway that's the answer for the Galaxy
if you will if your statutes in zero and
if J is none zero uh you just need to
compute a square and shift the Q and uh
um
square and you can get rid of the
[Music]
a uh a q uh minus uh a uh in verse J
uh and here uh minus uh a inverse J uh
then uh so that will produce this this
linear term in gene q and then you have
to add back in the uh plus I have J
that's both a inverse okay
for this term
you can redefine Q by shifting this away
and suppose
uh a inverse okay
so so that's the result of this
is that the result of this uh
General function of the regarding
any questions so far
straightforward
um so uh given this formula uh if you
have so we're going to be ages if
expanded values like that so I suppose
you have some function f of Q
let's have a few type of analog of this
insertion of the Q hat operators in the
Packer device population
insertions of these q and qns uh some
functional queue and you want to look we
want to calculate the equation value we
increase the value but it is defined to
be uh one over z uh with the J is set to
zero so that's like the pathogrows
without any operating section
um but then we have the pattern to grow
with the insertion so cut into the uh
you
so that that's the action here it's
actually not the path of two
so that's the expression value
calculates
uh but now using this uh gaussian
integral formula
we can
Express the result in terms of this Z of
J
uh so what is that so the result of this
is
um
uh so uh
zero
um so what is that
um well uh you can think of this as
um so how would you how would you relate
to the topics I think something like
this
um if you take a derivative of Z of J
with respect to J
uh you just pull down a insertion of
queue
uh
J twice uh we're back to J twice you
just pull down two factors of Q and so
forth so you can write this this thing
as F of uh
B by D J
derivatives we then set J to zero
uh what do I mean by this uh
or more generally okay they're serious
uh so a function of F is a series
and Q right and uh every time you see a
qn you're replaced by V by DJ that's
what I mean by this this thing so it
turns this function into a some
differential operator which acts on this
DJ you just take you taking derivatives
and after you do that you set J to zero
and then you get this equation back
any question about this
um so here we say the reputational and F
of Q that's definitely the normal cue
that's not been shifted by Chain right
uh this is the definition literally
right this is the defined to be this
experience later we're going to apply
this to uh to the value of operators on
the mechanical system but for now this
is my definition
oh I'm just talking because no there's
no j
so but I can relate it to the thing with
the tag by first starting with your
number J I take derivative and after
after
this exponential of J dot Q goes away
but I'm still definitely the peculiar
surface so the future is just some
arbitrary some some are very parameter
which we use as a tool but at least
just for convenience
oh this is just a simple bookkeeping
device for for activities of calculation
um so uh for example uh let's look at
some examples uh simple examples uh so
uh qn expression value
um now this is just uh
I mean we know this it's just because of
the the integround is the power function
of the view if you have a single q a
circuit but of course you can also see
from here because uh uh the the sky here
if you expand in J is always uh even the
power of J that appears if you take a
single derivative zero other results
so that's of course true
um and if you have a qn commands uh this
is just uh this well let's plug in our
formula
um so
um
so for this uh purpose uh we don't have
to oh worry about this uh determine a
and combined with these factors because
it's going to cancel between here and
here it's just gonna be some Concepts we
don't care about that in this expression
value uh so this point of theory is just
a b by the this formula D by b j n d by
b j m
huh uh potential of one half uh J
transpose inverse Matrix of a what about
J so let me write out the indices so
call it paq so p
now of course this is very easy to
calculate just expand this uh
exponential but there's only one term
that contributes which is the quadratic
which is determining moment or two J's
it's the first time when you expand this
out or contribute
um and uh uh we act on that term these
two dudes you can account either one of
the two J's to get them Factor two the
cancel game exactly like half and you're
just done with a inverse and then
that's good
um
any questions about this
sorry
all of all of these chains yes so that's
that's what I what I meant
the J vectors
um okay so uh let's do a starting one
complicated example
uh there's this uh
electorates will become uh
useful later
um so let's look at four queuing
surgeons uh the three cubic friction
again will give people zero because of
the symmetry of Q goes to minus q but
let's look at the fourth two
instructions so so this would be uh
uh
d by D okay n d by b k m
d by d j r d j s of e to the one half J
transpose a inverse J transpose with a j
zero
okay uh so of course the only term that
will contribute
is uh
uh the thing that's
quadratic in the exponents so one over
two factorial so let's bring
it
it's just that
now of course you can you know calculate
that uh but uh I'm going to uh draw a
picture that represents this uh that
will help us uh keep track of the the
commentatorics
[Music]
um
well actually for this purpose maybe a
bit of Overkill but I will draw this
picture anyway
um so it's kind of a useful uh way to
think about the common Turks okay so so
um let's write this as
uh so there's some backup one house
because I have a 1 8 here number eight
times something
uh what do we have uh well there are
various ways the derivative can act on
this case
um so uh several times I will specialize
especially how we do the sound or just a
moment
um now uh so I'm going to representative
with the external line here it's in the
stand and uh and uh r and s
um
and uh the stuff uh oh sorry this is the
transverse here
right so
um here uh
uh every time I have a fact of the this
J A inverse J I'm going to represent
this by uh a Vertex with two lines
coming out
um and then
you know this by a inverse uh with the
in the sense that uh you know if I take
the derivative all I need to do is to
connect uh connect the uh the lines
so
um
um so for example uh if I take this
derivative on that I connect this line
then take this derivative of that Jack
like this line and I read out the result
a inverse NR for the result okay so I
just need to look at all the possible
way to connect these blue lines uh to
the white lines for example uh here is a
way to do it like like this I can
connect this with that stick like this
with that and this is one connect and
then you can do whatever way you want so
here the sum is all possible all
possible
uh
uh ways
to connect
the the right line to the Bulldogs right
uh and uh and how many ways did they
have and in this case the the number is
uh equal to four factors
four different ways to
um the permutation of the four uh four
legs
um and uh uh so uh so in total uh you
will end up with uh uh 24 terms here but
there's a pack of one over eight and in
fact uh there are only three different
types of terms and if you respect this
it's not hard to convince yourself the
result is just a inverse and M
a inverse RS plus uh some permutations a
inverse uh and r
a inverse and I guess
um and Q and universities and R right so
so that's the results
um
uh uh I collect every white line to
every blue line and once I connect them
that's that's gone and I connected the
remaining so so I have to connect since
I have to pair up is that there's white
lines with the blue lines Why do I have
to do that because I'm taking derivative
this is
this can be connected to any one of them
any one of the white lines right so okay
I can connect this to any one of these
white lines let me remember the fact
that this derivative fact on each of
these drapes and it will give a
contribution
so so this is just how you take a
derivative it's nothing so so the result
is uh the sum of these three times
uh any questions so far yes so how would
so like the the specific one you draw
correspond to one term yeah yeah that's
what
it's on this one there eight uh
identical contributions
contribution for example uh you can you
can switch the video around and it's the
same and the answer is the same but
there is another term
so I'm just saying that until the a
program you have 1 8 times 24 terms but
that's inconsistent with that actually
end up with three times like this
um
uh but in fact uh you can uh this is
actually uh incredible Overkill Because
the actual answer is a much simpler way
to to phrase the answer so let me just
explain that
um so you can calculate the usually
uh you can generalize this example and
derive a rule for calculating the
equation value in this respect to the
calcium integral of the arbitrary number
of hue insertions as follows so
um generally uh we have a Q and Q and Q
R let me know whatever
so when you have a you want to tell the
the expression value of this we're back
to the scholarsity and integral
um and uh so this can be calculated by
uh well usually called the weak
contraction
um so uh let me is this
um some of uh or any equivalent
um
uh with contractions well I mean that
we're contraction I'll explain that in
the listening
uh so
um uh I again write down this sequence
of the cues but let me just write a few
more you I'll uh whatever
okay so an example of the weak
contraction is uh if I
uh if I uh connect a pair of excuse like
so you can like any pair I want but I
cannot uh but every time I can talk with
you that the spirit is gone then that's
repeat so I'll break down for your
contract this with with that maybe this
with with that so this is a possible
with instruction
and every queue has to be contracted if
you have odd number of Cubes the result
is zero it's only even number two
um and uh and there's no order in the
contraction so so if I can track you
enter Q out qn I'm not ordering uh and
also there's no order with back to the
different instructions so so
um so there's no other uh if I contract
this Q and The Q Alpha first uh and qm
with new gamma second or the other
around it makes no difference so
um I'm only going to sum over distinct
ways of the contraction which I mean by
all the in the equivalent
uh and the claim is that uh so for
everyone contraction
so this is a notation so every weak
contraction this is going to be uh
defined to be uh this a inverse
and then the current exam
uh and uh and you see that uh this
applies uh to the previous case right so
in this example uh if you know that we
can talk a rule then you don't have to
bother with the picture and just say
this could cover this let's connect this
and then there are two more in
equivalent contractions and you're done
uh and this one's General okay so so
that's that's
how you will generally calculate the
value of Armature number of Cubes
inserted in this legality integral
okay so all of this is just doing Simple
gaussian integrals nothing two things
uh so uh first of all you'll agree that
there'll be 24 charts
it's four factorial
uh and uh so uh it'll be one over eight
qualified by 34 terms contributions
uh so for example I can swap these two
legs
because you know I can connect this to
that uh listen to this that that's one
permutation against what these two and
then as well
go home and do all kinds of examples
yes um
you know the version of this will need
to uh you know what's uh I guess
preparing for that okay
um uh any other questions yes
uh in fact do you mean the Innocence
uh no I don't know there's no
restriction right so so in fact we saw
an early example of this day in verse
was actually only 9-0 with that and M
are equal uh so it's a general depends
on you know yeah so so we're going to
depend on whether a inverse Matrix is
so I'm saying that for Arthur n and M
this contraction the result is by
definition a inverse but inverse
measures of age the NM entries
that doesn't matter
let's quickly explain the rule version
of Harley Davidson
yes so so I have more cues yes uh so one
concussion is this uh the second
contraction
is uh one two three two to four and then
I can have uh one to four a two to three
yeah and that's it there's nothing more
again there's no other specifications so
that's it
and so the sixth which is another
example
I
always gonna be
uh uh once you go to this formula this
is a true formula okay you can try to
prove this if you want I'm not I'm not
going to to prove on the board but you
can try to improve it but in this
formula there is no contrary character
there's no coefficient one because the
sum of like once we get before oh uh uh
wow there's a number of terms you can
calculate it's not well it's not for
factorial because this is this example
it's a three okay
it's generally going to be you know
whatever uh and I like them to
annotations if the N factorial divided
by some one yeah it's whatever it comes
out that explains this exponential so so
it's going to work out
uh but you know you are invited to to to
try to improve it yourself but I I won't
bother with that proving this I'll just
assert this is true you have to trust me
uh any other questions yes
what other things there's no other
things right here
got 20 points
that's right these are only three things
but it cannot be anything else
uh all right
um okay so um now we're going to
generalize all of this which are for
finite dimensional intervals in this
discussion uh to uh the function of
lowercase
um this translation is more or less
straightforward but uh
um the only thing I want to explain is
uh
there's a little bit of detail that that
you're not care about you can't they can
do the normalization
how this works so we're not now I'm
going to generalize
uh to uh gaussian uh
functionalism
um so that means uh instead of
considering some n dimensional Vector Q
uh this Q Vector is going to be replaced
by let's say a few of Tau in our
mechanical model but this could be much
more General but now I'm just
considering function of one variable
because this variable being the we can
protect the time for an answer
uh right so so you should think of this
as
uh viewed
as a vector so this is a function and we
want to do this as a vector in the
linear
price
of
real functions
uh subject to some additional assumption
on functions which I will not uh
uh go beyond the level of mathematical
rigor I'm working with right now so I
would not specify that I'll just say
that q q account uh you know it's a
function Tau but we're going to view
this as just like this Cube as a vector
in a linear space of functions so for
example uh those qns remember we started
with QR pal but I'll respect the
functions on this uh interval between
minus p and t and we said that the
boundary conditions for the Q to vanish
at end points so that was made the
function so what some of the space the
functions on that interval the
advantages the advantage of the
endpoints the unlatchment function in
the cube I can expand on some arbitrary
Fourier bases and then got this Q an
coefficients but the Q and Company
tribute the QA coefficients has nothing
but the compressions of some Vector with
a personal basis uh Vector that you
choose on this infinite dimensional
space of functions okay so so that's
that's uh
um and so uh now this uh uh SC is going
to be whatever action uh the the
euclidean action they're going to be
working with
um I'm going to specialize onto the
bottom of this in a moment and this J
dog with q
um it's going to be replaced by uh while
Q is going to be a function now so this
dot product which sum over the indices
is going to be something like an
integral so let me write something like
integral of the Tau uh J or Tau Tau so
this J Vector is now also going to be
replaced by a function
um
and this that product is going to be
replaced by some intervalent Tau J Tau Q
attack but anyway uh you should be minus
the J still is just a bookkeeping device
that we're gonna eventually take a
derivative or function with back to J
and extract the correlation
functions of Interest
foreign
we're going to try to put the action in
the form of this Q transpose a q uh so
this a which with the Matrix The Matrix
a that appeared I guess I erased it uh
is now a linear operator
on the space of uh functions in the one
variable here in this example uh right
so a before it was it was a matrix the
multiply on the back to give you another
Vector so now a is a function between
another function so uh
now and it gives you something uh so far
in the
in the example of the
harmonic oscillator
I'll say another example
uh this was a very simple uh
[Music]
operator it's going to be minus the
accounts where the Omega Square
why do this we remember what was that
what was in the exponent so but
the harmonic
because
uh an action integral detail one half of
the cloud Q it's worth plus Omega
squared this one lower than you
including action so all I'm doing is I'm
integrated by Parts by parallel right
this is you now one half to do in front
q1 L minus the without squared plus
Omega squared
and this is what I call a
right so um
so so a that is replaced Now by a
completely defined in this way just
adapt it to the example of the harmony
operator uh but we're going to be
interested in a inverse
so the inverse Matrix of a which uh
whose analog here will be the inverse
awkward so what is the inverse operator
uh well
um
uh what's the inverse what's the inverse
of that differential operator
uh well uh by definition it should be a
convenient it doesn't have to be
differential operator because they're
they're more General linear operational
function than they can be derivative
they also do it works
um so all you have to be is something
that if you act with a again it gives
you back here uh so uh in fact this the
answer is that it's integral you now
Prime of sound G Count top Prime
Q of prime uh where G is some function
uh well I guess I'm using this same
notation as this G earlier but this
paper right is the difference in this no
at this point there's not a lot of
relationship and the brilliant G even
though there won't be a relation and you
see later but so far there's no
connection this is just some function
all right so what does this do you have
to obey well first of all this is
currently leading
um but you need a property that if you
act on this again
a few
um this year this will be
um
square plus Omega squared
at least if you can assume you can
exchange the order of the derivative by
this integral which you can use it at
some nice convergence property event
um all this requires is uh is that this
thing icon G which should give you the
Delta function
that is you want uh minus the power
squared plus Omega squared I know g l
Prime is Delta function
foreign
the boundary or an Infinity but we'll
come to that in a bit but the G has to
at least obey this property
where this uh well this statement to
make sense but there's a universal and Q
should be uh
um okay
so
um now
uh
uh so the thing we're going to be
interested in
uh is uh is is
represent values like like this
but more generally if you have more
through instructions but as you might
expect uh you know this is going to be
calculated by the same weak contraction
rule so actually uh all you can do is to
figure out what is the single weekly
track and why isn't all that you know
how we can do this for arbitrary number
two insertions
this one
well we've already encountered this but
now let's do it in a in a more uh
Elegance uh manager
uh so let me write this as a
uh so I'm going to use a shorthand
notification for this so this I'm just
going to write this one half above Q uh
in a product with paid Q uh so um by
this I just made a q Tau integrated
against a I can't hear whatever
so so this is just a location
um
uh by the way uh from now I'm going to
set H bar uh
um
thank you
q a one two
uh divided by
which is
okay uh so now uh you might say oh we
already know how to how to do this the
result is a inverse n and M but what is
n what is M what you meant to say it's
requested by Prime but uh
so this doesn't quite work okay so you
have to be very careful with that uh
with the normalization uh strategy
speaking if you want to really follow
repeat the previous derivation and apply
to this case you have to describe an
integral of steps
um but you have to worry about is this
measure factor which is the decimal uh
that's more step of course so so uh if
you keep track of that you can derive
the correct answer uh but um for the
purpose of clarity of expedition I'm
going to uh give you a shortcut
um and um
without having to go through all their
steps so I'm going to describe that
trick so uh let's look at this numerator
here
um so I'm going to rewrite the numerator
in the following way so that's going to
be written as integral BQ uh I guess no
one two
um uh so
um
due to the uh minus one yeah remember
this was the Italian
thank you
um so I've got a cue of pal one here pal
two uh but I'm going to write the Q of
Taiwan in the Holy way we're going to
write q a one importantly
uh
as
um minus a inverse actually
um B by B Q of a lot
uh so you see what that is do well this
is a function of derivative so so in
this box are derivative hits on this
Cube we can do the icon this Q right on
this Cube then on the first Cube I'm
just gonna get minus one have a cube
if I pack on a second the result
actually will be the same by the
integration by parts on this operative a
okay
um so
so the result of this function
derivative I can have this exponent uh
is just going to give me it's just going
to pull down from the exponents uh the
two terms the factor one half okay
cancel minus uh AQ and so that kinds of
the case is minus I'll get back to Q so
you think what
okay so so so so this expression here is
the same as the numerator
it's just a numerator
all right
um and um
um uh and a simple trick I'm going to
apply is that uh you know
um
this whole thing
can be used as the first order
differential operator on the cubes
at least in this case uh in the Galaxy
integral the measure is simple enough
that there's a transmission very
consumed again so it's very important
part so instead of this acting on that
is equal to minus of this
so by the functional integral by part uh
I just get this I can that so I have
principle DQ from e to the minus the
action uh then I get minus the two minus
signs okay so we'll just get a inverse
um
d by d q L1
Q down two
and then this function here it is just
by definition delta of Tau y minus Tau
two and if I act on that with a inverse
going to that formula just plug in the Q
of Tau Prime in the Delta function the
result of this is uh so anyway
is equal to this partial function uh
times so the expanded value here
expression value here this whole thing
is just going to be equal to a g
over Tau one
so it's a a inverse
um
foreign
[Music]
to get to the answer just using the
general property of an integration by
parts at the functional integral level
um and that's the result of this
experiment value which is the same as
the contraction the one you have that
can calculates arbitrary
number of students that's very important
so so this will from now replace this
paper calculation we did at the
beginning of the lecture where we had to
detected finally everyone take some
limit that was the pain and this is a
much quicker way to get to the end
um I I haven't showed you
bottom gear
now what is this economic Q by
definition is the other function this is
right so so the result is a inverse
actually on a function with the function
the function is Delta of power minus L2
that would be the variable
foreign
okay
information
NOTE END VIDEO M0py5a4RWhE
NOTE BEGIN VIDEO 4: vk_RlYUKUyM (2022-09-15)
NOTE JSON3 SHA-256 0b1a086f5babdf7e78c0bba97f00a61909231341106549195d256c30be9500b0
NOTE VTT SHA-256 435d8b50e283ed3a2382a8066babac9f187a96ce8dfa527c14282c68afed913c
Kind: captions
Language: en
thank you
um where we were again the last lecture
uh so we were considering a gaussian
type uh hat in the world where the uh
the related versions uh where uh our uh
variable was this appeal of this week
for his time uh and we considered the
case where the action could be
originated in this very general form you
can tell uh
where a is on a differential operator uh
so foreign
uh and the main result would be right
last time with that this thing is equal
to actually G of L1 is now two where G
is the nuclear internal the appear in
the inverse of the operative a so uh so
here this G but that's that a reverse I
can do a Tau uh it's supposed to be
integral detailed Prime g t Prime uh
Prime and uh uh you know in this case
for example uh it follows that the gene
would have to pay the equation that if
you take this dimensional operator say
just look at the Delta functions
um
uh and uh let me just uh carry on this
one more step uh this G uh in the case
of times agrees with the form of G I
wrote previously you haven't used the
same letter and it was actually the same
function so you see
um I can solve this equation uh by oh
yeah times one it's right on the answer
and it's easy to verify that the
solution to this equation uh is such
that D is equal to integral APK over 2i
and this Romans Infinity of uh e to the
i k times
over a case where plus Omega squared
so you can easily verify this because if
you take the dimension operator and act
on this thing here in the integrand
right you just pull down a k square plus
Omega Square tons of government this is
gone and the integral is just means
so at the beginning of Last Action we
did all that work but with some finite
times T minus capital T and we took some
limit and we got the answer but that's
actually can be reproduced by this you
don't have to
all right uh any questions about this so
far
all right so uh now let me just make a
comment about uh this expression value
um I've explained this yeah
this like the whole I mean the whole
person that we did um
correlation like the whole body like
when you don't want the normal season
budget right or well there's one just to
have been divided into these two right
so it's really nice in the measure
now uh
uh I hope you remember the physical
origin of this we had a different
interpretation levels there's one in
some kind of statistical average in our
original interpretation this came from
the analyticulation about actual Matrix
elements all right let's recall
so uh value from the left-hand side is
actually equal to
um
before
you missed that from our previous
discussion okay so uh
the way we derived this last time you
know there's no how and how to or
arbitrary right but the client said in
order to write this as a matrix elements
uh with this Q being the anti Convention
of the uh the original queue to UK and
time to do the time tab uh but this
right inside only actually makes sense
with power too fantasy recall it only
follows one power great and help you why
was that
um uh it's because if you if you spell
this out in a little more detail you see
the right hand side if I plug into this
way of writing that you had a Tau it's
um you saw that it's not now uh foreign
foreign
[Music]
and this is going to diverge
exponentially and the sound that will be
only fine so 84 right uh you know this
query generic system uh this right hand
side would only be well defined
um but in case I'm not answering some
coincidence because actually most of
these all except one-time Dropout but in
that case it doesn't matter so much but
generally you should understand this way
uh just don't make this just to say this
in a different way
um in the
um in the way I wrote this path of the
world uh uh the the you know there's no
watering okay without two and by
definition these are some very intuition
variable so by definition
the same the same in the middle of there
no difference like definition doesn't
care about the weather but the right
hand side in this case is only to be
bind with a state reporter the other one
is it doesn't make sense this operator
back on the vacuum if it's Taiwan it's
better than how two the sequence of
foreign
uh the real time
many I have a choice notation but
whenever I write key it's real time
it's uh it's uh uh it's the imaginary
the quicker time right so so this real
time QT this is supposed to be a pizza
that uh i h e u h
minus five
um and uh for this in a usual quantum
mechanics uh this you have here the
permission operator and this major
element are well defined real time if
you want these two so this is defined uh
without any restrictions uh you want to
do
um as it should be
um but uh the thing is that these two
lines often is not compute General
and uh we discussed a particular
instance where you can perform this
energy potential and release this uh to
this with a specific order of common
something
okay so so you know if you find this uh
confusing you know always go back to the
definition and see what's going on I'd
like to think more about this
yourself
but the point is that we have to be a
little careful of the different objects
which are closely related but
conceptually different than what I've
been talking about there's their Matrix
elements of these uh the skill height
operators uh evolved in real time
there's this uh which is related
calculation and then there are these
significant values computed from the
which are they pathway and as you see
they're closely related but they're not
exactly
the one we should look at
the little property they're full
but sorry what would you say okay
there's another thing
oh you're the time boilers uh let's post
on that discussion uh so far you know
you can Define whatever you want you can
choose to you know multiply this by some
functions
um but of course you know as a some
function that capture the information
the Spectrum the theory like so they are
not independent uh the time ordered
object will have some specific use
um the contents but let's post on that
discussion because so far it's not
obvious why that's a that's a useless
uh let me just say that so far I'm going
to discussed Ace visit evaluation that
works uh if you want to do something
different you have to uh you have to
show that it works well you close the
controvers uh let's talk about the
discussion because in order to explain
pictures so they take some time and this
is uh not necessary for what I'm about
to say
any other questions about this
uh what what this discuss the another
property of these teleporting functions
in the actual Quantum filter context a
more detail later but for now I will
only uh say what I what I actually read
soon
what
um
uh and let me just uh uh
uh make the additional remark that uh
this quantity here of course we actually
can do last time this is actually using
the radio formula this whole integral is
uh one over two Omega e to the minus
Omega is
whenever I write command two is
and uh if you compare it to this
normally you see that this Omega is
indeed that the difference between E1
and e0 so that agrees
that guy said that's very very simple
right we just get a single exponential
in general if there's a q hat zero and
the grass and has overlapped with the
other excited states you have the sum of
a bunch of exponential not just a single
explanation
uh this kind of thing over in the
content called the special decomposition
uh we'll have more to say about that
later
okay so uh
to example example two we're going to
discuss the first example so now the
second example uh after oscillator is uh
the N Harmony
is not harmonic
um so so what is this well this is a
specific thing that's okay instead of
this squared plus uh oh so um I'm going
to uh set this Omega uh also to one for
the for the sake of discussion because
uh you know here I keep track of this
frequency omega-coming oscillator but
the uh for the for from now you know we
don't need to worry too much about that
I'm just going to set that to one so the
harmonic acid will just be uh described
with hamiltonian P Squared however two
plus Q Square over two uh then I'm going
to add a quartic potential sorry
something like Q to the fourth uh but
just for the sake of convenience our
normalize this conversion should be some
can be constant G over four factorial
this is just a convention so there's
some number G here LG is a
so the G is there is some coupling
constants
uh it's just a conversion of a recording
terminal potential
okay
um so uh as a a system of quantum
mechanics uh you know how to study this
in principle you know you can solve the
energy levels by selling showing the
equation by normalizable and so forth
right so the advantage of discussing
this in the Practical language is that
we're always grounded you uh you can
always if you get confused always go
back to your undergrad economy kind of
textbook and figure out how to study
this uh the The Observers of Interest
any kind of uh you know energy Spectrum
or Matrix elements of
observations of interests like this Q
hats exhibition patterns
okay so but now again we're going to
study this using the path integral
okay
um so uh so first step we're going to
write lagrangian uh well that's
straightforward is still the kinetic
term uh minus the potential term right
which is this and uh and of course uh
you know we're going to play the same
game of the week rotated
um which is more convenient for our
purpose uh so
um the euclidean version is just uh one
half Intel Q squared plus squared over
two
okay so any question about the system uh
we are considering for continuing
all right so um once again uh we're
going to uh study uh a quantity like
this
or a computer using pattern to grow as
the president of this qt1 qt2 and
starting the pattern go exactly the same
as well as out here uh all I need to do
is to uh erase so I can actually recycle
this board everything on this board uh
still always except for them or
except that I'm going to erase this
formula okay so so this is very true and
I'm gonna erase of this
but uh but everything else still holds
uh
uh actually no okay
this is the business
foreign
okay so um so now if you are actually
able to calculate you see this uh two
point expression value you will be able
to read out information about the energy
spectrum of this Theory and the energy
spectrum of this oscillator well does
anyone know the switch what is the
energy eigenvalue of this in terms of G
between the two energy
situations uh no no no no oh let me say
as soon as you impossible so the
potential is like this
right so so let's say
the potential
uh looks like this
okay so so you know we have some energy
levels but whatever is energy levels in
other computes
uh
you can try but
the good news is yes get the provision
Theory values is that it doesn't
converge
but uh but but uh we're gonna try to do
it anyway and uh at some point what this
will come back and revisit uh the
district so yes you can do Hamilton
Theory but we're going to do the
lagrangea version of that
um
right so uh if you know the exact answer
to this two-point query function you
would be able to expand as a uh you know
as some obviously it's a sequence of the
sequence of exponential in principle and
read off and as well so so the capital
of the information you want yeah in this
case uh unlike the harmonic acid which
you had the ground said only had overlap
with the projects United States um
that's no longer true here this here the
cue pattern on the grounds they will
have overlapped with the first executive
State uh uh and uh uh and many an
infinite Tower
further exciting things
um
uh okay
um so
um
uh so uh we we just need to figure out
how to compute uh both the numerator and
the denominator with this uh Action Now
deformed from the from my alternator by
this according
um okay so so how do we do that uh let's
start with uh the denominator
okay so let's start right with this you
just want to do that let's call this the
normally the proximate function uh Z and
let's calculate responding
now certainly speaking uh we are not
going to
um know uh from this the way I probably
in this way there's some ambiguous
normalization uh and uh
um but you'll see uh where this thing
shows up uh but the point is that uh
whatever ambiguity there is It's Gonna
Cancel out in the final answer so not
enough worry too much about the
ambiguity in doing this stage of
computation
um so so let's try
um
uh so uh V is uh
into the uh
until uh so we separate this into two
terms so first we have the harmony
operator uh action which by itself would
be right to a gaussian type functional
integral and then we have the we have e
to the uh minus uh now uh so uh G over
400 kilo count to the fourth
um so
uh uh
right now uh we're just gonna uh well
the only thing we we know how to we
don't even know how to deal with this
anyways at the moment is to uh just
expand exponential so it was small
exponential uh I can rewrite re-express
this as of course the sum a little n
from 0 to Infinity one over and
factorial of uh minus uh some G over
complex operating outside integral
to the board uh
uh and uh
um no
um if you assume
uh if you assume that uh you can't
exchange the order on functional
integral with the sum over little n uh
then we'll be able to conclude this term
by time and each term is of the form of
the equation value well not by the
existing value but it's the the gaussian
integral of a bunch of probably a bunch
of queues and we knew how to do this
last time we introduced this rule of the
wick contraction uh that would allow you
to recover this turn by turn right so if
you can exchange the order of some as an
integral
um but then you can compute this the
right term and then we're in good shape
any questions so far
uh so now uh as most physicists might
have received if I assuming that you can
always
but uh but there's not that it doesn't
work it turns out that you cannot quite
do that uh however there's a sense in
which
um you can uh
the thing is in terms of what happens if
you change the time of the integral
um the sum actually uh
um will not uh actually converge so
we'll have zero radius converters in G
um but
um uh but none of us would be correct
but it captured all the all other series
expansion what happens that the the
actual current function as a function of
of G uh is actually not the real
analytic
um and uh it entire series doesn't
conversion itself
um but for now we're going to ignore
that problem for now we're just knowing
too
um uh but you know this is this is the
extent of which QED device
which means you might but
so so this problem can be partially
cured as you see uh but for now I'm
going to ignore this individual and
Transformers
um
okay
so
um
you can do that and you can exchange the
order of the of the sum and uh uh and
that function integral uh then
um uh we can say that this is the uh at
some value G uh so I'm using the Z sub G
to denote the uh
is it because you have G to denote the
the primary function at a particular
value of G of the copy
um and if I compare this to the very
function as zero copy which will just be
the that of the harmonic oscillator
um then uh that that is just uh equal to
uh the expression value of this quantity
um
zero
uh Theory
it was Zero model
um Q of Tau one uh to the part
uh Q of Tau n
so there's two of zero and I.E the the
the quantum
or are we now integrating over top one
to seven
uh on this experience you know I I'm
just writing this out right I mean you
know I have this integral to n power I I
better change in my variable if I want
to write them as a as a single integral
I I was renaming the variable
and different tasks
all right and and of course as you might
have noted I have secretly exchanged the
the song with the integral uh you know
you might have uh Mr missed that dude if
at the end point it out but but uh you
know these things are actually more
subtle than you might have thought
uh but anyway we're gonna proceed so
this is really importation but we're
going to proceed
management with us
um okay
that's the integral over to cube right
uh that this is integral over at DQ uh
by the weighted by just this action so
so that would be that's why I write a
subscript uh g code zero or in the
officer Theory so so this will be the
extreme value of the product with excuse
uh in the gaussian function interval
yes
remember I'm divided by the two zero
here
how are we able to write and like as a
factor like exactly things now you could
after all we're doing it yourself and
that gas is part still depends on that
right all of the acute house are
different parameters different variables
for every now two times the variable or
something
so you can think of this as that is if
you want uh but uh the talent is labels
which variable we're talking about
they will show something in there of
course I think we're in there
so that's why you wrote it
uh yes ah maybe you're asking why am I
allowed to pull this integral outside of
the
expression value
but I can because uh you know literally
by definition this is just a sum of
different variables
um
by definition you're saying that it's
just going through early there is
execution
yes that is by definition
this thing is integral of detailed one
to tell one to the course zero Utah two
to the part uh and so on and so forth
now
is
that for some of our uh
uh okay so uh now uh so you know we just
took a few of this and this we have
learned from the last lecture that will
get confused from the weak contractions
so we did this one so let's just do that
um
so let's move this border by order uh
the little end
well of course at the living water is
this one right so this whole thing
starts at uh one let's correspond to the
term angle angle zero uh and then
another n goes one what do we have we
have
minus G over four factorial times
integral detail of uh just to tell
uh I'll just write sub square root of
zero this is in the in the theory so
that's again the harmonic acid Theory uh
and uh and then the next one that we
have one half uh minus G over four
factorial uh squared integral detail one
Theta two uh for your value of computers
support
okay so let's look at this uh one at a
time but let's look at this let's
quantity here so what is this
uh well let's remember our rule the last
time I wrote this I wrote u n q m q r q
s uh but that's you know that's how it's
the level just like this n and M
subscripts
um so
um uh so of course
at the same time but that's not uh it
doesn't matter okay so let me just write
this out uh and the liquid contraction
tells us that it's going to calculated
by uh you can track them this way
uh so I represent this by
uh revertise
so every kind of uh um every time I put
down a pack of G I get uh the insertion
of four queues and same value now
um and um uh I'm just going to draw a
diagram uh to keep track of the fact
that every time I have a Vertex accounts
with this coefficient so it comes with
this coefficient uh minus a geode report
so I'm going to associate this this
formula here I'm going to have something
with a graph where this vertex is
represented backpack there's this uh
multiplying this whole thing uh but then
every white line that comes out on the
board from this vertex uh correspond to
a q insertion and these white lines are
tied to at the same point uh this
represents the fact that all the cues
are at the same value of euclidean times
I'm not gonna
keep writing that
um so um
and then
the which contraction
is just some way you can tie these uh
white lines together with uh these
uh bird boxes what I call it a g earlier
there was the inverse of the Matrix a in
the Galaxy integral that I discussed
last time
uh now uh there are three different ways
to do it between practice right so so we
saw that last time but in terms of the
picture we can say that there's this so
you
you draw the vertex you fix these white
lines but then you just can we can
choose different ways to to contract
these this white line together with this
um
G uh so and then there's one more ways
you can connect this with that and this
would
and of course as you might see that they
are actually all identical so you have
three copies
at the same time
and what you actually uh have for the uh
purple line here well this purple line
supposed to represent a cute Tau you
know the community house
um could be a different house but here
it is
so that's according to our goal uh this
was uh G of power and how two I thought
what I'm talking about
uh
uh it was one of our two Omega you know
Omega to one this country is actually
equal to
um
okay uh any questions so far
point so when we didn't work with
children now
the contraction last time we did it as
like a main event e to the Q some Matrix
to right and uh yeah but you remember
the end result of that contraction was
just that excuse now one uh could help
to contraction uh with the same thing as
the extreme value of 3.12 right and then
we just can in the beginning of lecture
we said that
speak of this Matrix
or convince yourself
okay any other questions
um all right so uh so let's put this
together and calculate the like one or
two terms in this expression
uh okay so uh the order G term in this
expansion in the of z uh is just as we
see here minus G over 34 times 3 because
there are three identical diagrams and
each one of them is going to be now G of
Tau Tau squared
uh
yeah
okay
uh so it's good that we calculate this
with another squared uh the the values
is that this appears to be Divergent
because you're integrating uh the
content uh in Tau
all right
uh any questions about this
the complaints
well uh you know we said that you know
we're going to run into some issues with
very toxic but this is going to be uh
in in the immediate stage uh we're going
to interpret this Divergence soon and
figure out a way to to fix the problem
uh in fact this is uh as often occurs
here it's a feature another bug
yes so what is integrated
there is no power two and power one
right I mean this is where it comes from
remember this came from the term in the
action it's just into a detox that was
in action there was no difference
between Taiwan County they're all just
power
compels
right so that's right yeah
any other questions
thank you
um
okay this because in this case how are
how how our knowledgeable they're not
like problems right I mean a towel is a
it's like an index right yeah
uh okay good so so so so we'll revisit
this uh Divergence later and we'll see
what it means
uh we have something uh well okay so
what do we have we have one now uh minus
G over four factorial squared and you
tell one you tell two
um q a one uh to the fourth Q now two to
the fourth uh again completed in the
Galaxy well
um and we're going to uh first turn this
into a picture and send a picture back
to the equation
um
uh so uh well that's all our rule
um so we got two furnaces here
uh one will be you can write 1000 to
remind yourself that the car is going to
be two thirds first one to four cues we
started times how one you quickly Factor
one this four Q is at the top two
and then uh where instructed to consider
uh to sum over all the possible weak
contractions of the eight cubes uh now
there are different types of diagram you
can draw you can contract this way
uh
this is this is one diagram you can draw
the corresponder one term in the weekly
fashion the possible with contractions
uh here's another one you can draw so
um you can contract uh like this
right uh you can also do something like
before you can do
I'm not going to uh
exhaustively diagrams but uh here
there's some examples this all right you
guys draw the possible graphs
uh the contractors and you just have to
add them together now what do this graph
mean well this one again is like GTA one
tell one you know what that means and
here so what is this for example uh this
guy here is G Taiwan
this is g l one L2 this is another g l
one l two where this is G now to the top
two oh this function return no there's
some simple functions that we concluded
earlier and just multiply this together
and multiply the coefficients and then
you add that
okay very simple I have the integrator
which is Divergence but don't worry
about that yeah and
a bit uh any questions about this
all right
um
foreign
function would only be well defined if
you do this integration and finally
range
um and without boundary condition
uh we said that you could take the ratio
it explaining value but this
bonification doesn't matter it will drop
out if you take a limit but if you just
can do the D by itself the publication
doesn't matter your homework problem
with some Iranian population
but that doesn't matter
um so here uh in principle uh we need to
uh put this integral declared some some
range and if we take this range to be
very large but not less uh the a part of
that have to be finite so that would
cause this Divergence okay it's
Divergence
um but in order to understand the
potential interpretation of the project
function uh it's going to be useful to
figure out how we want to reorganize all
the diagrams
um and uh we're going to now do a little
bit of uh combinatorics to figure out uh
how to how we can kind of rearrange all
these uh diagrams here
um as you can see
um some of them so already the second
order in G some other diagrams are are
these are connected
graphs
these graphs are disconnected
okay but you see here that the
disconnect graphs are related graphs in
a very simple way you just multiply a
bunch of clinical graphs together right
this corresponds a term in this
expansion but literally just the product
of this term with that term
okay so
um uh so we're going to uh simplify our
life a little bit uh by trying to
express this whole party function in
terms of just the connected graphs
so uh generally at some order
G to the n
so each write the sound each set of weak
interactions
um
can be
represented
by ignac
so every time whenever I say wrap in
this particular context I mean uh I take
a bunch of these coordinate vertices is
with the four lines coming out and let's
connect the legs with the with this
purple uh purple lines
uh so by a graph that uh
uh consists of
let's say uh K connected to components
[Music]
um and uh among among them
among these kinetic components
um uh let's say Suppose there are for
every l
there are ml uh connected
uh graphs
uh but
uh contained
uh
L vertices
huge
so for example
um
so uh so let's say uh this represents
right there contains some L versus uh
and you can have a another graphic
alvertise another graphical
and the total member of this would be ml
minus one
so
uh
the product yeah I'm talking about a
specific uh so this whole thing is uh
what I've been calling a single rap if I
can book and disconnect so this is a
single graph so the total number the
total number of vertices
um okay
um
so
uh okay so first I I don't understand
the K is the sum of an L uh uh
one uh and N is equal to some L times
okay
uh okay so uh for
uh a given
uh partition
of and according to this pattern so I
separate and it is your end into this uh
subsets of groups of L
um
specified by the MLS
um the
a number
of ways
of grouping
the and vertices
in this matter
like so so you know apri uh the point is
that you know you know this verses I can
I can connect them uh in all possible
ways and I want to look at the uh the
possible ways to arrange them into in a
graph of that
um the number of ways to uh group The
invernesses in this pattern is uh n
factorial over a product L greater than
equal to one
um Alpha factorial to the power and L
times
so basically here is just that I tell
you all the presentation of endpoints uh
m versus uh and I divide Us by the
permutation then leave this computer
should be better so that that is uh
again permits within each group of
albertists and I can produce all these
ml groups of America
so that's a different ways to to uh
uh uh let me try to do this so so you
take you take emphasis and then you uh
you group them into uh into like l in
this first group uh in this movement and
this without any kind of the order of
this uh books of film and for every app
so you you pick your setup you pick
yourself ml right uh
so in this case uh in this case m one is
equal to one and two is equal to zero uh
and uh
okay so we have to take all of this into
account
uh that is arbitrary integer right so
I'm just saying that uh three times
these things add up to the Ten Perfect
so n is arbitrary yeah
okay
um
uh so uh here so the total contributions
uh
thank you
um so what do we have in order to do to
the n to the end order
um we've always got this one over n
factorial from expanding out the
exponential at the beginning right
and uh and then we've got
uh this number of ways of grouping
versus this command factorial over
product okay then one now factorial and
L kind of say no
um and then uh and then I have to uh
take the product of all the actual
graphs each one of it which requires
about the formula in the way I described
earlier so uh but that's now easy to
describe I just have a product over L uh
and g l to the ml power where GL
is the sum of of all graphs
um
uh uh uh
all connected to say in a second all
connected uh with contraction some of
all kinetic graphs
uh that uh
uh the same forms
out of
uh quick interactions
um
of L versus
okay
um
so you know this
discussion is that I'm now rewrite
re-expressing the G to the end the other
contribution which involve both
generally connected disconnect graphs
into just kinetic Labs because after all
I knew that the disconnect graphs are
not Independents from the clinic graph
they're just part of Connecticut graphs
but this is the explosive formula they
express this in terms of just the sum of
the kinetic graphic well L vertices
right so so for example if I got uh well
maybe this is okay so for example if you
have three vertices right
then the G to the L here what
um
uh would contain uh contributions like
like this
so so this is included in the G to the L
but uh something like disconnected
like that
like that this will be uh this will be
discarded here
let me just just say this because again
generally every time the sum every time
every this kind of graph will be of this
part so they're just probably graphs
right so so this is summarizing this
formula so the spirit factors are just
different different ways that are given
the same company that's it
[Music]
I mean you also have the input of the
Taiwan tattooism
good
um all right uh so now uh once you
accept this formula it would be uh
what was to accept this formula
um it's uh you can just sum it up
um so Z
is
uh some uh over all the possible
assignment of MLS uh product so it's the
N factor of cancer right so I can just
write this as uh equivalent as a product
called L greater than or equal to one of
one over ml factorial uh and then one
over and just bring the two two products
together I have one over n factorial and
then have one over L factorial G to the
L to the power and to the L
all right so uh this is the same as a
product okay to the sum for it
independently for each L because ml is
independently every l so sum over h m l
uh from 0 to Infinity one over ml
factorial remember this uh ML and the
the this thing here is exponentials this
is equal to exponentiation exponential
of 1 over l g l
uh so um this is saying that actually uh
if I had taken the log of z g
if I had taken the law of dependent
function it would be like itself but
only keep track of the kinetic wraps
uh any questions about this
so it's saying that the sum over graphs
just actually exponentiates uh and uh if
I just compute the kinetic wraps
is taken care of so yeah I'm doing this
characteristics once for all I mean once
we understand this later you know you'll
understand that kind of whenever you
have this is going to grab they're
always going to explanation in this way
you don't have to calculate by hand of
the it's going to grasp on laboriously
it just follows from expanding this
explanation so when you when you expect
you know just say this again if you
expand this exponential you get a
product of those G's right by explaining
this in return expansion and that part
of the juice is going to take taken
account of all the disconnect graphs
with the exact right commentatorical
positions
uh uh I'm
uh I'm not sure why you need that
interpretation of this uh all I'm
describing here is a way to uh to to
compute the permanent function and I I
said what is connected uh provides are
but so far I've not discussed it's
written value yet I mean uh because this
is
okay
um
uh any other questions
yeah so it's a dumb question like where
does it evolve oh gee it's included in
the graph itself so every vertex every
vertex comes with a factor of minus one
minus G over four factorial
uh so maybe I wasn't very clear about
the uh about the about that but uh
computes some number out of this and
what yeah
um no I'm going to so we have GG values
examples so there but like aren't we
taking a product of the uh main
functions and when we're doing I'm not
going to be a functioning yes right so
far oh sorry my individual graph yes
we're taking that yeah yes yes
I mean that there are different graphs
right like three verses that are
connected right so for example there's
this uh there I can also draw different
program right so so there's that you can
enjoy uh I don't know
and all of the possible ways to contract
the three vertices in the case of L
equal three uh uh as long as the whole
thing remain connected
yeah so you understanding before we're
doing this derivation for part either in
a big series
is example uh oh uh yes I should have
written
thank you
so
this or this right so here I'm summing
over all the possible uh uh
decompositions uh so uh
right so so I'm suddenly over so when I
write the sum over this question of MLS
uh I I'm talking about uh I'm something
over all the possible
um uh uh sequence of integers that that
ordered to enable how many N1 and two
and three so this is some over N1 from
uh zero Infinity M2 from zero two to
zero Fitness and so on and so forth
by definition
it's uh you know I I
um
[Music]
maybe
yeah the difference is this this bracket
right this bracket means that I'm
summing over this entire sequence of uh
integers and one and two and three and
so forth I said yeah I'm just send me
over individual one but inside the
product it's the same
also the first one even to find there's
ml before like L is larger than one
um so
um I you choose M1 a sequence
of the meters right
um uh but the only finally many of them
are not zero uh once you have chosen
that uh you take the product over L and
if you see whatever L is put in oh and
now right that's that's how we derive
this so I mean the point is that
um we are looking at all the possible uh
you know partition of integer and
um in this way and every discipline
graph where can I graph will be labeled
by some exclusive ml cool finally
anyway anyway
let's just do this for n up to five and
you'll give yourself that yeah
um
no GL is around here is the sum of all
kinetic Rock when I say when I when I
say the graph I mean that that the
formula the correspond to grab of course
sure all right so so the sum of all the
kinetic graphs the correspond to
distinct with contractions of Albert is
this but they have to be such that the
whole the result of reconstruction is
results in the graph that's connected
uh while the congratic practice doesn't
have to do with with that itself but I
just have to do with high groups so why
is
equal to one and then we get like a
single vertex and that's like um the
right from secondly last class
where do we derive like if it's Q to the
four then it's like one x
three ways
right well I said at the beginning
is
right yes but last time we described
this q n q m q r q s this is the same
thing
you know the weak attraction formula
I mean if you want you can just
discriminize you know there are two ways
you can derive it we can either
discretize all these integral in time
into these three steps that's one way
you can do something or you can use the
simple equation by part trick that we
introduced this last part chart
and the results
but it's a bit more uh a little less
intuitively that way but improve it
um okay uh so uh now let's interpret the
meaning of this so far it looks like I
can produce something that's not quite
physical
but uh in fact it is
uh provide that you interpret it
carefully
this
it
um if I uh take the integration range
say from zero to the type of d
yes
right so this as we said at the very
beginning this is supposed to be uh
actually
um
uh Matrix element of the uh would rotate
in time evolution of it
uh where a Qi give that there's some
boundary condition that secretly this
this cube is subjective
I would have uh please ignoring up to
now because uh It won't always have
emphasize is not important the valuation
won't be important when we take e to the
Finish
uh but if you like the final Advantage
Edition is that you have to keep track
okay
um
um so uh but we're interested in uh the
people continue limits
uh how does this behave uh well uh let
me see uh
so you can you can post hours as sum
over and uh
where and as always in the basis of the
United States
right so uh
let's say uh dominated this is dominated
by
uh by the ground stage by the ground
state
um
and uh so it's just one term so assuming
that there's a unique advantage point
for the moment
um
um you see that log of G
uh is going to be uh minus e0
plus there's something of the other one
so so whatever that overlap is as long
as it's not a zero generically it would
be between zero and two I or two F it's
just going to be some uh only one number
but adding it to this uh term that the
diverges I think it goes to Infinity
uh so in other words uh if you define
the Z and finite parallel t uh there's a
limit P equals infinity of one over T is
log B now this is actually what is nine
this is equal to the minus the ground
state any
now of course here for comparing CG from
C zero uh if you take the log of C zero
this is G by Z zero you just get uh the
difference between granted energy of the
and Harmony oscillator and the harmonic
acid there is a correction due to the uh
a correction energy uh due to the
interaction term this G uh Q to the
fourth
all right
um
no uh we're in a party function no but
the Gap will be uh if we look at the
excision value of you know QQ we're not
doing that right
this is the perfect function so so uh
you know I haven't discussed yet what
happened whether we have a q a search so
this is just a party button itself
because the third part of the process is
something that you thought may not have
a good interpretation because you run
some some overall normalization but you
see here that actually it does have
interpretation
um and in particular is log is supposed
to linear diverge okay this is the
diversion we're talking about earlier
right position this one's in the future
another episode of the book okay
um so
um
uh okay and uh and we speak from this
discussion the log of z
um
uh is the sum over
uh
kinetic wraps
so this is just by how you would do the
uh expansion in G
um like for the Z itself but instead of
looking at autograph we don't look at
diagrams and then what you'll be
Computing is the log of this effective
function and the result of that
is supposed to be out of this newly
Divergence uh it's supposed to give you
the grass at the energy
okay so now let's uh let's put this to a
formula
so for example
um uh well we have already done this uh
at the order G
order G to the one
uh we have done this already right so so
the g g l equals one
so what is this uh this was uh three
times uh this graph so I won't keep
drawing the purple color so you know
what I mean by this
um and let's write the formula for this
right so this is three times uh minus G
over four factorial which is what we
wrote before integral detailed of G
TaoTao
to the fourth
oh sorry I swear
um okay and uh this equal to
minus g o over eight times uh uh
integral in Tau which of course whatever
this but this is the thing that's
supposed to be the capital t uh then
times this G squared this G remember
this so I recall that uh G so the
harmonic oscillator this was the wrote
one over two Omega e to the minus
Omega one two absolute value uh so the G
power tau is there's one of the virtual
Omega and here when we set Omega to one
for Simplicity but otherwise there's one
word to only
um so actually now let me restore this
on my Independence it doesn't matter
absolutely yeah we're clear to look at
um so uh
so because we conclude that
um the ground state energy
of the anthematic operator take the
following form so e zero uh is uh minus
the apart from the the minor sign here
so the minus this plus G over a times
that one or X Omega Square the strip of
this linear Divergence in time so so it
is G over eight uh one over two Omega
squared and then there'll be some other
G squared time which we're not Computing
at the moment
okay so this is actually a physical
uh result right so it's a you know
um and uh
um
you could recover this from hamiltonian
perturbation Theory uh as you burn in
your intro economy candidate class and
uh I wrote this in the note I think I'm
out of time now so I won't write the
Hamilton the combination of this but
it's a you know if you remember how to
do hamiltonian permission Theory so
first of all there you should be able to
easily recover this in that combination
so the resulting should be equivalent
yes no
um if we look at the origin squared
um isn't that ultimate Bridge even if
you decide
no
uh it was only that averages would only
occur if you have disconnected but
remember here we only have delay
diagrams so
if you
at L for the two right if you have this
diagram
yes that would average like t squared
but we don't have this anymore because
by definition this only keep a mechanic
one so it depending once obviously
things like either this or or maybe this
and you can do that there you go you
find that there's only one Divergence
I'll show you the example right now so I
want something right so this is
the Constitutional constant so the
constant resistible we have three
so you look at this integral
this is Convergence
so you only have one linear Divergence
right the whole point is that because of
this G
um
these two points in the measuring time
cannot be very far separated otherwise
this whole thing is suppressed
exponential
yes
is this the first order
Corrections
yes that's what I said I mean I might
check this using hamiltonian
formulations
oh this is uh this is supposed to be
clear now foreign
foreign
um
uh what's living are you referring to
yeah
is that interesting oh yes uh yes uh and
uh that information is not accessible
from here and you see because
that's weird yeah so but uh next time
we'll discuss uh next lecture we'll
discuss uh the QQ but we're not done
because we started by talking about the
particular value I only covered the
compounded it's so humorous
okay so we're going to set a numerator
next time
what is
it oh
um uh well uh this uh this series
well first of all I didn't use the word
number three I think up to this point
but uh uh the second is that the serious
expansion generally were not um zero
radius convergence uh so
um but nonetheless it is true that uh as
a function of G uh the granted energy if
you look at this Taylor series uh this
will give you the current Taylor series
the same is just the Taylor Swift
doesn't actually convert to the function
itself but this um
uh you know I mean this is not something
uh uh too strange uh you know if you
have a
minus 1 over X
right it's about X greater than zero and
this function
right the standard series identical zero
it's modified
uh but it doesn't doesn't converge into
this function
um this is not the example where the
textures itself I mean we're going to
discuss examples but uh
um
you know
there's a very Elementary examples you
can discuss maybe if you're interested
in the infection but
um we will
most did not touch upon this number of
issues uh in this uh in this semester
the number three aspects is the major
topic and then
I think yeah we'll mostly avoid
applications
that
this uh you know numerically
approximately it's still going to work
as long as it's too small there's a
reason for that and uh let me post one
explanation of that
all right
absolutely
yeah
right now
oh
[Music]
um
differences
I realize
NOTE END VIDEO vk_RlYUKUyM
NOTE BEGIN VIDEO 5: 3VG2kDHso08 (2022-09-20)
NOTE JSON3 SHA-256 f860f9bed32130a7a9ee1c378aa112ae4fd949ea969d44cb9708f5f3e632a8e4
NOTE VTT SHA-256 5bb40ce724e6759688913066dbb4e092770441a99960579654e1e8dd8e922046
Kind: captions
Language: en
yeah
okay
um so uh
prom 7 is due today as you probably know
from that uh two uh is um uh has just
been posted
um
now uh uh but at the end of the uh we
need to look at the processor right now
but today's lecture you should know how
to do common one and uh
in the new kitchen set is going to
concern technical field Theory actual
field Theory
um uh and uh you know I think at this
point I mean by next Tuesday you will
know that all the tools to do that but
you can also try to figure it out before
that by trying to generalize what we do
in a one-dimensional quantum mechanical
example which is actually not not so
hard to do
um and uh anyway the the new piece that
is a little bit more substantial than
the previous one and so the due date is
uh slightly over two weeks we do on the
Thursday
all right
um okay so now uh let's continue uh our
calculation of the uh euclidean uh two
point function in the uh
theory of the harmonic object there is
right remember this let's see uh the
graphics
there and we're looking at the graph
State uh expansion value of the product
will be two operators uh and this style
is the imaginary time
and as I also explained last time
emphasize this
um this is a probably only one
as a value only medium tau is a positive
um
uh now let me just comment on that uh
this particular expression as you saw
before
um and this paper right the right hand
side makes sense for power both positive
or negative but the left hand side only
makes sense is when power is
so if I were negative uh you're skipping
into something it's just we can do this
to uh with the water extension
and by exactly the same reasoning as how
we arrived
but anyway but for now let's just
discuss the okay it's part of it
let's be clear
all right and uh the way we're gonna
approach this the last time we studied
this with me on maybe we saw the
denominator
um we're interested in its dependence on
this uh coupling uh parameter G of the
unharmonic oscillator uh and we saw last
time that how we can calculate whatever
in a power series expansion in NG of
this uh now at every order as a result I
was actually Divergent due to this
integration time but we saw about the
integration of that was that would last
the correction the ground state energy
uh the power series engine
finite range of people in time after you
have done the computation both numerator
they take the limit that time range goes
Infinity they're supposed to arrive and
result which is a physically unambiguous
Equity value foreign
okay so the numerator uh
that's right uh according to the lottery
last time we're going to uh just expand
uh the action well each of the minus
action between an action we're going to
just expand this out in a power Series
in G and then we can write everything in
the numerator as uh they already know
how many positive Theory to the G Factor
zero
factorial
and we'll pull down this uh
pass some power and power of uh the
company term in the in the action which
is minus G over four factorial
it will be top Prime Q Prime of this e
to the force both into the N power and
this will be the equipment value taken
in
foreign
uh any questions about this
okay so um so let's look at what this uh
what this term actually looks like what
it is like again uh Builder by order uh
as uh
uh wow I mean we're not afraid of
calculating any kind of experience
in the Galaxy integral again the rule is
just with contracts okay computes
again compute really
um right so um uh so what what kind of
uh contractor do you typically have well
I'll just give you a random example for
instance uh if you have some
and
um
if you have some uh number of these
factors let's say uh material integral
Prime
right right and then you have a bunch of
attackers okay
um so here's one possible contraction so
one thing you can do is that uh you
might uh
you might contract uh let's say this
queue with a q in here so you have to
try this out I wanted to write it out
because
with that
not if you're there okay so now that
removes two of the cutesy here you still
have the two more cubes right so for
example you can try them with each other
you can do that or maybe this
awesome
okay so um now uh and we can represent
this diagrammatically just like people
the only modifications uh compared to
what we did last time but now we have
this extra cues
out here
so the the form of the graph
will look a little bit different so for
example let's just start this example in
this example uh just like last time
there's a cube report turn can be
represented by a Vertex with four lines
coming out each line represents a cube
uh so just to keep track of that let me
label the cues outside with some
uh just denoted by some red dots
all right so let's say you know this is
your Qs how
secure zero just to write this two
remains myself what is going on once you
get familiar with us you will not have
to write all that things but for now
let's let's write this and uh
represented by a line connecting this
red dots to the right leg and here you
have an internal pair of computers
inside the screen support which are kind
of one of these products so you can
disconnect these
uh now of course if you actually want to
calculate the whole thing uh there are
multiple different contractions looking
at the same answer right so you have to
be careful with them with sort of
factors uh we'll come to that in just a
moment
um so in this case uh if the contraction
is well this shape then this part of the
product will just give you the diagram
but we're not done
this this stuff right here but if this
was the case where you see here is that
the result it will be this times some
um let's say other uh graphs uh that are
disconnected from the this one have
drawn here how they're disconnected
and once I grab I mean the number that
represents which is given by the statue
of the interactions
um okay uh so uh it's not hard to see
how this will generalize so generally
um
uh generally
uh
the psalm
of all the of uh well uh uh let's say uh
this this uh extreme value at least in
fact some uh well uh factorized it is
that basically looks like the left-hand
side but with more company stuff in the
middle uh so we have some whatever it is
it will be connected
that's some kind of kinetic graph and uh
with uh these uh
purple legs coming out
and uh and um these uh uh queue now
thank you
so here's our question is the simplest
number example but we can we have you
can draw more graphs about Jordan in
just in just a moments and the question
as you might recall every graph are you
supposed to be keep in mind what is
represents is is a number this number is
calculated by uh
so associated with every vertex we have
a factor of minus two over four
factorial uh there's also integration
over Tau Prime and every purple line
give you a factor that is the this uh G
this uh
so for example in this case it's right
in here what are these purple line
represents this represents uh G uh how
uh Prime right so this particular point
then
represents
uh so so we're gonna have some status
connected uh and then at times uh the
stuff that is
disconnected graphs
um and this disconnect the graphs do not
have any
um
uh uh I do not have any uh assertions of
these rent thoughts the skew or 2000
user
I should say that uh aprara if you allow
arbitrary and interaction time it could
have been that I could also have a
situation where I have the skew outside
here and there was something with
nothing coming come on here and have
some ground over here connected to this
but this kind of diagram is not possible
in our current uh example uh because uh
zero you only have to have you must have
even number of cubes and in this case
every product will have an even number
of Cubes uh so so this will have a
problem review that that's not that's
just going to be zero there's no way
correction but in the homework problem
number two you'll see an example where
where that's not zero but I'm not going
to discuss that right now
all right so uh it's not hard to
accomage yourself that is this whole
thing is just going to be given by it's
in the background in this form where
this works factor is just the sum over
all the possible kinetic graphs uh
connecting to this uh red uh external
cubes uh and over here it's just a sum
of all the parts of disconnected group
graphs uh connecting or disconnect
graphs uh without I say this is
different from this stuff here without
any Q research
any questions so far
um uh but this stuff the sum of all this
stuff a welcome video already this is uh
this is
your last time
okay so uh but we're gonna divide it out
so you see that this is e here uh is
going to uh let's go to cancel against
over there
okay so so we're in luck uh for this
expensive value of a q q is a ground
state uh actually for the graph so even
the last time we studied laboriously
only some of these diagrams uh with no
external cues actually for this
particular problem we actually didn't
have to compute those they'll get
canceled between the numerator
uh but uh we're left with we're left
with this stuff which is a q here Q here
and the whole graph has to be connected
okay
um any question about this so far
foreign
that will be allowed
um so what we see here is that if we're
competing this quantity
um uh
you have to have zero
um so it will include is that we have an
expansion in powers of G
and uh by the way this of course is the
G to the first order there's G to the
zeroth order which is just the leading
term not just the QQ contraction in the
harmonic oxidative Theory so it starts
with the it starts with uh
um
so
this just represents uh uh the factor of
this uh G how zero
there's two point function in the um
uh this two point function in the um
uh later on I'm often going in the
context of discussing these graphs and
associated with this factor of this G
functions I'm also often going to refer
to the G as the propagation uh it's uh
slightly different from the definition
of property in the quantum mechanics
language but this will be the notion of
Provider later on when we discuss Theory
so so from now on I'm always going to
refer to this the G characters
associated with these with contractions
as the property
this
um
and uh uh so that's the first order term
so that's just
um
what we have is uh you tell zero uh so I
only have uh uh this is the diagram I'm
already drawn from here
and this wrap and as I said so up to
some overall uh Factor this is the
different ways to do the contraction uh
this is the only graph that appears so
for now uh even though earlier
um even though earlier when I droved it
through this graph I said every word
that comes with the factor of minus 0
over 4 factorial you have to keep in
mind that the different way to do the
contraction so uh when I write an
expression like this I don't want to
keep writing repeated in the graphs of
the same of the same uh type uh so I'm
just going to use this picture to
represent the sum of all possible weak
interactions so that that has to say
that okay well we'll see exactly what
the factor is in just a moment
um but as you can see there's really no
apart from permutation of these legs
there's no way to there's no other way
to contract
if you only have a once uh vertex
any questions so far
okay so so let's go on
um uh so then we need a two verses
like this
and
so you can have a conversion like this
repeat
uh anything else
what else can you draw well the rule is
that at the next one I said that you
know this is for the G there's no other
G squared or the D Squared have to have
two vertices but you're Contracting any
way uh you want so uh for example
you can have a Vertex here a Vertex here
and you connect them in this way
thank you so so that's that's one
possibility
uh any other possibilities does anyone
see any alternative
are we done at this order
so yeah there's one more there's this
right and uh and then we're done
actually so there's yourself that these
three are the only ones you can control
I just wonder there's really no more
literally this right I mean you know the
graph literally is a weak attraction
right there is a queue there's a cute
if you want to write in this in this
language but let me just write write it
down and let's take let's take this
example let's look at this guy so so
this guy would be
um
foreign
that
all right so so that's that's these two
external lines over here
and then there are three contractions
between these pair of vertices so you've
got three cubes left here so there's one
there's another one and another third
one
so the graph is an easy way to help you
organize uh what are the possible
contractions uh but you still have to do
a little bit of work to calculate how
many uh you know what are the coming
four factors that come in with each wrap
and uh we'll discussed that in a moment
any questions so far and of course the
series continues to hire you can see the
ground I got more and more complicated
um
all right so let's let's turn this uh
pictures into the formula
uh so
okay so um this first graph which is
just uh the probability itself between
the Q at times zero I won't keep writing
the Q I just indicate the the time to
remind myself the first thing is
supposed to be to put the represent from
the formula that is g Tau 0
um and just from now on but I'm just
going to write G like power one power
two and G of the different one we can
tell two because uh uh remember that
this is a time for special invariance so
it only depending on the difference
between Taiwan and Tau 221.
how
this one here's the propagated for this
this QQ two point function for the
harmonic oscillator with Omega sets of
one and uh that means one over two Omega
e to the minus Omega
now I said at the beginning that I have
assumed thousand department but uh if I
use the path label formula this would
also make sense for negative in fact let
me just a mistake that a bit more
explicitly uh from now on I'm going to
write if I write something like q0
um uh in the uh the editorial like let's
say in the um setting I'm gonna just
write this nearly useless if you note
um uh if this is a power that you put it
in time I'm going to use it to denote uh
this quantity
uh
for now on the negative positive or
assuming others the opposite ordering
which is well defined and we're now
negative and the way we encounter this
using the euclidean path integral uh the
Tactical formula is uniform in both
cases so so then I don't have to
distinguish and just use this this is
it works in both cases
all right
um
uh and uh you might recall that there's
a useful uh Fourier transformed
expression for this which will come up
which will be very convenient for us so
um so this geotel is useful to write
deploy a transform the version of it you
can write it as much as well as DK over
2 pi or minus infinity to Infinity okay
uh oh this one's going to be called a g
uh from now let me put a subscript zero
uh just to uh uh to to remind ourselves
that the G zero is this two point
correlator uh in the harmonic
oscillatory not to be confused with a
two-point coordinator in the anjaman
oscillator Theory right so this one now
right as a voltage G but anyway
just remind ourselves
okay
um so
um this guy has a four-year
representation
is the frequency uh well it's not a
group it's a pregnancy
but yeah uh it's uh everything is
real okay
uh and uh you might remember what this
particular case we discussed this
electric couple lectures ago so this was
one over K4 plus one before it was case
for plus Omega squared to not pay for
plus one because I said Omega aspect
it's more Simplicity of notation
all right
um
so that was the problem right there any
questions
okay so let's continue let's look at
this graph the second graph uh is Wonder
G so what is this
uh well uh so first of all uh
uh there is a Tau Prime
so so this vertex you want four cues
um at the time you put in time so there
was uh this integral in Tau Prime
um and uh we've got a doctor of uh minus
G over four factorial from vertex as
always
but on the right we have general account
right so it's a different community and
from here
we have a g
so top Prime and top parameter is zero
so let's do zero at the time yeah
separation too
okay so uh a single with contraction of
this shape will give us that number
uh but we have to remember that uh there
are several different ways to do this
contraction so let's let's remind
ourselves so we've got a q here and here
we go four cues
q and final activity
so how many ways do we have to contract
them
well that's a good run this first queue
with any one of these four I've got four
choices
there's a backgrounds right there's a
back and forth because we have four
choices so once I've made the choice I
can try this cube with one of these
three cubes I got three choices four
times three
and once I made these two choices I have
no more choice because I have two few
left I have to convertible and that's
not what it is contraction so that's it
so I have a factor of four times three
and that's it
so the result of this is uh equal to
minus Z over two uh what is the copy
done that
expression uh well let me just arrange
here so this whole thing is because
minus G over Z
um any questions so far
yes
uh so let me say this again so the first
few contract with one of these four
tubes I have four different choices once
I have made that choice if I could run
this cube with a remaining three I have
three choices
yeah
uh any other questions
it's very important to be able to cancel
this counting correct
uh it's also very important to get all
the science projects
correctly um
okay uh
you know in textbooks um in uh can be in
this kind of graphs uh often you will
find in textbooks we will talk about
symmetry factors but graph
um I would rather not to uh rather not
introduce that uh at least not for now
uh because I think it will just uh give
you because I'm actually confusion I
mean there's an easier way to to get
this kind of kind of a territory factors
not by laborers the accounting number of
ways to contracts but by studying the
order of the automobile group of the
graph but I don't want to Define that
because I think I've just introduced
some extra activities so let's just do
this the contraction which is really a
clear way look at least when the graph
is not very complicated it's very
complicated uh you might want to you
need to use web Theory but I'm not going
to need that in this course
uh
okay uh so uh of course this integral is
Elementary you can discover the integral
uh but I'm going to rewrite this
integral a little bit to make some of
the properties more manifest
okay so uh the first thing I'm gonna do
is to write every G 0 here using this
Fourier representation and this will
turn out to be always often very
convenient for calculating this let me
write you this I'll write this as uh so
minus G over two so I'm going to turn
every g into it
so this looks like maybe no cover time
for now but there will be a payoff later
uh so uh so each one of these so there's
a k the K Prime K double Prime so we'll
be right like that so d k so the first G
becomes DK over two PI right uh and then
there's the DK Prime over d p i uh uh
and uh uh uh
um
okay double Prime now these uh arguments
these time arguments we're going through
the exponential here so you see you have
this times e to the uh
e to the I uh okay uh Prime so this
comes with that guy that's for the
playoffs who was this perfect first
um and then we have a factor of feature
that let me just write this down in the
exponents we have personality so the
iPad coming some primers of that
um and then we have for the second
second propagator here we have e to the
i k Prime uh Tau Prime
all right
foreign
okay so first of all uh actually uh
look at this interval here of course
this K prime it doesn't appear in this
exponents
okay just duplicate Prime mineral
unfortunately chord just get back to
this that's kind of trivia this G zero
of zero is a number it's number is equal
to exactly one half so we actually
didn't have to write it out but I just
wanted right in this uniform way for
reference uh but the reason that you're
seeing it in a second but of course that
that one easy calculate
um and uh and then
we can uh interchange the order of pay
and tell Prime integral if we integrate
over top Prime first
um you see uh it's going to produce a uh
two times a Delta function uh right so
because the Tau Prime only appeared in
exploded integrals are over top one each
of the uh okay P to the i k Prime minus
K times Prime I'm just going to get the
two by times the Delta function the
Delta function will set K Prime to be
equal to K
so the result
so let me just uh continue to calculate
this so what we have is G number two
times uh responding one half this one
half this comes from just G zero of zero
so it is f that takes care of the K
prime a double primary table and then uh
we have the uh D Tau Prime integral E
power primary control uh is going to
give us
the e to the minus i k l prime plus
Prime is going to go too high Delta of K
minus 10 run
we do that we can then get rid of the K
Prime integral or nothing with physical
Decay over 2 pi and over here which is
how K Prime set to okay which until the
k
um
uh squared
uh let me just plug in the explicit
expression now so 1 over my K square
plus 1 squared
uh and then I'm still left with this is
um so uh so that's the result uh now I
mean of course you can try to uh
some more Premier function
um but as you will see for the reason
itself be kind of clear
um later today uh very often uh we don't
need to do that very often it's actually
more convenient to work with the whole
example of expression so so just look at
this 50 Grand here it's going to give us
all the information that we'll need
um uh but let me uh give you a kind of a
uh you know a diagrammatic shortcut or
whatever's answer in fact once you get
familiar with this it's not necessary to
write out all these steps you'll find
that it's always the same set of steps
it's very easy to arrive at this
expression without actually doing all
that
um so
uh what you can do is to look at this
graph
um so once before you transform you can
associate every leg every propagator
with this weight number okay later in
the field Theory context uh this K will
turn into something that would call the
momentum but for now this pay is just a
wave number that is the employee
transform of the variable the point
that's a little different parts of town
okay so so this you write hey here
associated with this this this problem
here here you have a k Prime
all right so remember the K was uh you
get my boyfriend will be the first
propagator that's this guy here K Prime
come from a boyfriend comes in the four
extension from the second propagator and
then and then we've got a k double Prime
um and the drop of the tower the Tau
Prime integral and the tile Prime is
theory
uh what do you tell a primary do we
produce some Delta function this Delta
function is set K to be equal to K Prime
uh actually if you think about think
about this whole thing uh generally well
that's how Prime integration does is
that it says the total number of this
wave number okay okay Prime whatever but
flow into this vertex that will add up
to zero so if you interpret this case
I'm kind of momentum it's not really the
momentum of this model but
later we'll have something with momentum
field Theory uh this just says that the
momentum is going to served at the right
expert so that the K is the flow in
equal to the K that flow out
uh that's it so you know if you if I get
confused about this rules just always go
back to the formula it's everything
would derived no I think
[Music]
um
so uh any questions about this
yes
so I have this factor and this factor
that identically give us one over K
square plus one squared
because remember the G was the one over
K square plus one
okay
all right so so the smarter this is
two-factor on the property and then I'm
just left with this exponential
everything else happens without friends
okay
oh yeah
uh the direction uh the direction is
always uh uh well uh well you see uh
there was an orientated to begin with
right this one's gonna tell mine is how
Prime this is how primary two so I just
do take a nice uh up to you right
because we're just putting label on the
graph it really is that's that's what it
is right so so you you pick one
conventional orientation but then it
takes this one scroll so let's say you
know our convention it's always going in
um so you know
and style prime before you transforming
this way we're gonna put the arrow
always going to come this Tau Primes
just pick One Direction
so evolving in yeah
yeah
okay any other questions
all right so
um
um so that's a that's an interesting
computation uh we're going to understand
the interpretation of this uh in a
moment uh now
um uh is more instructive for you to do
this more complicated yourself than in
the class and indeed uh these three
graphs are left uh in the home right so
that's the problem one problem a uh
it's a really not that difficult uh but
you know these are
um it might look difficult it might look
complicated anyway first time you see it
but once you play with this doesn't work
it's really going to be quite
straightforward and it's important to
get familiar with this uh with this kind
of manipulation because uh you know
we're going to encounter a lot more
sophisticated version of this in the
field Theory where we have to worry
about you know the regularization some
of these kind of terms of all that if
you're not familiar with the basics okay
the massive you can do is
foreign
uh okay
so uh so okay so that will be uh
um but uh but what is the general
structure so let's get to some idea of
the of the general structure
whether you you get by signing up this
kind of graphs so as we said
um the full uh result at least to all
other in this copy Factor G is supposed
to be calculated by uh the sum over
all the connectors
graphs like this
you know harmonic acid in the theory
um so let's think about let's try to
organize it just a little bit even
though the sum of all graphs will be
fairly complicated as you might imagine
um uh there's a there's a useful way to
to organize this so for example we
always start with the problem
you know
um and um
uh and it's possible that uh uh it's
possible that uh this this wrap uh well
connected uh might separates into into
the district
that uh you know uh it might be like
pumped up here sometimes yeah but
there's a line
um now I'm going to convince you in a
moment that you can't indeed organize it
this way uh in terms of new more
Elementary building blocks
okay so and uh and so forth
um uh so I'm really declare that
actually you can think about all they're
going to connect graph like this in the
following way there's something that I
did not by one Pi this will refers to
the shorthand for one particle
irreducible
um so what does ybi stands for what
stands for is that this is a graph
but my definition is defined to be a
graph that cannot
be
disconnected
um
[Music]
okay so so for example uh so for example
uh if you look at this graph that we
have already seen
I'm just looking at the the thing in the
middle so not counting the external legs
so over here the only thing I could cut
is with that but if I cut it uh it's
still kind of still connected
or if you look at something like this
because
any one of these internal legs or the
propagators uh in this stuff is still
connected so that let me buy one
particle are used
a graph like this of course uh will not
be one part of original because if I cut
this this one separate into two parts
but the claim is that you know
uh I can photographs by this by taking
all the possible one particularly
reducible graph one of the eye graphs
over there one paragraph over here they
have one line coming out and uh and I
form a graph like this and then the next
I can have detail uh and yeah I uh
one of the eye and it ends another Cube
and and so on so forth you can imagine
um uh what is that so every time here
when I draw the 1pi I mean the sum of
all the possible one particular
irreducible graphs that connect to these
two external points
uh is are people is everyone convinced
that all the kinetic graphs have been
represented in this way no objection to
this formula
yes
why yeah I guess uh wow so far uh no
reason uh so far that's to say that
again I can't dig them both into a
simpler transitions uh but uh but that's
the reason you'll become clear in just a
moment so these things will have
important interpretation
um but for now this is something I can
do with the identity that's true yes
when I come over like this when I came
to draft speed but
the second the first second order one we
just got them right now I'm sorry which
one are you referring to the first one
the first one yeah that's right this one
is not ypi right because this one will
fall into this exactly
[Music]
why is that
um it's because uh well let me uh
all right
so
um if you calculate the Fourier
transformed version of that uh two point
function
um all right so according to our
rule of the flow of this wave number
okay
momentum right it sounds like this
all right so whatever that is doing
inside uh there's some code that goes in
here that's the same thing out this is
going to blow out here okay
um so
um and uh so the result of a a graph
like this if you actually use the rules
that we have at this y to calculate uh
we're just going to get the product a
bunch of identical
identical factors Each of which is going
to be a function of K they're all the
same function
all right in fact
um so for example
uh this this first guy here
this one let me this one as we know is
the G zero this was the harmonic
propagator
uh now the next one is this guy
well
uh whatever it is you know there's going
to be some um
[Music]
so whatever it is uh it's gonna come
with a factor of G zero here and the
factor of G zero here
um well that's really imagine the
providers and
um well if I read this in in terms of
the Junior's house I'm not taking
particular product because
but if I look at the what extent from
the whole thing then uh organization I
just have 0 because okay yeah I just
have an apartment user available
through this this rack for the reason we
explained earlier when that's the result
of integrating out all these Primes
universities inside this the scrap
um so the result of this graph is just
going to be a g is going to be General
tilde K uh time well squared times some
other function uh okay let me call it a
sigma okay the sigma K is the result of
calculating uh the uh you know the the
information over the internal wave
number okay Prime whatever you have uh
associated with all the graphs like
something together okay whatever it is
it's going to give it a stop option okay
but if you know that by Sigma okay
um but if you know what Sigma K is you
will know the next one
this one
uh the
all right this one the four examples
okay uh
you have two factors
and from this and so on so forth so just
add every every time you add another 1pi
you're gonna you're gonna get another
Factor
together another packet of Sigma okay
so the whole thing
so the whole thing would be uh
uh so uh
this thing which is our let me give this
name let me call this the bolt space g
uh
this was uh this is
how
zero it's very evaluated I defined right
inside of the word uh in the I'm
harmonic Oscar Theory at least return G
um so this is supposed to be so what we
learned now is that you can show your
reputation you know there's the detail
number two Pi is row e to the i k Tau
uh of the sum of all these things
and so forth and the sulfate in the
geometric Series so this is
n from zero to Infinity okay
uh the same in the pay
with n power
with no extra commentary patterns
professional just one uh and N is the
number of 1pi bubbles appearing here yes
why why is
that down there the bottom right into
graphs yes so in that case the 1pi
bubble represent the sum of these two so
when I have to write about the eye I
mean the sum of all one bis with these
two legs coming out
good
uh any other questions
all right uh so uh now we might as well
do the sum because that's very easy to
do you want to know how to do this
geometric series
so the result
is um
so the result is that both page G of tau
is integral Decay over 2 pi e to the I
can tell
okay
saying okay
right so we let that be right in that
way but you remember so recall that uh
two zero code okay for us is the one
over x squared plus one so you can
describe this as
this whole thing as an integral being
paid upwards of Pi e to the i k Tau uh
e to that I K Tau over
all right
um
and uh just to uh remind you uh once
again hey how would you actually
calculate my pay so
um
so here Sigma k
um is uh conducted by the one pi
uh graphs the sum over one over one all
the one there graphs let me say that uh
you know
uh
without
including without the external
uh
obviously though of course you have to
draw the line here uh but uh we actually
accomplished Sigma K we don't take an
account of this GTO the zero on the
outside right that's that's how we
Define it
without wisdom come so this this
external probability that is
okay so
um uh usually uh we often refer to this
as a amputated graph in the sense that
um
uh in the sense that this external legs
are removed
uh and if you uh in our Theory
write it out as an expansion you see
it's just the sum of this Plus
the next order we have this and uh and
this
um
again without external X right uh and
and then energy equals
it'll be sum of all of that
but but they don't they don't repeat so
you like because
the this diagram for example we'll just
do already so this is not here
that we want
all right
uh any questions so far
yes the person one was like two with
like if with some with the middle ground
do I have to do like cases where like
the first Tower
yeah yeah I mean you know it all graphs
uh as long as my congratulations
we have this and Minnie Mouse I don't
know the cactus
so I would consider like cases of like
where like um
like the base vertex is which of the
towel because we have like all prime
double Prime uh doesn't work every every
vertex will come with an independent
power parameter uh and they use the if
you use the uh display type of
representation you don't need to
integrate of the entire access anymore
but you have a conservation of this case
and enemy vertex foreign
um
uh so uh the first web we have already
calculated this was this minus G over
two times four remember uh we are
stripping off the problem right so so
for the sigma K actually it's just the
pre-pack this man the jewel report
that's the first
so this this graph just gave us this
number minus 0.
uh and the sum of these two graphs uh
you can calculate so uh so this was
times
okay so your homework exercise the part
of it is to to recover your systems
um all right
um so
um uh so let's uh uh so that was
concludes about uh this analysis uh what
have we learned so far uh
we have learned that the we're outside
two-point version function if you had Q
hat in the AHA Market
or Theory
right so this one all right bone space g
which was integral okay uh okay
okay
is of the form uh one over
K squared plus 1 minus Sigma K and it
will be uh
so minus let's say plus G over four
minus G squared over eight uh
plus nine uh plus uh calculating
um now uh why did I
um
um okay you see uh so why did I sum up
the geometric series I could have said
that you know I'm just gonna take this
whole thing and expand to this whole
expression expand in our G and start at
G Square Order uh now I found the parts
over summation right you see what I'm
calculating here uh even though I'm only
I've only done a calculation after G
squared order explicitly you want to do
this this part is let's see
um and uh but it actually secretly
contains
because
experience in series right
you don't have any more diagrams for
example
um diagrams like uh like
like this one
this diagram will be happening in Canada
already
not everything but uh it's a lot more
than what you would just have a second
one
okay so that's Point number one but
that's uh you know you're gonna say that
well why is that special
diagrams so what's the big deal that you
have can't calculated some but not not
the rest
um uh well okay so here's the point uh
what is the uh
um but let's say if you're interested in
studying the energy Spectrum or the and
harmonic acid the most basic observable
in quantum mechanics
um as we said before you can extract
that information from
um
uh from this two-point variant function
so let me remind you that uh Spectrum
Edition
several times what does it look like
um
so we know
uh for instance that
um
this guy here you have how
things really value this is seriously
that's the same as that's for uh that's
how greater than zero right uh this one
as we have to before can be decomposed
by inserting a basis of energy eigen
space normalized
um so that this looks like uh and value
Q sorry and measurement of two and zero
zero there's another one with a zero and
switch a q is a few thyroid permission
so this is the amount squared a lot of
times e to the minus E N minus e0
the information of the difference
between the excited States and the
ground state
we said this before
so that's the same function where
calculator
uh now so how would you read up
information about the energy spectrum of
your polynomial system from that
employee representation at the first
look this is pretty weird
uh because uh
as you see
uh
as function now or okay there there we
have some function Tau in the smaller
transform right but what function of
cloud do we have what have each of the
ik power K the real by definition this
integration are very okay
the the exponent here an exponent here
are totally different
okay
uh so how can that be
right the time is in different function
well first of all there's no
contradiction because nobody says that
uh you know uh they cannot be too into
or some representation of the same
function one over integrated or some
over real exponents the other one
integrated over imaginary exponents so
there's a contradiction we might have
seen the example of this an example we
have seen before
was that uh in fact I wrote this just uh
earlier today
all right
um as you might recall there was an
example we saw that integral Decay we're
going to Pi of each of that I came down
over the K square plus one was equal to
one half e to the minus power of the
value so if you take account to be
positive it's important is this right so
you see here
you have e to the minus Tau the left
hand side you have e to the ik power
only star 99 exponents but they're equal
there's no problem
but in general how how did you how do
you read off you could have expression
on 11th time how would you know uh you
know what kind of exponent can appear
okay well we discuss this rule I think
the second lecture
uh well a simple way single trick to do
that you use a controller right so we
saw that as you recall from our uh in
the second lecture the left hand side if
you think of this as a contour edible on
complex territory
as a pair of bows
one above the real axis one below the
real axis right higher the minus Pi or
the okay okay
and uh if power is greater than zero so
this whole thing is explanatory
suppressed at large uh positive
imaginary k
then you can close the Contour
on the upper half plane and represent
this accountable integral and you treat
the Contour and pick up the revenue uh
and I can do this
so uh the lesson of that simple example
was just that if you have this integrand
or this shape
if it's sufficiently suppressed at the
Infinity on the upper half plane let's
say and you have some hose uh then uh
the results in the country is equal I'm
just gonna every call is gonna give a
residue that looks like each of the some
number of times down
in this case it is
okay so uh now we can play the same game
with that
in fact uh it does not require uh
to this so what is it what do we expect
um
yeah this is
the version of that right so we're just
correcting this
is
one of our character plus one uh but now
has something much more complicated
um
but whatever it is
uh we expect since the system are
probably about is just one mechanics in
the particle one being in the potential
the bouncing around like this right
energy levels
yes so whatever it is whatever the GK
data is you're invited the summer row
very complicated graphs we could do a
few of them but whatever it is the whole
thing has to integrate into something of
attackers
um so uh so how could that happen well
uh you know what was it the only way
that this can happen is if
um
this uh the complex
okay
um we're gonna find is that so we'll
have this real integration Contour
and that's how we Define that integral
this way thanks one but
it must be
that so I'm gonna be agnostic
about what having the law happens this I
don't really care I mean the focus on
the other half planes because that's
relevant for for the combination yeah it
should be positive okay we can discuss
what happened Lord helpline but that's
not relevant for our current newspaper
so
um whether it is I must have some
sequence of posts uh this post must be
uh as a positive imaginary values of uh
okay interesting because only if the
codes are as positive Imagine by the
okay when I calculate the residue I'll
get e to the minus something times the
power the something is about the real
number
just like in this example
uh and in fact if I find a oh study off
that foreign
so then it's not surprising that this
particular pay has to be someone
complicated because they have to have
infinite number folks every poem
correspond to a possible and the dragon
states that has measure overlapped with
two hands yes
whatever the case
that's correct because in that case as
we have as I have comment down before
nothing more
that's actually indicate the harmonic
and you know it could happen written as
a very annoying operator
but that's not true
this will have overlap actually uh
because there was a parody symmetry
with that first excited third excited so
all the odds
foreign
that's also why it was uh kind of useful
to sum up the geometric series because
we're going to be asking okay the
question of where are the posts is ask
where the denominator vanishes all right
um if you if I did some of the geometry
series you will never find the post at
least if you're translating the
perturbation here during the final order
you'll never find folks because uh you
will you will in fact you have made a
mistake you had said you would have
thought that maybe the polls are still
at uh you know okay he goes bye because
you have one over K square plus one well
the thing is that you have you have a
whole series when you restart the series
you find the post position would have
been shifted
is our easy to deduce because you know
in the case of the harmonial center uh
you see one pole for the reason we just
said
um and that one will probably get
stripped a little bit as you pronounce a
little bit interaction well where is it
shifted to well it's not hard to receive
from that formula right so
um so uh uh
uh
uh at uh let's say uh okay it was so
okay hi
uh this corresponds to the person
uh excited state
excited there's faith
of the uh anthemum
um
and uh you can just see uh
what is the value so you know you can uh
you can uh so so what is the value uh
close to it goes to I uh which is
another advantages and uh but okay you
have to have a little calculation
because well actually it's not it's not
so hard to do because uh
um you might worry about this um
if you expand around K close to I the
correction must be opposite t uh so any
correction to this away from K plus I
would be higher order
G and so to G Square Order you don't
have to worry too much about that and
the result you'll find this corresponds
to the call
is
trying to figure square root and G over
H minus G squared over 32 Plus
so this correspond to uh in other words
the Gap e y minus e0
all right so so from this we conclude
that um
the result of this little calculation uh
will tell you about other things this
can take more information than this
energy Spectrum but in particular you
can learn about energy Spectrum you
learned that the gap between the first
excited state and the graph State I had
an expansion uh one for the harmonic
operator and then the Restoration in G
and b square foot
okay
uh and let it reminds you for doing
nothing but you know a good old you know
undergraded quantity campus so far so
you could have replayed reproduced this
results from coming per Direction here
in second order or if you want you can
just forgive a plug-in value of G that g
equals 0.1 and solve the shortening
equation numerical you must recover the
answer is consistent with this so uh you
know if you do anything about all this
path in the world magic uh you can
always check the answer using other
methods
number two will be vastly more
convenience for filter generation yes is
the scariest trixology
uh the the series in the powers of g no
it does not converge
um it does not converge uh for
there's a very simple intuitive reason
why they converge uh it's just that well
it's not the readers written name but
they gave us why you may not converge uh
you know if it converts it'll be
something function for small G
um if we converted to black or answer uh
but uh which will behave so it wouldn't
be similarly for g75 or something but
you know for that one we have a system
if you have a g time to keep on the
fourth potential with the sign language
from below so something will not become
catastrophic right
Progressive so so that's the hint why
you don't actually expect this thing to
converge
um that does not mean this proximation
doesn't do anything in fact there's a um
what you can still understand that the
proclamation is still a good
approximately after some people order uh
that is just compatible they provide
that to you small
um but that is the discussion that I
will not get into
so
um any other questions
okay so um
uh that's all I'm going to say about
harmonic uh
I'm going to uh one more example notice
I don't have much time so I'm just gonna
tell you what the example is uh and
we'll discuss it uh uh analysis next
time which should not take more than
half a lecture and that will actually
we'll be doing generally good theory
um so uh but the reason I want to
explain the third example is uh have to
do with uh
something that will show up over and
over again in in the continuing field
Theory right so
um so thanks for example we'll discuss
is again following mechanics
yes what can I do with one mechanics
with Vladimir Freedom well uh let's
start with uh let's go to the ground
here for the harmony officer and I'm
gonna add a interaction term okay so
previously added and keep the four uh
now let me consider something different
I'm going to add a term like this uh
minus some coefficient it's still called
it g because she had nothing to do with
our OG this is a new Theory the new
model right uh it's not important to you
I encourage you over eight uh Q squared
uh Q dots
okay
all right
um I'm allowed to do this you know
lagrangea mechanics right because
they're like only mechanics actually uh
normally says
the queue will could be any generalized
coordinates I'm allowed to redefine
non-linearity what my general coordinate
is and the all the ground equation the
classroom mechanics will be completely
boiled right so you're allowed to use
whatever quantity you want the franchise
your mechanical system for example uh
for the rigid three-dimensional rigid
body you can use some other coordinates
doesn't care there's all equipment yes
what happens is
uh uh well uh I'm gonna say this with a
sign of genes ah and also I'm going to
treat it for terminally so so let's not
worry about
uh
uh okay
um and uh so um so you know in general
we have a connection like Q Power Square
if you make a relational variable not
linearly your produce a parents just
like that uh
anyway
um so let's look at the ham intelligence
what's the time I'm telling you well I
can write a hand in terms
this is a step in the learner transform
uh as uh somebody to do this you can do
that
um one minus G over four
to this way
um and so by definition
is Q dot P minus l
but subject to a replacement of Q naught
replaced by the expression in terms of
the T right so
imagine that
um and if you're just plug in calculate
and express the result in terms of a b P
what you find is one half y minus G over
four Q squared
inverse these words plus one half this
one oh I said how many other correct it
in some way but you're correcting the
kinetic term
all right
um so this is
um so uh next time we'll discuss the
quantum version of this now you already
see it is
going to be some celebrity
perspective uh you're gonna have to
worry about ordering of these and q's
so there's some pleasure ambiguity we
mentioned this before so so
um and not surprisingly you will imagine
that end up happening on LeBron James
when you contact you to the passenger
World there'll also be some kind of
ambiguity
uh we'll see what happens next time is
that uh if you're not evenly just
calculated this kind of climate diagrams
as we did today for these kind of
correlative functions uh you'll find
some divergences you'll find that this
uh okay integral will give you different
cities
um but you know the time you know it's
perfectly good times
yeah so
um
um so so there's a bodycon mechanical
system
um uh but but you will find some
divergences in this video diagrams
uh and we'll see that how that will be
resolved uh the resolution will have to
be that you have to carefully regularize
the pattern well you have to cut off the
range of integration in the momentum
we've had to add counter terms all of
that will be uh familiar and see it over
and over again is build theories uh but
in this case
you know you know that it's a good
mechanical hamiltonian there cannot be
anything wrong with it provided right on
Hamilton yeah so there has to be
sensible answer right so so you know
even though this is lagrangian having to
grow you run into some naive learning
some infinities you know they're having
result in some way I will learn how that
will result
I don't know
um
NOTE END VIDEO 3VG2kDHso08
NOTE BEGIN VIDEO 6: TtMNnZ8__UU (2022-09-22)
NOTE JSON3 SHA-256 1d9ebae0a4096f9c5fb33865475f274fe8880804dd3a6a0353e87f8747da55c0
NOTE VTT SHA-256 b5e8f48f52c4f732d88d99f91cc74341a84bce2780dc6002926268299171714e
Kind: captions
Language: en
yeah
all right let's get started it's a short
one though
yeah I think okay let's get going okay
so uh recall well we and we're gonna end
it at that time uh I'll welcome to a
certainly uh let's pass in the group of
the following lagrangian uh still for a
mechanical system with one degree
freedom and the Branded uh want to have
uh Square minus one half two squares
G Q squared uh Q thoughts word
um now uh uh I come in last time that uh
you know this kind of a queue depends
again
all right now uh in fact as I uh at the
end of lecture notes uh uh which I
didn't write on the board uh last time
um in this case is Dr tossable to uh do
a redefinition of your generous
coordinates Q you're trying to compute
some other coordinate you can't absorb
this term into the into the standard
camera so you could do that
uh generally uh with more than one
coordinates uh it's not always possible
to absorb uh this kind of Q dependence
into the static electron without the Q
dependence in this with us for our time
um but I do not want to discuss in more
General case uh just to avoid uh having
to write more you know copyright format
on the board I'm just going to
illustrate the point with a simple
example even though in this example
I could have absorbed uh let's turn by
by definition if I do that every
definition you've got to check you can
absorb this understanding turn but then
I'm going to get a correction to this
potential term and the new coordinates
which looks just like the Animal
Hospital okay so um if you were to do
that at a classical level the classic
mechanics it's in quite this model quite
similar to it
the physical results uh to be that
different
um for the for the quantum theory uh but
we're gonna try to proceed and and uh
the quality Theory defined by the
pattern we're going to see what happens
um and uh once again to avoid some
complications with factors that I and
ordering operators and so that's we're
going to uh do the weak rotation and
work with the uh euclidean or the
lagrangea
um so this Q uh
um uh and uh I will write to euclidia
around you because minus L with this
stuff so I could do a challenge
Q squared uh and this variable is going
to have the same sign so a G Q square is
all right so
um so this will be the equilibrium what
we're going to be working with
uh and uh once again we're gonna expand
uh perturbatively in G
um uh say for the of durable that is the
two coin foreign
space language in terms of those two hat
operators and for now uh with this uh
with that that understanding I'm just
going to compute function around
uh and uh and the rule is uh uh is clear
just like last time uh the only
difference the last time I had the Q to
the board now I have a Q squared the
power Q squared so it has to change the
vertex a little bit but apart from that
the graphs the final graph that we're
gonna they're gonna contribute to this
two point coordinate function uh is uh
pretty much the same setup perhaps with
some additional decoration because you
have the crack of this so I'll tell uh
and which we'll do now all right so uh
so this will be given by so first of all
we still have the harmony propagator g0
now remember this was some functions one
half e to the minus two absolute value
but I'll just uh I won't plug that in
before the moments
um and then we still have graphs like
this
right we'll have a single vertex
okay so
um now uh uh well they're g once again
we still have a single graph like this
but let's look at whether this guy is
in terms of the actual uh formula
so
so this map
uh let's calculate
um so this way more questions
we got a few towel
um uh two zero well let me let me
provide a q zero and on the right hand
side just to match with it because there
is that one release it's not important
uh and we're expanding each of the minus
capture each other it's minus so there's
none of minus 10 there two minus signify
cancel okay
[Music]
Prime uh
squared
um so we have all of this inserted by
the way instructed this graph correspond
to remember there's a connected with
concussion okay so according to the
graph the pattern of contraction is that
this Q is going to be contracted with
one of the cues here this cubic time
with one and Q is here and another pair
of Cubes here I can cut it but
um but uh when I choose this graph like
last time all the four series two powder
identical right so we have some
commentatory factor four times three yes
you might recall
um now they're not quite all identical
some have derivatives some don't have
derivatives so I actually have to uh
uh count them separately okay so if I
just join this graph is nothing up here
so so
yeah yeah I have to uh do this a little
bit more carefully but but we can do
that so uh in order to do that we just
have to remember
um
that uh
in writing this vertex
uh each of the leg coming out of the
vertex represents one of these cubes uh
but two of them have a derivative on it
uh and I can choose which one whether
the one with the directive or without
you or to be contracted with either this
Q or that kid
all right so so I can represent the
derivative by uh let's say a little uh
um uh blue uh robotics little blue uh
over here
um and so for example
here so each one of these represents a
uh Prime uh
so that's one possibility uh and then of
course you can produce the others uh so
there's you can also put the blue the
derivative on these two lines or
uh again
two more possibilities
and so I can
do this
um I can
also for this
um well actually
right I also have I can also do this
um
but I think that's all the possible ways
to sprinkle the two derivatives uh on
these uh
okay
uh any questions so far
um all right so um
uh let's uh let's focus on the first one
we've got the first one is gonna uh
let's see it's gonna be the one that uh
looks a little bit problematic to the
others are more or less going to be
standard
um in fact for example uh if you think
about oh okay let me just write this out
so see more explicitly what you point
out
um so uh for this pattern of
construction this corresponds to the
situation where uh uh where um these
queues outside are contracted with the
queue here without directly and then we
used to get back with
so uh so this diagram is calculated by
the following weekly practice and Q
Power Q 0 and G over H integrals through
Tau just write this down two top running
u sound Prime and d q cell Prime d q r
Prime
uh and uh the pattern of contraction is
that so please do with the derivative I
can practice with that two
and then that's it so so this is the
only these are the only instructions
that correspond the graph of this uh of
this
any questions so far
okay so now let's let's plug in
calculator this is equal to uh G over
four times integral of e power Prime so
this gives us a factor of G the
probability power minus Tau Prime
uh
right uh these contractions give us a
factor of G zero of uh
is
a level of interactions
remember and of course the two zero was
actually a function of collapse of
values
uh but uh but
what what is this what is this
um so for that let's just do a little
calculation because this is totally
obvious but it's just uh you all you can
do is to separate those uh two times
let's say you consider two power one
which is
that right uh so what is this word
contraction
well this might be trying to do the same
as the variation of derivative of that
power one derivative we write the Tau
two of the contraction uh one two times
two these are the same thing okay
why are why there are the same thing by
definition okay
you should definitely derivative right
so derivative like a difference of two
power two with q52 plus Delta Tau two uh
but you know
uh two if I shift the argument here
that's just a different variable in the
functional integral and the way the
contraction is calculated is exactly by
the same propagated
all right so so uh so these are my
definition identity
okay so the result of this is just
detail one detail two of G that one L2
which is G and power minus times two
zero
uh and of course uh this is the same as
um
the same as minus 0 to the power one
by one minus R2
okay and uh and then I take the limit if
I take limit uh two going to Tau one so
that these two times the euclidean times
go inside like that I just got minus
zero
and that's the result
um any questions about this manipulation
here
this will be true for any kind of
working contraction here
where this yeah this is from uh uh you
know professional calculus right okay
okay yeah
any other questions there can you
explain again the first line where you
can fill up like the explanation uh
right so uh what is let's recall from
freshman calculus this is defined to be
a limit okay let me erase it will
understand that uh
two minus two l two over the other one
um now uh
right uh now
you know then I just calculate the
contraction of of this Cube and this Q
which is the other two separately
because these are different variables
yeah every time if I have a shift to the
argument out this is just another
variable all the q's house were
different measures how are are infants
are the variables in your functional
integral so they just contracted
independently of each other and then I
take the combination the result is the
same as taking the derivative of the
contraction
uh well uh all I'm doing
is that you compute this as a functional
too and then take a limit how to go into
Tau one
uh uh that's right this is the viewer so
I'm using the partial rotation but it's
just a single variable of course this
means that I take the derivative of this
function entice and set as argument to
zero but right that's the usual notation
okay so uh so that's our result here so
uh we're very welcome thanks I will
write down the answer minus partial
squared uh G zero of zero
um okay so but of course uh as we uh
have said before uh it's uh last night
and it's important convenient to write a
four-year representation of that
um and so let me do that right
everything in terms of is four year uh
um representation which is a bit
convenient because uh it's uh it's
directly tied to this uh picture with a
momentum flow so I'm going to pay going
in
here and uh over there and the
convenient thing about the point
reputation is that you can just
integrate out this power Prime variable
and all that does is that it implements
this conservation of the K that goes
into
there's Vertex or Edward vertex so so uh
so to repeat the same exercise a lot I
mean Prime uh from these first two
factors you're going to get into the ik
pal over
um K squared plus one uh squared so let
me just remind you that this Factor one
over K squared plus y squared come from
these two propagators in this four
years-based representation right last
night and this is how this comes along
with the right
um but then uh there's this additional
Factor here which I can write in
employee representation uh as integral
of DK Prime over to Pi
um so uh K Prime Square that's one that
would be the case uh it would just be
that if I didn't have this derivatives
that's what we had last time but now we
have the derivatives uh and if you go
and rewrite this in the representation
you find that the derivative just gives
you a factor of K Prime squared in the
numerator
I I mean you know
recall that uh yes
the point of repetition of that so take
two derivatives
on this you just get a backup minus K
squared but the minus signs of getting
that to get a backup K squared okay
Prime squared in this case uh and uh and
they start out to zero
whatever you call it
um all right so so that's the result of
an integration range is always reminds
me into Infinity by these days
uh any questions so far
okay now let's try to calculate let's
try to evaluate this while you have a
problem uh this is Divergence
um
this integrand goes to one in both
directions
well uh of course it was Divergent
because you should have complained
earlier this guy here is going to be
fine remember our two zero
of Tau
was one half e to the minus value you
can plot this function right
L to zero Tau uh it looks like this
so if you take the second majority of f
equals zero uh it's infinite
a little question that's what you see
from the polio repetition as well
uh okay so we encounter something bad
right so so this this thing is this
thing here is infinity
foreign
um numerically
um so uh so what is going on what what
is uh we have done something wrong okay
so what did we do that was wrong
right and yeah
proposal
I think everything will happen
this expression is identical to that
extent
okay so uh
so what was wrong
um well nothing that I wrote on the
board the calculation was completely
correct
um
uh so uh
but you know why is it that uh well you
know you had to think about the source
of Divergence it came from
doing this book contraction of this DQ
and how to do queue and go time
um and um a clear more clear way to
track down the source of the Divergence
is in avoid architecture so the boy
impatient I didn't write this explicit
on the board uh but we can track another
transformation of cube I wrote this in
the lecture note that was posted so you
could directly level in the Fourier
transforms for you right
um so you can write a few town to be uh
some uh okay
[Music]
there if you are too likely to grab it
yourself
um but um
uh the uh origin of this uh so from that
perspective
um the origin of this beverages is from
the integration at large values of K
Prime
uh and that has to do with the
contraction
uh the word contraction of this audio
mode of Q
um at large wave numbers
uh why do we have this contraction
equation of the larger wave numbers is
because in the path integral we have
this measure
uh and
uh this measure the way we actually
calculate in the Fourier space as you
have seen in the first problem set
um you can uh abdominalization this will
just be integral e to Theta k
over all wave number okay
but as you have seen it did in the first
problem said even with harmonica
oscillator sometimes
you only calculate uh this uh maybe
it'll be fine unless you regularize
after all mathematically this is uh this
kind of integration is not sensible
unless you in terms of independent or
integral by cutting off let's say the
wave numbers in this case actually a
wave numbers would be continuous but uh
you know the homework uh you saw an
example with numbers were discrete and
indeed you can first Realize by cutting
it at a large wave number and you
calculate the physical observable of
interest and homework in the partition
function and at the end at the end of
the day when you have responded quite
normalization you take the color of
infinity and that would sensible answer
so in this case uh you might uh want to
do the same thing because otherwise uh
you know there's no guarantee the path
of the goal was
um you know well defined in the first
place so uh so let's uh do we always
have to regularize
sometimes we get away with not
regularizing we're lucky but generally
you always have to regularize
um and uh so we can verbalize by say
cutting off
um there's
um weight number of 40 amount of view
that appears in the pathogable measure
some large number uh and only do this
um and then hope that at the end of the
day when you calculate some physical
variables of interest you might uh you
might end up with some quite as a result
but there's no guarantee of that at the
stage uh so but let's try
all right so if you do that if you
define the measure uh with this
organization then uh the effect of that
is every time you do the weight
contraction you're always going to
integrate in the momentum in the
frequency space you're only going to
integrate okay up to that
so of course if you do that uh that will
turn this integral uh into into a finite
integral
um okay so so if you regularize uh
if they regularize uh
with this
shut up
uh then uh you're just gonna
so here you're gonna integrate every
time how to learn
um and of course that's going to make
this finite but uh it's still going to
be a number that is for the lamba and
when land is large this number is so
large but uh but at least it's an
expression that's uh that's mathematical
sensible and we can try to proceed and
calculate physical observables of
interest uh by the way I should say that
uh uh now uh
we only have one of these diagrams but
you can you can verify for yourself I
wrote this introduction uh
that we posted
um but it's not hard to verify that uh
the same kind of diversion does not
occur in any of the other diagrams this
is the only diagram that has discovered
the other way I said uh you have to
divide by another cut off by then I
could get away with it so we haven't
Define this way and we can see what it
makes sense again
the original integral was over all the
pain
uh well we'll see yeah
okay
all right yes
in general will the actual time
um
uh uh well it's better not if your
theory is defined if you have fun behind
your system uh it better not matter at
the end but that's not guaranteed at the
state
but I'm having a population kind of
obvious it's about management
um all right so but let's proceed well
you also an example the homework that
you did get away with in that case we'll
see what we're going to get away in this
case it's not obvious
okay uh so uh let us for example let us
inspect the common sequence of this on
this uh two-point version I saw was
intimately applied to the energy
Spectrum of the model
the spectrum of having someone
and so for example we saw that last
night at this 2.4 later uh is what I
call this voltage G of how and this was
a really uh a metaphoria representation
uh Decay because
over a plus one minus this is okay on
the second one k remember this was
calculated by the countries diagram
[Music]
s everything is
um by the way uh this Sigma K and later
we'll see the quantity context this has
a uh
for it it's a very poorly uh cells and
terminology it's called self energy uh
in the current context uh this name
doesn't have any
is
um and um
we saw this last time so yeah
we calculated and we calculated leading
uh contribution to this right so um
uh what we saw was that uh this uh
signal okay as weather G
uh
uh receives the contribution
uh the contribution from this diagram
uh
well we please talk about another
several diagrams but the other diagrams
are finite those only one is the
Divergence so the Divergence would be
diverted contribution uh which is which
is this quantity here that is just that
just G over four uh
this Lambda over I
stand that number this is the Divergence
well this will be diverted if you remove
that we will cut off and that uh This
plus something finally
okay
uh no uh well at the end of the day we
do need to take that Infinity
um and this skill looks problematic
right because uh we said last time that
actually uh the the pose of this
integrand which is the zero of the
denominator
advantages as some complex actually
period imaginary K uh that this sequence
of posts on the upper half complex carry
plane we explained last time there are
some of the actual energy levels of our
model okay I'm telling you
uh so this will contribute
to the actual energy crisis with energy
levels or the first excitation energy
and if this diverges that uh looks bad
yes
you're gonna get uh
the land is large you can get something
that emergencies but like it's too
Lambda right this is
the rest will be fine
we're not going to worry about that but
most of you are concerned about the
Divergence because this thing to be uh
English inconsistency of our formula
okay so so uh so something is wrong
actually uh we end up with the basically
the answer doesn't make sense
okay so what did we do that was wrong
well uh this was actually the thing that
I wanted you at the beginning when I
discussed the derivation of the passing
for performance sketches
so
um I said that there can be ambiguity of
order H bar in this LeBron they try to
produce the correct exact connection
uh so so far we've said always said H
bar to one but it's useful to restore H
bar just to be able to keep track of the
uh the H bar dependence and uh and where
where the what are the functions versus
the classical contributions so the path
to the world when you play a signature
or sorry in this rotated version uh it's
a it's a I'm going to restore this H bar
um you find this here
um
well
uh do you believe the End come on Jim
um and uh
like that actually
um we know the the model is defined in
this way with us
uh lagrangian myself
um but there's a possibility that in
fact
um there could be a order H bar uh some
other H bar corrected to this uh after
all you know all we know April is that
this thing has to reduce the classical
LaGrange H5 to zero limit but who says I
cannot add some term of order is
zero this will still go away so I should
still go away
um
uh our goal is to
we want to have it I want this particle
to reproduce the physics of some
hamiltonian I want to fix the Hamilton
but you saw the hand intelligence is
also a potential ambiguity that's
wondering the p's and q's when you
contacts and these two are potentially
tied together by the relation the
precise relation is not obvious
um and let me find out another issue
which is also closing related which is
that uh uh you know I don't really know
that the measure is just exactly this of
a constant Factor what if the measure
has some acute dependence uh in fact if
you think about uh I made a guy in the
beginning that you could have made in
non-linear redefinition of variable
deals so they're going to turn this into
more standards around you which is two
thousand square credit cards we're going
to change the potential turn this into
something more like an harmonic acid but
if you do a non-linear here we
definitely some Q which of course you
are free to do in classical mechanics
the path in the world
you are going to introduce the Jacobi
the factor itself behind something
now you could imagine so let's say oh
but then we made a mistake
well actually you can even correct for
this mistake because the Jacobian Factor
get written as equal to something but
something is going to be some functional
of cube that could be written as an
integration compound because there's one
for each time
okay so this uh if you have a drink okay
Factor you could have imagined uh
Curriculum
by uh in second way that you restored it
correctly
well what would impactor look like uh
yeah
something in the exponents will have no
h bar dependence
so that was going to precise the quarter
H bar term
okay so what what H5 correction can
potentially account for the Jacobian
Factor right we would have missed if
that were the correct definition of the
model right so uh generally you don't
you just don't know if you start saying
that you know if you divide the model by
just saying that I'm going to quantize
this lagrangeas
happens your apron agnostic about you
know what are those possible recovery
factors right maybe you can take it to
do this but maybe that's not correct
definition of the model so you have to
figure out exactly what are these bar
Corrections
uh luckily in this example we have the
hamiltonian will provide them to assist
us to uh you know
it should be you can always try to do uh
the uh lagrangian to arrive at the
correct uh physics that matches with MSW
that's one way to proceed of course you
might say that we're going to defeat the
purpose in particle but so far we're
just trying to understand how the
formism works and
um
um I'm trying we can use the hamiltonian
as a guidance
um so uh and indeed uh okay so now uh if
we restore H bar where would H bar sit
in all these uh uh calculations of the
correlators
uh well uh in fact you'll find uh that
you find the a square
up there uh that just comes along with
the right
uh but then in the calculation of
um uh you see uh let's do uh
uh it's easy to see why you have H bar
up there because uh in the player space
you have a case k square plus one for
numerator and when you have like the
Gauss integral remember you invert the
coefficients that's the code the case
one plus one the numerator gets inverted
it's one over K bar plus one but this
one over H bar gets inverted into the
back of this box we have the H bar there
um and uh
uh and then
um
yeah if you calculate uh the diagrams
you can get the fact of H bar from this
property probability that is far from
here there's some H bar from here and uh
there's also a spar from this propagator
and then you've got one over H bar from
the vertex because you're just expanding
the
the financial purpose it comes back up
on the page bar
um and uh at the end of the day this
term compared to that term acquires one
attribute so it needs to cancel it
requires one extra packet
but but then remember we're summing up a
geometric series to get the expression
like this so in fact in the self-energy
this thing comes with the factor
of H1
so
anyway this is the idea to restore the
HR Factor you just remember where it
comes from
um but the point is that uh the question
now you can ask yourself is it where
April were agnostic about the possible
or the H bar correction so this
lagrangian is it possible that we choose
a specific term
here uh you have to cancel there's this
Divergence
um now and maybe you can do that uh so
um very important for instance
so the idea now is that we're going to
uh modify
to look around you
so uh we're going to Mommy bye
uh we're going there by adding
okay
time somebody's going to call the
counter term
context all it is
whenever I see the word counter term
what it means is that it's a term you're
supposed to include in the lagrangian of
the regularized
right the counter is nothing but a term
in the LeBron James uh but there's a
term that you uh may not have guessed
staring at the the classical expression
but in order to Divine the quantum
uh in the world uh with this
regularization uh you have to also
correspondingly modify the ground yet uh
by some kind of term the idea is going
to be that you know here you've got the
Lambda dependence the counter may also
depend on Lambda in such a way that the
other day he chose down him correctly
you take down to Infinity the physical
answer uh will have some kind of
well-defended
all right so uh let's see
um so the contract what would it be well
uh let's try it so uh so
um
let's try and development upon a term uh
now
um
order in G so far at order teaching the
first order it would have this
Divergence we want to cancel that
perhaps with some common term so let's
try it so some coefficient C we'll
figure out what it is times G
um and whatever it is this
bar for it to make sense so because it's
supposed to represent a Quantum
correction to lagrangian that will go
away in the classical element
um uh and uh let's just use let's just
sign this excuse whatever
so it's uh it's something proportional
to Q squared so this is like uh
correcting the frequency of the harmonic
oscillator itself if you wish
all right
um so uh
okay uh well it's very easy uh to
understand the effect of this uh because
all you are doing
this yeah you you can there's several
ways to do this you can either view this
as a Vertex with only two lights coming
out but we don't have to wire go through
all that exercise again because you know
this just this is a term that similar to
the term already appeared in the
original uh uh remember this was one
half
oscillator right so in the back of this
at least well the effect of this adding
this term is simply that you're gonna
replace this K square plus one it
replies to a square plus one plus uh
this solution H Bar C G
right so and that's that's very easy so
so we see that there's Sigma k
now what does this look like this looks
like
um well uh we're going to we're going to
get the correction and pull your H bar
um G
um
uh so uh
uh we saw right here that we have this
uh uh
last step over uh for pi
uh there's some uh finite stock uh this
one is that you can calculate this if
you want but I won't bother you know and
this part of the stuff is uh Hey
generally pay attention
uh I guess I raise the background now
but some of the other diagrams we are
finite I will give you additional okay
dependence but but uh but you know you
know I don't care about that too much at
the moment uh the the important Point
here is that if you uh
it's at this
um
uh well it's going to uh effectively
you're going to subtract from Sigma uh H
bar CG right so Sigma is a contribution
of this thing uh minus C
uh then that's it and uh and then higher
order terms of order G squared I wish or
not the duty at the moment
okay so so very simple so so the result
of having this kind of term is that
we're going to correct the self Sigma
self-energy but anyway shown having that
uh two-point function
um it's just another G is going to
correct this polar G term which is
really
an order H bar previously set the one
um but shifting this bypass
it's constantly being there the
professional content we're adding
um
uh so uh
uh the idea is now
we're going to uh choose
right so we're gonna choose
uh choose
if we choose C to be uh you know Lambda
over 4 pi plus some finite constant
and a constant
um well the C have to be constant by
definition uh but by our by our choice
so far that's how we're defining the
Strategic world when the fact you know
produces the right hamiltonian or not
that that's something we have to
investigate but I want to at least get
something that is that produces a
well-defined answer
you take a limit Lambda to Infinity uh
the result will be finite would be
finite uh but this is not very
satisfactory it doesn't seem very
satisfactory because uh
um
it's very arbitrary Finance number uh
right and you don't know a program where
the number is
at this level uh there is no way to know
what a number is because there's an
interest ambiguity how you define the
quantum here so to fix that finite parts
of the common term uh that's physics
that that's how you have to use some
other physical principle that with so
far uh do not know uh based on the
information of just this lagrangian
alone
okay uh if you have some additional
symmetry or something that might help
you in terms of accountable without that
uh there's uh we cannot pin down what
this model is
okay so uh that's the that's going to be
the status of this five people
now as I mentioned before uh this time
because you can have Metallica as well
when you try to contact the hamiltonian
and unless you without putting it down
what is the audio prescription there's
no way to sort of determine what this is
these things are tight one another
uh but in any case uh December right the
point here is that in order to Define
this happening world for this type of
lagrangea in this example
um we need to rationalize
we need to include the common term
uh this customer term might be Divergent
individually remove the cutoff so you're
supposed to Define
the particle by always regulating with a
cut off so the concept of dependent
cutoff and at the end of the day when
you do the conversation with the country
included uh you come to the physical
observables such as the sigma K or the
two-point query function and you take a
little Lambda capability at the end you
should restore a sentence that's the way
how you will Define uh the quantum
theory by happening
yes
so when we add this concept I can see
how you know we fixed this term in the
platform was no longer uh diversion in
the Islamic Infinity limit but don't we
mess up our lagration because now we're
LaGrange yes but the who carries were
like well actually it's not a technical
thing the physical things are uh you
know silver space I want to know whether
the spectrum of the states whether it's
very valuable the actual Department in
fact we'll see later that it could also
be the case okay so let me emphasize
that this important Point here
um so we want specifically Sigma K to be
to have fun and limit because it already
affects the actual values of energy
eigen values right so
um uh so you know it's thinking okay
they'll be fine then you don't have one
energy like a value so that would be
problematic it's now guaranteed that
this entire two-point function would
have people are defined because no
there's nothing sacred about the
operator Geo's path is going to be
defined for the package it could be that
uh the operator itself is still defined
but the difference from some work by an
operator by sometimes in the back
there's no reason why it has to be after
all you see these are all the H bar the
clouds are limited go away anyway
so there's nothing exactly about the
branch unless you have some critical
reason to believe that this term are
directly rate the physical observable
there's no reason why they have the same
finance and remove them regularly
uh and and also there's nothing sacred
about the operator cube right this
operative could have been receive an
infinite uh
the originalization but uh you know but
you know in the quantum theory the
quantum mechanics there always well
depend operators it may not be this
queue it may be
receiving that is also possible yes
um
uh yes of course if you change your head
like around you and you will generally
find a constant you'll change physical
Observer such energy levels so my point
is that you didn't know
is to begin with
at that order
this is
necessary yes
it's just kind of like oh I didn't say
there's a one-to-one correspondence I'm
just saying that it's a hint that
there'll be some ambiguity I'm not
saying that that's the only ambigued
uh any other questions
um okay so I said that uh you know in
this one mechanical system uh well
without additional principle some
additional symmetry whatever uh we
cannot really fix this in the final
Concepts uh after all in the usual
quantum mechanics uh if you're going to
propose hamiltonian functional use or
rather if you have a few heads uh you
know anything goes as long as it's a
conventional operator with the
foundation basic property like that and
if you can imagine any Quantum model you
want to get at any time you wanted to
have intelligence
um uh so in that context not much more
you can say about these common terms but
but a volunteer will turn out that
things are much more restricted uh
because I've read the visible account
and we'll see that uh in a large class
of field theories we're going to be
interested in uh in the squares and
very often this long terms are not
arbitrary and they are up to some small
amount of ambiguity they're more or less
all going to be fixed by the principle
of uh microcos Alex
okay so that's going to be uh the uh
well anyway that's that's where we're
going from
um and okay so uh I think with that we
are
finally done with uh this quality times
one and we're ready to actually do a
field Theory
um but let's summarize what we have
learned so far
um so with the Practical formulation so
we're learning we can do preservation
Theory with the family diagrams
um we've learned that you have to
regularize the past level you have to
add the contact
will be completely trivial in fact you
can probably already figure out the
roots to do from two even though I can
I've been quiet introduce your theory
yet but we'll do that properly uh next
lecture
um but uh
all you need to do is add some
additional variables special variables
uh and uh we'll see how that works uh
but before that uh just as a
um to prepare ourselves uh I should say
a few words at least about a classical
field Theory because I think uh perhaps
not everybody's uh coming to the stats
are uh familiar with uh
uh with a classical filter there's no
classical mechanics but actually a few
words about classical field here I think
in the uh old days uh you know students
will take a quite impossible skill
Theory but I think that that's standards
for this curriculum anymore so so I
should say a few words about uh
classical field Theory
um so
um
okay so um
uh
uh so all we need to do is to uh
consider classical mechanics but with
implemented degrees of freedom of a
specific type so so we're gonna replace
so so the classical
mechanics uh where we have this uh
generalized coordinates
uh we're going to replace this by uh
we're gonna replace this eye by some
continuous primary for instance they
could be some description X Vector like
so
lecture we're going to be interested
primarily in uh field theories that have
a random physics symmetry so later T and
X are going to be related by
uh from various symmetry learn
transformation
um uh and uh we can introduce asymmetry
in a way that's manifests at the level
of reaction
um so
um I want to emphasize that
um
uh here this x is a
uh it is going to be a label for the
coordinates the coordinates of this
mechanical system are the five
themselves
okay so at the instant of time
complexity uh you know the the the the
the dynamical variables are Pi where
this x is available you can use labeled
by the variables
um and uh as a matter of convention
um uh will be uh later always working in
uh indeed dimensional
we have CNN
uh you know space time
um where
they think of this x and the uh B minus
one
a dimensional Vector uh parameterizing a
special point and I'm always going to
write X mu to be uh
[Music]
ad summation of this Vector where this
x0 and the T are typically interchanges
sometimes I write x0 and to make learn
symmetry manifest sometimes if I want to
emphasize time Evolution I'll write a t
but unless otherwise say that this x
here and P are interchangeable
um
and so far I'm going at this point I'm
going to discuss uh Real Time with
Laurentian and Dynamics and the weak
rotation will play a role later when we
come to pattern
space
okay so uh and uh the classical
mechanics uh or the time evolution of
this field variable Supply will be
completely characterized by the action
so I didn't tell you what the action is
production with uh integral in time just
like in the ordinary mechanics but now
I'd have to also integrate in the
spatial coordinates of some laguology
intensity L
um that is the function of Phi of uh x
uh so so just be noted together as
Phi of x
if I have X without any label on it uh
it stands for this p-dimensional Vector
it's a 5x and have a partial mu Pi of x
um and of course uh if you adjust those
special integral this is what we usually
call that lagrangian is possible
mechanics but now this involved in
variables
um I should say that uh from the point
of view of lagrangea mechanics with
implemented degree of freedom and this
kind of thing this is not quite the most
General thinking right right there's
already some kind of a locality that
there's lagrangia this has some kind of
integral in this special coordinates of
a sound expression typically involve
only finding finally many derivatives
but at the same point
okay see this is already a bit
non-trivial there's nothing
that's built in um but if you want to
write a manifestive Lorent invariant
action uh is uh these are the most
General the most obvious part of action
to write down and we'll see that they
will indeed the right potential for
field theories okay
okay so uh
uh any questions so far
um now of course the equation of motion
In classical mechanics is still the uh a
variational principle that is the
variation of action we're back to
arbitrary the first father uh
zero and this function derivative
and uh so you know as usual if you
assume that the lagrangea is that only
depends the one that's the only
difference another person directed then
we can write the variation uh before
very
the first order the variable
so we can write the version of action
that's integral
in space-time uh well there's the
variation of Pi of x uh L by y of x
R and there's so many people are I mean
we usually like our red if you are
familiar with the rule of functional
variation
right
um
um now
uh the variation of the derivative of Pi
of X is uh by definition assignment
derivative of the variation of violence
um I hope this point is clear because
all I'm doing is that I start with the
pi of x i vary into a new five Max I
recall this Pi Prime of X I take uh you
know if I if I compare the derivative
before an after the variation the same
as the derivative of the variations it's
because linear personal advantage
turn the second term into something
proportional something to worry about
Parts assuming that that is uh Fields
playoffs are through passive Infinity
um
um and turn this into or maybe more
fantastic assuming that it's my
variation uh that is in fact Infinity uh
then
um
this
is
the motion to says that let's take up to
zero that would be the equation for
arbitrary of X that comparative action e
to the zero
um so so this is that this is also the
formula the ground equation for the
okay
um so let's uh look at uh the most
basic example
of this so we can take the uh
uh so the simplest example uh would be
uh three
uh scale the field
scalar yield right so we can take the
let's try to write down uh some uh
lorettes a variant expression uh so we
need a kinetic term
uh the character should look like uh d0
quite hot squared
plus five Factor one half just for
normalization
uh it should look like that no but we
want to make a lorency variant
um so this integration measure here is
valency variance as you might know
um
launching variant because the the large
formation Matrix this Lambda has
um
and uh so it's a Memory loans in very so
we just need to need this uh the Divine
identity to be a Lowrance uh covarian
expression uh and uh for that we have to
contract with indices uh in in a way
that man impersonates and the the way
the obvious way to do that is to replace
this
one uh
I mean you have seen this in homework
already and I'm always going to be using
a convention where this Matrix is that
of the mostly positive signature
before I mentioned like this
um so this has that genetic term of the
correct side
um and uh and then I can add some
potential term
uh the simplest uh
[Music]
I squared
okay so so that's the uh simplest uh
sort of non-trivial uh
density you can write down for a
relativistic invariance classical
filtering
any questions about this
um
so uh what is the equation of motion if
you follow the rule of the LaGrange
equation right the equation is important
um
uh you just very this we're about to buy
first uh you get so so the derivative of
L with back to Pi of x l at x with 25 of
X is that uh n minus M squared by
uh and the derivative of this with back
to partial meal of five is equal to
minus uh partial upper middle by
um and uh and so uh the equation motion
says that
um minus
R2 mu of Pi minus M Square five zero in
other words there's also usually write
this as the Box y minus n Square uh
okay
uh any questions so far
okay so let's solve the equation uh all
linear differential equations are
trivial to solve using uh
and uh so we can just write down all the
solutions
um
so uh the most General solution
the most General solution what do they
look like well uh
uh let's start with the foyer
transformed expression and let's write
this as integral
and V dimensional
let's say momentum variable just
momentum you just puts the name with
this variable doesn't mean anything just
some parameter okay new
integration okay
e to the i a valuations
uh at this point
um I'm always in the kind of a working
the Laurentian signature
um so this K is going to be some viewed
as a b dimensional Vector uh and
implicitly every time I write dot this K
dot of x
if this can actually viewed as records
in because I'm I'm always going to
Define this to be okay then I would
expect here my minus K zero with zero
the same as Theta lower mu Nu okay upper
mu X number I mean this is just a
connection
um to uh this will be convenient uh
working in the learning signature later
by to perform quick rotation I'm working
UCL signature the start will be replaced
by Euclid it in a product but right now
it's the Lawrence
this is just a definition okay I'm
allowed to always change the sign here
but we Define the variable anyway this
is the way I divide uh the convention
for the employer transform in the in
calcium space
all right and any question about this
there's nothing but the employee
Transformer back to each variable
independently but I can package it in
this way
uh okay so uh did you write this uh
what's the what's the solution to the
equation
yes
um
it's kind of like you know it's like
fine it's like and it's like I'm really
important
um
well uh you know if this will be you
would think that General you can yeah
like this the question should be a
constraint on app okay 40 seconds right
um
that's right so you think that you just
basic question right so you take this
and knock on that you get K square plus
N squared uh times uh F okay
uh I'll go zero
and that's the question all right uh
while you're gonna say that maybe this
doesn't have a solution if we're doing
okay but uh but there's a cash advances
that actually it was F okay
um where the biolence of interest in
this context applications distribution
so uh the segment of that
um so F of K F okay
okay is a distribution
to my other functions uh but it's
important support the meaning that
participating including that zero but
it's on the functions I can't really say
this value we're supported as uh kmu uh
beta can spread
this this constraint what you usually
called the mass shell
so it has to be something that roughly
speaking proportions of Delta function
in this time right
uh as long as so of course this
condition if you write it out this is
usually dispersion relation all right so
so that's just my understanding or
elsewhere plus okay squared plus N
squared equals zero uh so okay zero this
uh frequency the nine initially the
frequency uh the k0 is uh plus or minus
square roots of K letters squared plus
Cent squared and that's of course we
recognize uh uh would be the
relativistic dispersion relation uh for
a particle of mass m even though right
now I haven't said anything about
particle or mass and there's some
parameter that shows up in the LaGrange
density for this field very
um but anyway uh if you have a for any
distribution that's supported at the
mass shell this will be a solution
okay so this almost uh solves the
problem of time Evolution uh in this
very simple example but regulatory it's
very scalar yeah
um speaking uh this is not part uh
doesn't quite address the question of
time Evolution because the question
about time Evolution uh is uh really
about as we if I start with some real
configuration
zero what does it involve it
uh okay so that kind of answered through
this but I haven't quite answered that
question but we can do that
we can do that in the following way
so
um
so to fully solve this classical field
Theory uh we should address or solve the
initial value problem
um
that is to say uh so given
so what is the initial value problem
uh we need to capture the classical
state of the system and sometimes I
think of zero uh what are the parameters
we have to specify well in the cosmic
mechanic we have this no query that so
same thing here you have to specify a
fine by that
so to especially digital value problem
uh it's like saying given by at uh let's
say Time Zero but arbitrary spatial
position but that's not enough you don't
have to specify the time derivative uh
say B by DT of Pi times equals zero and
then so now I expect to my Q language
and that really is about to specify the
classical state of the system and they
want to determine it
positive p
so so that's the initial value problem
right that's what we care about In
classical mechanics
uh so how do we solve that uh well let's
just do the we'll have learned that this
is the most General solution and so so
let's expand
pi and table zero
using the general form of f of K let's
see what it looks like this looks like V
is okay so what we know is that uh
uh well the general solution
the genomics looking Pi of X we said
that it has to be uh supported uh on the
master
uh so uh that is Jose uh k0 and we're
I'm only here right k0 is determined by
K special Vector ocular PSI so the only
once you specify okay space a vector
there's only two choices okay for K zero
so we can say that Pi of X is uh
um integral in the Special K Vector uh
with some other function let's call the
top tilde of a special Vector
um e to the i k the three to Vector with
X rated Vector uh minus I uh so I'm
going to Define this Omega K so that
there would be square root of the base
where the second square plus N squared
that with a positive side to Omega K is
always positive
uh so I Omega k
X zero
so that's a one composite Solutions but
that's not all there's also some other
uh
uh minus E to that minus I well I could
have written plus here let me finish
writing and then explain this expression
so what I said earlier was um
right but I said earlier what about uh
the most General solution is of this
form uh that is uh K zero can be either
plus Omega K or minus Omega k
uh but now I also uh assume I guess I
didn't say this but biobex is a real
valued variable right x uh so for this
thing to be uh real valued I need these
two terms uh to be the complex conjugate
one another and three to always redefine
this okay so we prevented the minus
itself
minus itself
relax but then I know that this has had
to be the 100 than that
why do you know that
um
this this is the arbitrary there I I'm
always ready to redefine it I didn't say
this I didn't say that okay
it's just some parameter
so One Direction this way these two are
related back on this contribution so so
these are the most General Solutions I
can write in this way for some are now
really arbitrary function uh
Hey special Vector
um so now the initial value problem
uh
uh means that I want to specify Pi at
times zero and this time derivative by
time
right so so what are these uh the first
guy is integral uh the case special
Vector e to the I okay special Vector
topic with X ratio Vector of what uh
well I think I said x0 to zero and I
have this uh and so here I just have a
filter okay
back to there and plus F Delta star of
minus Theta
uh similarly if I take the time
derivative and then set due to zero
I just have uh
this
uh if I take a Time derivative
I uh yeah a factor of minus I Omega k
and then I have episode
minus until the star minus scalar
so uh now you see if I'm given these
initial values uh that specifies by
apply a transform uh both the plus and
minus mean a combination of f till then
until the star and therefore of course
the specified equivalent to the star
separately and once that is specified by
X is 25 and therefore the initial value
problem is solved at arbitrary time
uh any questions about this
uh okay so with that we have completely
settle the question of the classical
View at the time we also know this build
Theory and the writing to set the
quantum version of the theory uh we are
of course uh out of time
um let me just make a few comments
before uh getting to the quantum's
version here now this is the a very
simple uh free scalar Capital Theory uh
it's pretty in a sense that the question
of motion is reading and then there's a
look into things about the problem is we
almost finished as you can see here it's
easy to resettled by the boyfriend
um uh you could of course but yeah
classical filter isn't all that trivial
uh you know you can consider you know
non-linear propagation of waves there
could be some interaction uh term we can
add like by q five to Fourth and so on
and so forth when you have non-linear
terms
um you know the things don't just
populate according to this uh this kind
of uh simple
um dispersion relation uh and
furthermore you can have things like
solid pounds yeah you can have foreign
[Music]
we're not going to explore much of that
at the moment uh we're going to move on
to the quantum version of theory and
we'll proceed uh by two different
approaches of quantization I actually
person I should make a comment you know
we want to be vanished not every quantum
mechanical system of Interest come from
a stripper organization classes
for example uh you know particles with
the spin is not obvious how to get that
from a project system so a classical
business
uh go Theory but perhaps the most well
known example be that the permiance but
they're much more specific examples as
well uh but uh for now we're gonna be
studying the most straightforward most
simple kind of failed theory that can be
uh more or less understood by quantizing
a possible filter and we're going to
proceed uh by uh simultaneously with two
different methods of connotation one is
going to be phenomicalization which is
an operator and Builder space the other
with the pattern
they both have different they both have
pros and cons
Hamilton
system but as I mentioned before uh
lorative variants become manifest and
causality is not manifest the lagrant
information allows you to purely to
manifest the right variants uh but you
have the regulates and uh and that's not
always always and we will see how to
proceed with that standard
foreign
you know
NOTE END VIDEO TtMNnZ8__UU